<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="nosferatu_schema.rnc" 
       type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"
  ?>
<root>
    <script>
        <head>
            <title>N O S F E R A T U</title> by Henrik Galeen <note> (F.W. Murnau's hand annotations
                and scenes additions and location markers are in Bold Print) </note>
        </head>
        <act num="1">
            <title>ACT 1</title>
            <scene>
                <annot>8 meters location shot: Wismar</annot>
                <cam>Fade in.</cam>
                <loc>Townscape</loc>
                <cam>View over the roof's of a small old-fashioned town built in the style of the
                    1840s. The sun shines peacefully on pointed gables and leafy squares.</cam>
                <cam>Fade out</cam>
                <cam>Two shot, one from the church tower onto the town the other from the harbour
                    over towards the town. 1st: view of Lübeck. Dissolve to harbour of Wismar</cam>
            </scene>


            <scene num="23">
                <cam dis="4" sync="2">4 meters 2x</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in</cam>
                <loc>Outside a window</loc>
                <dir type="stg">There are flowers in green window-boxes. On the window sill a kitten
                    is playing in the morning sun. With graceful movements she tries to catch a ball
                    that dangles from a thread. Now the ball is being pulled in through the window.
                    The cat jumps in af ter it.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="34">
                <loc>Ellen's sitting room</loc>
                <cam dis="7" sync="2">7 meters 2x</cam>
                <loc>Small neat kitchen</loc>
                <dir type="char">The morning sun casts the shadow of a window frame onto the floor.
                    Ellen, by the window, is pulling the thread with the ball, the cat follows it
                    with a leap. Then she puts the little animal on her arm. Playing with it she
                    sits down on the window sill bathed in sunshine and looks out dreamily. She
                    squats on the floor opposite the animal and plays with it. Her dressing gown
                    moves in the breeze, her big child-like eyes a laughing.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="34" sub="a">
                <cam dis="20">20 meters</cam>
                <cost>Hutter white jabot blue waist coat.</cost>
                <loc>A small sitting room (attic)</loc>
                <dir type="char">Poor-looking and tidy. A bed, a chair in the period style. Hutter
                    is standing in front of the mirror. He is about to put his jack- et on. He
                    pauses to listen, takes a look through the side window. Smiling happily he
                    finishes dressing and goes out.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="4" sub="a">
                <loc>A small flower garden</loc>
                <cam>Shot from above.</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter appears, gardening knife in hand, looks up front of Hutter's
                    house beaming with joy. He finds a clump of carn- ations, cuts the flowers with
                    a quick gesture and makes a bouquet.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="5">
                <loc>The small kitchen</loc>
                <dir type="char">Ellen, still playing with the kitten, hears Hutter coming and jumps
                    up.</dir>
                <cam>Shot of cooker</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen comes over and begins to busy herself with the sauce pans,
                    with a childlike earnestness towards her house-wifely duties.</dir>
                <cam>Shot of door:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter is standing in the doorway and laughs and laughs. Hiding the
                    bouquet behind his back, he laughs and laughs</dir>
                <cam>Shot of cooker</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen turns around, catches sight of her husband and seems a little
                    ashamed that she hasn't yet made breakfast. Now Hutter moves closer to her,
                    looks into the sauce pan holds it upside down indicating that it is empty, and
                    looks at her reproachfully.</dir>
                <title>Ellen!</title>
                <dir type="char">She is sulking now and trying to placate him. But he pulls out his
                    watch; it is late already; he has to go. He kisses her good-bye, but she calls
                    him back again to confess that she hasn't got any money left to do the shopping.
                    He pulls out his purse with a sad look and holds it up: there is nothing in it!
                    They both sigh. He leaves with a heavy heart. The moment she is alone she takes
                    a small basket of potatoes, which is all she can find, the last resort of the
                    poor house-wife, and starts peeling them. A potato drops on the floor, the
                    kitten comes up and plays with it.</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out</cam>
                <dir type="char">They are rushing towards each other, Ellen throws herself into
                    Hutter's arms</dir>
                <cam>Long Shot</cam>
                <dir type="char">He produces the bouquet, hands it to her beaming all over his face.
                    She is touched then, saddening, she takes the glowers looking at the stems and
                    stroking them. His voice asks for the reasons of her behavior she says:</dir>
                <title>Why have you killed them ... the beautiful flowers?</title>
                <dir type="char">Hutter is taken aback for a moment. He apologizes and kisses her.
                    Then she forgives him, they stand in an embrace.</dir>
                <cam sync="2">Fade-out 2x</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="5" sub="a">
                <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
                <loc>Lauenburg</loc>
                <cam>Fade in</cam>
                <loc>Street with front gardens</loc>
                <title>Professor Bulwer</title>
                <dir type="char">Professor Bulwer is walking vigorously, yet slowly along the road,
                    enjoying the morning and the sunshine. His stick strikes the ground
                    energetically. Suddenly he stops and turns around. Who is following him in such
                    haste? Isn't it Hutter? He grasps the passing man by his sleeve; he holds on to
                    it. Hutter greets him, looking pleased. Bulwer laughs and looking deep into his
                    eyes says:</dir>
                <title>Why so hasty , my young friend? One reaches one's goal soon enough.</title>
                <dir type="char">Hutter, of course, doesn't understand him. He has to get to office
                    quickly. He greets him again and again. Until he manages at last to break free
                    with a laugh and rushes off. Bulwer stands there for a moment, then he resumes
                    the regular rhythm of his walk.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="6">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <title>Caption: Knock - a house agent</title>
                <cam>Fade-in</cam>
                <loc>Dusty cramped office</loc>
                <dir type="stg">Pale light is falling through tiny blind window-panes into the
                    strange room which is eccentrically decorated with bits of old-fashioned
                    furniture. KNOCK is standing at a high desk. People call him a house
                    agent.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">Knock's spindly hunch-backed figure. Grey hair, weather- beaten
                    face full of wrinkles. Around his mouth throbs the ugly tic of the epileptic. In
                    his eyes burns a sombre fire. He is reading a letter.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up The letter. On a sheet of paper decorated on the margin with grotesque
                    vignettes a medley of intricate and quite ill- egible signs.</cam>
                <cam>Med. Close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">Knock seems to be able to make sense of the strange letter, for his
                    ugly mouth sets into an understanding smile. Then he turns and opens the
                    door.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="7">
                <cam dis="5">5 meters</cam>
                <loc>Small room ad- joining the office</loc>
                <dir type="char">Very narrow and dark, totally without sun. Hutter, buried in files.
                    Knock looks through the door and calls him in.</dir>
                <annot>Another clerk is present</annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="8">
                <cam dis="30">30 meters</cam>
                <loc>The dusty and cramped office</loc>
                <dir type="char">Knock and Hutter enter. Knock points to the letter with mysterious
                    gestures and tells Hutter: </dir>
                <title>Count Orlock - His grace - From Transylvania wants to buy a beautiful house
                    in our little Town</title>
                <cam>Close-up Knock's demonic face with wide open eyes</cam>
                <title>You could make a nice bit of money . . . It will take some effort, however .
                    . . a few drops of sweat and blood. . . Perhaps a little blood .</title>
                <cam>Closeup</cam>
                <dir type="char">In Hutter's face expressions of mounting joy and strange
                    apprehension are fighting each other. Yet joy wins in the end.</dir>
                <cam>Long shot</cam>
                <dir type="char">Knock digs up and old atlas from the depths of the cabinet and
                    opens it. His finger runs over a page.</dir>
                <cam>Closeup The route from England to Transyvania on the map.</cam>
                <cam>Long shot</cam>
                <dir type="char">Transylvania? asks Hutter, his eyes suddenly shin- ing at the
                    thought of a journey. Yet Knock has turned back to the letter, now reading the
                    last page.</dir>
                <cam>Closeup The back page of the letter, covered with the same illegible
                    squiggles.</cam>
                <cam>Long shot</cam>
                <dir type="char">Knock seems to be able to make sense of this page too. He turns
                    back to Hutter who is al- ready day-dreaming about his journey.</dir>
                <title>He wants a handsome deserted house.</title>
                <cam>Long shot</cam>
                <dir type="char">For a moment Knock is lost in thought, then he has an idea. He
                    limps over to the window.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="9">
                <cam dis="4">4 meters Window frame, take in Knock</cam>
                <loc>Section of window View down the street The deserted house. A dilapidated
                    facade. Black and hollow windows. Not a sign of life. Shadows on it.</loc>
                <time>Daytime - Sun</time>
            </scene>
            <scene num="10">
                <cam dis="15">15 meters</cam>
                <loc>The dusty and cramped office</loc>
                <dir type="char">Knock walks back from the window and says to Hutter:</dir>
                <title>That house...just opposite yours. Offer him that!</title>
                <dir type="char">Hutter seems to be a little taken aback, but he rallies around
                    quickly. Knock urges him to set out on the journey at once, hands him some money
                    and doc- uments and pushes him to the door.</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out</cam>
                <cam dis="18" sync="2">18 meters 2x As in scene 8</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="11">
                <loc>Room in Hutter's House</loc>
                <dir type="char">Ellen is sitting by the window. Now she can see him coming. She
                    waves to him. Her face lights up with joy. She hurries over to the door.
                    Presently Hutter enters. Moved and happy, he puts his arms around her and tells
                    her his great news:</dir>
                <title>I shall go on a journey far far away to the country of mountains where there
                    are bandits and ghosts still.</title>
                <dir type="char"> Ellen is startled. A shadow passes over her forehead. She wants to
                    hold him back. But he is not listening. He has got to pack; already he is
                    leaving her.</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="12">
                <cam dis="15">15 meters</cam>
                <cost>Frau Schroeder without shawl saddlebags</cost>
                <loc>The attic room</loc>
                <cam>Fade-in</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter is packing his little travelling bag. Ellen appears in the
                    door behind him. Sud- denly she starts to beg him tearfully, en- treating: Do
                    not go! I am worried about you! But he rejects her remonstrations. Now he has
                    finished packing. He gets up. Ellen realizing that he has made up his mind steps
                    back, resigning herself. But there is fear in her eyes. Seeing her like this he
                    hes- itates for a moment. But then he embraces her again with determination,
                    takes up his bag and leaves the room with her.</dir>
                <cam>Fade out</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="13">
                <cam>15 meters</cam>
                <loc>(Lord)Harding's park</loc>
                <dir type="char">Hutter, all ready for the journey, takes his leave from Harding and
                    his sister Anny. Ellen, weeping is supported by Anny.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">The two men. Hutter, taking both of Harding's hands and looking
                    deep into his eyes:</dir>
                <title>I entrust Ellen to your care.</title>
                <dir type="char">Harding promises his friend to look after Ellen, she can live here,
                    she will never be alone.</dir>
                <cam>Long shot of all characters</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter gives his hand to Anny and then to Ellen One last farewell
                    kiss. At this moment her grief is over. As if she had a premonition she
                    says:</dir>
                <title>Farewell! There is no escape left.</title>
                <dir type="char"> At first they are all startled by these words. Then Hutter breaks
                    away. Another farewell, another wave of the hand and Hutter vanishes into the
                    park. Ellen is staring vacantly into the distance.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="14">
                <loc>Square with fountain</loc>
                <dir type="char">A number of healthy-looking people are walking about in the
                    sunshine. Tied to the fountain a lonely sattled horse. Hutter appears, mounts
                    the horse gives one last backward look and gallops off.</dir>
                <cam>Fade out</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="15">
                <cam dis="9">9 meters Schlesische Hutte</cam>
                <title>The Carpathian Mountains Wild and rocky mountains. Contre jour</title>
                <cam>Fade-out</cam>
                <time>Evening</time>
            </scene>
            <scene num="16">
                <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
                <cam>Long shot</cam>
                <loc>Outside the Carpathian inn.</loc>
                <dir type="stg">The big mail coach drawn by four horses drives up and comes to a
                    halt.</dir>
                <cam>Shot of door of inn</cam>
                <dir type="char">The inn-keeper, a small old Jew, comes out and sees the
                    coach.</dir>
                <cam>Shot of coach:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter jumps out first. He looks around.</dir>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="stg">The house. One part of brick-walled living area, the other coach
                    house and open stables Shot of coach In the meantime the other passengers have
                    got out. Long-haired, black Huzules. All identically dressed and of identical
                    appearance like ghosts. they go into the house. The inn-keeper has gone up to
                    Hutter and greets him with an inviting gesture.</dir>
                <cam>Shot of coach</cam>
                <dir type="stg">The horses are now unharnessed, the coach is being pushed into the
                    coach house. Night is falling.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="17">
                <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
                <dir type="char">servant: Frau Kurz</dir>
                <loc>Inside the Inn.</loc>
                <dir type="char">A large smoky room with an enormous tiled stove. A central hanging
                    lamp throws out dazzling light At tables in the background the passengers.
                    Hutter who came in last, is standing in the foreground, he looks around and sits
                    down right in front. At once the old servant approaches with a glass and puts it
                    down in front of him. He overcomes a strange anxiety that was brought on by the
                    evening mood in a strange country and puts on a sudden show of liveliness. He
                    knocks on the table and says:</dir>
                <title>Quickly, my meal - I must be off to Count Orlock's castle.</title>
                <dir type="char">The servant recoils in horror. The strangely identical looking
                    passengers, sitting in the background rise up abruptly to stare at him.</dir>
                <cam>Shot of bar</cam>
                <dir type="char">The old hunch-backed Jew pricks up his ears.</dir>
                <cam>Long shot</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter looks around in embarrassment, then takes up his glass
                    resolutely and downs it in one gulp.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="18">
                <cam dis="4">4 meters</cam>
                <loc>Walddorfsenke</loc>
                <loc>A grassy slope behind the inn</loc>
                <dir type="stg">The ground falls away towards the back. Night mists are creeping up
                    from the valley. The horses are put out here to graze. Suddenly, they raise
                    their heads, as if frightened and, scattering, gallop away.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="19">
                <loc>Inside the inn</loc>
                <cam>Shot of window:</cam>
                <dir type="char">The passengers, seen from behind are standing by the win- dow,
                    looking out apprehensively. The old servant has not go the courage to go up to
                    where they stand and makes the sign of the cross. Hutter stands alone, looking
                    around. He is perplexed and wants to ask what is happening. The old servant
                    comes up to him and whispers into his ear.</dir>
                <title>You mustn't go there now there are wolves about Spend the night here.</title>
                <dir type="char">Hutter understands and decides to stay.</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out19a</cam>
                <dir type="stg">Horses, panicking</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="20">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <loc>A room at the inn.</loc>
                <dir type="char">A tiny white-washed room with sharp angles: a flickering light from
                    the old servant's candle. Now Hutter enters. She puts the candle down, goes out
                    without a word. Her eyes expressing concern for him. Hutter alone. He goes over
                    to the window, throws it open and looks into the starless night.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="21">
                <annot>(missing from script)</annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="22">
                <cam dis="5">5 meters</cam>
                <loc>Inside the inn</loc>
                <dir type="char">The pale passengers, now without Hutter in the enormous room, look
                    frightened. They, too, are listening to the hor- rible howling. They look at
                    each other and are crossing themselves in terror!</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="23">
                <cam dis="20">20 meters</cam>
                <loc>The tiny white-washed room</loc>
                <dir type="char">In the light of the candle Hutter, shivering, closes the win- dow.
                    He is no longer sleepy. He walks up and down the room restlessly, stopping in
                    front of a little bookcase.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">Looking for something to distract him Hutter pulls out a book at
                    random.</dir>
                <cam>Long shot</cam>
                <dir type="char">He moves back to the candle, sits down on his bed and opens the
                    book. He gets interested in it.</dir>
                <cam>Close up The book's title page: VAMPIRE</cam>
                <dir type="stg">The page os being turned over.</dir>
                <title>THE NOSFERATU From the bloody sins of mankind a creature will be born which
                    will seek revenge for the sin committed by the parents and visited on their
                    children and children's children. Whosoever lusts after blood without reason in
                    under his spell, the spell of the vampire NOSFERATU.</title>
                <cam>Shot of bed Close-up </cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter, shaking his head, continues reading Book:...grown up on his
                    native soil - from which alone he draws his power.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Hutter shuts the book, having lost interest. It seems confused to
                    him. He yawns and puts out the candle.</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="24">
                <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in</cam>
                <loc>Small white room at the inn</loc>
                <dir type="char">Morning sun is flooding in from the window. Hutter wakes up.
                    Yawning like someone who has slept deeply but not well. He sits up rubbing his
                    eyes. They fall on the book on the bedside table. He reads the title</dir>
                <cam>Close-up VAMPIRE</cam>
                <cam>Normal shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">spits on the floor in contempt of the confused rubbish and throws
                    the book playfully into a corner. Then he pauses to listen, goes over to the
                    window to open it. He takes a deep breath of the morning air.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="25">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <loc>Walddorf</loc>
                <dir type="stg">The grassy slope in the morning light. Coachmen and grooms are
                    rounding up the horses with long whips and lots of shout- ing.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="26">
                <cam dis="5">5 meters</cam>
                <loc>The small room</loc>
                <dir type="char">Hutter steps back from the window. His eyes are laughing, as he
                    turns round. He stretches himself happily; then he takes off his shirt, goes
                    over to the washstand, pours water over his body. He has a proper wash.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="27">
                <loc>Dolny Kubin</loc>
                <loc>In the yard</loc>
                <dir type="char">The old servant, mother to all animals, throws corn to her
                    chickens. There are sparrows, too. Everything is bathed in sunlight.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="28">
                <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
                <loc>Outside the Inn</loc>
                <dir type="stg">The bustle of departure. The horses are in harness. The passengers
                    have got into the coach. Now, in the morning light, one can see their
                    differences. They are much less uni- form than they had seemed the previous
                    nightfall. They are chattering noisily to the people who are staying be- hind
                    and with the peasants and nosy children who are gathered around the coach.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">The coachman is about to climb onto his seat, but the small Jewish
                    inn-keeper holds him back: one passenger is missing. They look up to the
                    windows; angry about the delay the coachman cracks his whip a few times.</dir>
                <cam>Shot of inn:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter appears in an upstairs window, still only half dressed; he
                    gives a wave: I am coming. And disappears again.</dir>
                <cam>Shot of door</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter comes rushing out with his travelling bag.</dir>
                <cam>Shot of coach</cam>
                <dir type="char">He climbs to his seat on the coach-box, the horses start
                    moving.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="29">
                <loc>Outside the inn</loc>
                <dir type="char">The Huzules take off their hats. The children are waving. The old
                    servant has joined them. God bless the travellers. May he guard them against
                    evil spirits. They stretch out their hands as if warding them off.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter breaks into loud laughter.</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="30">
                <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>
                <loc>Westerheim</loc>
                <loc>A Mountain range</loc>
                <cam>Long-range shot</cam>
                <dir type="stg">In the distance a steep path cutting through the wild scenery, on it
                    the mail coach creeping slowly upwards.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="31">
                <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
                <loc>road to the Schlesische Hütte</loc>
                <loc>The mail coach</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
                <dir type="stg">The mail coach is moving into the setting sun</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">A coach window, and old woman. Hutter leans out, giving the
                    coachman a push with an umbrella</dir>
                <title>Drive on!</title>
                <time>The sun is setting</time>
                <dir type="char">Next to her another old woman, identical looking She is staring
                    into the abyss. Now the first one turns to look in the same direction: two
                    identical faces.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="32">
                <cam dis="4">4 meters View from Schlesische Hütte</cam>
                <loc>The rocky gorge</loc>
                <dir type="stg">Wisps of mist are rising and falling in the last rays of the setting
                    sun. Patches of sun and shade</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="33">
                <cam dis="10">10 meters Close to Arler Hütte</cam>
                <title>At the crossroad</title>
                <dir type="char">A carved madonna casts a long shadow across the road. Behind it an
                    old woman on her knees, deep in prayer. She lifts her head and looks down the
                    road. The mail coach approaches, the horses are pulling with difficulty,
                    breathing hard. She seems to ask herself: do they want to drive to the haunted
                    castle? and gets into the middle of the road to warn them off. The mail coach
                    stops. Hutter gets off the coach box. Now he stands at the crossroad. The
                    passengers are anxious to move on gesturing violently to him not to take the
                    left fork. But Hutter disregards their shouting He waves farewell with his hat
                    and walks briskly off.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Hutter walking past the carved madonna</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="34">
                <cam dis="8">8 meters Vratna Pass</cam>
                <loc>Distant mountains</loc>
                <dir type="stg">View through the cut made into the rock by the road into the far
                    distance. In the background the fantastic castle of Count Orlok in the evening
                    light. One can see a steep road leading straight up into the sky. Something
                    comes racing down. A coach? A phantom? It moves with unearthly speed and
                    disappears behind a ground swell.</dir>
                <loc>1) Castle Orlok</loc>
                <cam>dissolve</cam>
                <loc>2) Steep road between boulders</loc>
            </scene>
            <scene num="35">
                <cam dis="4">4 meters Near Schlesische Hütte</cam>
                <loc>At the crossroad</loc>
                <cam>Angle as in Scene 33</cam>
                <dir type="char">Mortally fightened, the coachman beats the horses. The old woman
                    has disappeared as if swallowed up by the ground. Astonished, Hutter follows the
                    vanishing coach with his eyes. He is all alone now, standing like this for a
                    while. Then he pulls himself together and walks resoltuely along the road on the
                    left.</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="36">
                <cam>Vratna Pass</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in</cam>
                <loc>Carpathian virgin forest.</loc>
                <dir type="char">The trees are castling long shadows on the forest path. Hutter
                    appears. He halts: what's that? Some- thing comes racing up, turns around as if
                    moved by a hidden force and moving jerkily. Stops dead. Hutter likewise. A black
                    carriage. No wheels? Two black horses - griffins? Their legs are invisible,
                    covered by a black funeral cloth. Their eyes like pointed stars. Puffs of steam
                    from their open mouths, re- vealing white teeth. The coachman is wrapped up in
                    black cloth. His face pale as death. His eyes are staring at Hutter. Raising his
                    whip he makes an inviting, almost commanding gesture. He waits. Hutter cannot r
                    ally enough strength to follow the invitation. Yet those eyes assert their
                    power. Step by step, as if pulled by invisible threads, Hutter approaches the
                    uncanny creature. He gets into the carriage. It reverses quick as lightning,
                    dashes off a disappears.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="37">
                <cam dis="5">5 meters At the Vratna Pass, behind Tyer Hora</cam>
                <loc>A fairy-tale forest</loc>
                <dir type="char">Empty. By the roadside a wise, man-sized raven. Its shoulders
                    hunched up. It turns its head listening. Then takes two hops forward and looks
                    down the road. Who's coming? The familiar vehicle sweeps up and past. A young
                    man, holding on desperately, sits inside, looking terrified. The raven follow
                    him with mocking eyes behind glasses.</dir>
                <dir type="stg">Coach drives at top speed through a white forest</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="38">
                <cam dis="5">5 meters Long shot of a snake- like bend.</cam>
                <dir type="stg">Valley. Deserted lane. Only a lonely twisted will-tree with a
                    straggly top can be seen. Again the carriage races past. Like an ancient man who
                    has been disturbed in his rest the tree looks after the vehicle with blank eyes.
                    Isn't there a grin on its mouth? Drives over stone bridge across deep
                    gorge</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="39">
                <cam dis="15">15 meters Poczamok</cam>
                <loc>Count Orlock's castle</loc>
                <dir type="stg"> The arch of a gate in the shade. The silhouette of the carriage
                    drives underneath it at a sharp angle and disappears in the moonlit spacious
                    castle yard.</dir>
                <cam>Shot of castle yard</cam>
                <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">The porch. The carriage stops in front of it. Al -most in a faint,
                    Hutter slides down. As if in a whirlpool, the carriage circles round him and
                    disappears. Hutter turns around and follows it with his eyes. He stands in front
                    of the closed gate, holding his bag.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Then, very very slowly the two wings of the gate open up. Somewhere
                    far back in the dark corridor a man can be seen standing motionless. He is
                    holding a candle which lights up his chalk-white face. He is waiting. Who is
                    that? Hutter bounds up the two steps and stands in the doorway. He would still
                    like to go back. Yet it is too late now. Hesitantly he walks towards the
                    stranger. Behind him the gate closes</dir>
            </scene>
            <title>End of Act 1</title>
        </act>
        <act num="2">
            <title>Act II </title>
            <scene num="40">
                <loc>Hall.</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">In the center Orlok, the candle in his hand. The walls of the hall
                    are plunged in darkness from which Hutter's back emerges. He faces the mot-
                    ionless figure. It is pale, ghostly creature with hollow eyes and thin mouth the
                    lord of the cas- tle himself?</dir>
                <cam>Close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">The face twists into a polite grimace. Sharp r atlike teach appear
                    over the lower lip.</dir>
                <cam>Medium Close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">They are now face to face. It must be the count for this is no
                    servant's gesture with which he now takes hold of his visitor's bag.</dir>
                <title>The servants are asleep It is almost after midnight.</title>
                <dir type="char">Hutter's clenched fingers let go. Bag in hand, Orlok turns around.
                    He holds up the candle and walks ahead. Hutter follows.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="41">
                <loc>Gallery of ancestor's portraits</loc>
                <cam>Medium Close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">One of the castle owner's ancestors , frontal view. For centuries
                    he has been asleep like this with his eyes closed. Now something approaches. His
                    eyes begin to move. Two figures are passing: Orlok and his visitor.</dir>
                <cam>Long shot panorama</cam>
                <dir type="char">He follows them with his eyes. They walk close to the wall where
                    portrait follows portrait.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="42">
                <cam dis="25">25 meters</cam>
                <loc>Dining room.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Gigantic dimensions. In the center a massive Renaissance table.
                    Somewhere in the distance a fire place. Flanked by two armoured figures. Black
                    and motionless. In older times this must have been used by knights for their
                    drinking bouts. Are these their armour? Is that long line that runs across the
                    wall a crack in the old structure? Or a lance left hanging there? Suddenly,
                    Hutter notices that the count is waiting. Quickly he hands him the plans of the
                    deserted house and Knock's letters. With a smile Orlok takes them and begs him
                    to take a seat. The meal is waiting. Hutter sits down. Orlok lifts up the papers
                    and studies them.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">Orlok reading. The back page of the letter shows a con- fusion of
                    numbers, legible and illegible letters. The holy number seven is repeated
                    several times. In between, cab- balistic signs. The spindly fingers holding the
                    letter cover up the rest like claws.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter is spell bound, his eyes wide-open</dir>
                <cam>Closeup</cam>
                <dir type="char">Over the top margin of the letter Orlok's eyes appear. He is
                    looking over to Hutter like a snake about to hypnotize it's victim.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter eating. He puts a morsel into his mouth. He lifts up his
                    eyes. His look turns into a stare. He is unable to swallow</dir>
                <cam>Long shot</cam>
                <dir type="stg">The hall with the halo of light in the center; the figures are
                    looming above the table.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up</cam>
                <dir type="stg">An antique clock with a pendulum. A hammer strikes the hour. The big
                    hand points to 12 o'clock.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter staring into space as if transfixed. After the twelfth
                    stroke he drops his knife and fork. The knife grazes his hand, it is
                    bleeding.</dir>
                <cam>Medium Close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">Quick as lightning the count rushes up to him offering his help. He
                    prevents Hutter from wiping off the blood. The knife might have been poisoned
                    The sticky blood should be removed from the cut. His lips are sucking at the
                    hand hastily. Frightened, Hutter pulls away his hand from his grip. He moves
                    backwards towards the fireplace.</dir>
                <cam>Medium Close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">By the fireplace. The Count is polite; he has lost his ghostlike
                    appearance. He is asking for something in a friendly, almost sad manner.</dir>
                <title>Shall we stay up together for a little while? It's a long time to go till
                    sunrise . . . And during the day I am always out and about.</title>
                <dir type="char">The Count sits down. And Hutter cannot resist his chivalrous
                    manner. He sinks back into the massive chair.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="43">
                <cam dis="18">18 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in</cam>
                <loc>The same hall</loc>
                <dir type="char">Hutter wakes up in the large armchair near the fireplace. He can
                    hardly remember the events of the night. The armchair opposite seems to be
                    empty. But there is light on it. Hutter's gaze wanders across the hall over to
                    the window.</dir>
                <cam>Shot of window It is very high and divided up into small panes. Morning light
                    is streaming in.</cam>
                <cam>Shot as before</cam>
                <dir type="char">An old-fashioned window. An ancient hall, very dusty. Nothing
                    strange about it. Hutter yawns. His eyes fall on the cut in his hand and he
                    remembers a few more things. What has he got on his neck? He touches his throat.
                    Must have been mosquitoes. A mirror! His bag is nearby on the floor. He takes
                    out his mirror and looks at his neck.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up The mirror shows two red spots on his neck, very close together.</cam>
                <cam>Normal close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">Why should he worry about a few little spots? he thinks and puts
                    the mirror away. He yawns once more. But suddenly he stops. What's this? He
                    looks at the table, astonished.</dir>
                <cam>Close up: A still-life of food: fruit, a joint, all kinds of gastronomic
                    delicacies.</cam>
                <cam>Normal:</cam>
                <dir type="char">He is overjoyed. He rushes over to the table and begins to eat as
                    if he were starved.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="44">
                <cam dis="22">22 meters Poczamok</cam>
                <loc>The dilapidated terrace</loc>
                <dir type="char">Still eating, Hutter steps out into the sunlight. He looks around,
                    seeming relaxed. He holds a sheet of paper and a pencil in his hands. Then he
                    casts about for a suit- able place and, leaning against the stone wall He begins
                    to write a letter.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <title>The beginning of the letter: My dearest, my only one. . .</title>
                <cam>Normal:</cam>
                <dir type="char"> Hutter stands upright, looking at the clouds. Why does that stupid
                    mosquito buzzing around his nose stop him from concentrating? He catches it
                    quickly. And now he knows how to continue. He puts pencil to paper again.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <title>Part of the letter:...the mosquitoes are a real pest. I have been stung at
                    the next by two at once, very close to- gether, one on each side...</title>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter keeps writing</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="45">
                <cam dis="14">14 meters Poczamok</cam>
                <loc>Forest near the castle</loc>
                <dir type="char">A man on horseback is approaching. He stops occasionally and peers
                    over to the castle as if he were scared of it.</dir>
                <cam>Outside the porch:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter stands there, waving with the letter. The rider comes up
                    cautiously and takes the letter without dismounting The he dashes off at a
                    gallop showing signs of great fear.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="46">
                <cam dis="15">15 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
                <loc>Dining room</loc>
                <dir type="char">Orlok is sitting by the fireplace bent over some plans. Hutter is
                    standing behind him. Orlok shows more interest in the young man than in the
                    papers lying in front of him. Looking over his shoulder he asks for some more
                    information. Hutter rummages among the papers in his bag. A little picture falls
                    on the table. He wants to hide it quickly, yet Orlok was quicker. He has picked
                    it up and is looking at it.</dir>
                <cam>Close up A miniature portrait of Ellen.</cam>
                <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">Orlock asks about the person in the picture. And Hutter is forced
                    to answer him.</dir>
                <cam>Close up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Orlok's eyes open wide. His lips look even thinner than before.
                    Contemplating the picture he whispers:</dir>
                <title>What a beautiful throat your wife has...</title>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter is breathing hard. The fear which grips him in the count's
                    presence is replaced by a sudden fear for his wife. He forgets himself and
                    reaches for the miniature. For the first time he touches Orlok's body. The count
                    jumps up. He raises himself to his full height with triumphant determination and
                    a glazed look in his eyes, and says, anticipating the horrors to come with
                    pleasure.</dir>
                <title>I shall buy the house... The handsome deserted house opposite yours.</title>
                <dir type="char">Quickly, he takes up the contract and signs it. He hands it back to
                    Hutter. Hutter bows uneasily and retires. Orlok watches him go, a satanic look
                    has come into his eyes. His hands have turned into claws. Hutter takes his bag
                    with him</dir>
                <cam>Fade- out:</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="47">
                <cam dis="15">15 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in: Candle is burning</cam>
                <loc>A small room in castle</loc>
                <dir type="char">Hutter is standing in the middle of the room, quite dazed. He
                    shakes off his misgivings. He decides to leave tomorrow. He kisses the picture
                    and starts to undress, when to his amazement he discovers a book in his pocket.
                    The old book from the inn. Did the inn-keepers wife put it there? Mechanically,
                    he opens it.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up: The book</cam>
                <title>Chapter II Night is the vampire's element. He can see in the dark which is a
                    wonderful ability to have in this world half of which is night. We humans,
                    however, are helpless and blind at night</title>
                <cam>Normal</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter shuts the book. A horrible thought has occurred to him. He
                    is feverish. Is it this book, these ancient walls which make him believe in the
                    existence of ghosts? Did not the count seem to have vampire-like claws and rat's
                    teeth. He jumps up, first running, the sneaking to the door.</dir>
            </scene>
        </act>
        <act num="2">
            <scene num="48">
                <cam dis="4"> 4 meters</cam>
                <loc>Dining hall</loc>
                <cam>View from door deep into the dining hall</cam>
                <dir type="char">By the fireplace Count Orlok, no, not Orlock but a gigantic
                    vampire, a motionless, sombre watcher in the night. <cost>Medium close-up</cost>
                    He looks at Hutter with a fixed glaze. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="49">
                <cam dis="6"> 6 meters</cam>
                <loc>The small room.</loc>
                <cam>Shot of door:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter. He supports himself against the doorpost. A ter- rible
                    realization has dawned on him. Shut the door, shut it quickly! There is no bolt.
                    No lock. He looks around, puts the heavy oak-chair against the door. Is it
                    possible to escape?</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <loc>Window.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Hutter rushes up and flings it open.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="50">
                <cam dis="3"> 3 meters</cam>
                <loc> Tegeler Forest</loc>
                <loc>Night. Undergrowth.</loc>
                <dir type="stg">A pack of wolves, raising their heads howling.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="51">
                <cam dis="8"> 8 meters</cam>
                <loc>The small room</loc>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter falls on his knees by the side of the bid. Hutter clutching
                    the bedclothes, he stares at the door behind which the horror is waiting. What
                    is this? </dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="stg">Moved by an invisible hand the door opens to half its width in one
                    single jerk. </dir>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter. Terrified, he covers his eyes with his arms, pulls at the
                    bedclothes and shields his eyes. He mustn't see it. He mustn't look!</dir>
                <cam>Fade out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="52">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <title>The same night</title>
                <loc>Ellen's bedroom at the Hardings</loc>
                <dir type="char">She wakes up suddenly. She has been dreaming. As if she had seen a
                    vision ... She has a premonition of danger ... Now she gets up. Moves over to
                    the window and steps out on to the balcony. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="53">
                <cam dis="6    ">6 meters</cam>
                <loc>Harding's study Night.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Harding is sitting at his desk. He hears a noise Rushes out.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="54">
                <loc>Ellen's bedroom</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up of door</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen is perching on the edge of the balcony. Harding leading to
                    the balcony rushes into the room. Discovers that the bed is empty. He shouts:
                    Ellen! </dir>
                <title> Ellen!</title>
                <dir type="char">He catches sight of the sleepwalker at the moment when, woken up by
                    his shouts, she loses her balance and falls over. He runs up to her and gathers
                    her in his arms. He carries her over to the bed. A servant, alerted by the noise
                    appears in the door. A doctor! shouts Harding. The ser- vant disappears.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="55">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
                <loc>The small castle room</loc>
                <cam>Long Shot</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter in bed, tense and doubled up. Slowly, Nosferatu creeps up on
                    him. Irresistible, he bends over the terrified and help- less man and buries his
                    fangs in his throat.</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out. </cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="56">
                <cam dis="7">7 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade in.</cam>
                <loc>Ellen's bedroom</loc>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen shouts:</dir>
                <title> Hutter!!!</title>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <loc> Ellen in bed</loc>
                <dir type="char"> ...in delirium. Anny is kneeling by her side. A doctor. Professor
                    Sievers, is taking her pulse.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Harding</dir>
                <dir type="char">Ellen trembles like a wounded bird. She doubles up throws herself
                    about and retreats into a corner of the bed.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="57">
                <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
                <loc>The small castle room Night</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">NOSTERATU turns his head. He is listening intently as if he could
                    feel - hear the terrified shouting in the distance.</dir>
                <cam>Long shot</cam>
                <dir type="char">NOSTERATU moves away from Hutter's bed. He dissolves into the air!
                    leaves the room</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="58">
                <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
                <loc>Ellen's bedroom</loc>
                <dir type="char"> Ellen is calming down slowly. Her terror turns into apathy.
                    Breathing weakly. </dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">She settles back listlessly into her pillows. Sievers can tell the
                    improvement from the pulse-rate and says to Harding:</dir>
                <title> Normal congestion of the blood. . . caused by an awkward position during
                    sleep...</title>
                <dir type="char">He has assumed an academic air. His beard trembles in his
                    eagerness. </dir>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="59">
                <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
                <loc>Poczamok</loc>
                <dir type="stg"> Behind a pointed gable of the castle the sun is rising
                    slowly.</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="60">
                <cam dis="7">7 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
                <loc>The small castle room</loc>
                <dir type="stg">The light of dawn is falling through the window as though a
                    sky-light and moving along the wall until it reaches Hutter's face, looking
                    half-faint -ing, half asleep. Suddenly he wakes up </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="60">
                <annot>continued</annot>
                <dir type="char">He starts up and clutches his throat. He jumps out of bed,
                    clenching his fists, runs over. To the door. Carefully ...he looks out</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="61">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <loc>Dining hall Daytime.</loc>
                <dir type="char"> The room is empty ...Hutter, pale and hollow-eyed, staggers in. He
                    looks around ...nothing. Shaking his head, fists clenched with wild
                    determination, he drags himself forward. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="62">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <loc>Portrait gallery with flight of stairs</loc>
                <dir type="char">Hutter is dragging himself along with difficulty. He goes down a
                    few stairs. At the end of the corridor he finds a door. He opens it.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene sub="62a.">
                <loc>A curving gallery exterior</loc>
                <dir type="char">Hutter opens one door after the other</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="63">
                <cam dis="15">15 meters</cam>
                <loc>A vault Empty and dark.</loc>
                <dir type="char"> In the center of the darkness a black coffin. Hutter has pushed
                    the door open and enters. He starts back. He stares without understanding. Fear
                    grips him. But he must make certain. Trembling heavily, he lifts up the coffin
                    lid. He recoils in horror. Dropping the lid, he retreats into the darkest
                    corner. For inside the coffin he has seen, black and long, the lifeless body of
                    NOSFERATU. Horror-stricken, Hutter almost collapses. Then he rushes out. </dir>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="64">
                <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
                <loc> Poczamok Vratna Pass Tatra</loc>
                <cam>Fade in.</cam>
                <dir type="stg">Sunset. Between a line of bizarre tree-trunks evening approaches
                    like a ghost...</dir>

            </scene>
            <scene num="65">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
                <loc>A niche inside the castle The small castle room.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Hutter is crouched on the floor. His body is twisted with fear. His
                    hair is standing on end ...his eyes are staring. Sud- denly, he starts up and
                    listens. Can he hear a noise in this desolate place? Could it mean his
                    salvation? With difficulty he drags his weakened body over to the window.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="66">
                <cam>Window frame for out-door shot</cam>
                <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
                <loc> Poczamok The walls of the castle</loc>
                <dir type="char">seen from outside Hutter stares from a window. He refuses to
                    believe what he sees. </dir>
                <cam>The crossbar of a window</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="67">
                <cam dis="6"> [ 12] meters 6 meters</cam>
                <loc> Poczamok</loc>
                <dir type="char">One can see a low-wheeled cart with the two fantastic horses
                    harnessed to it. And now: is it a shadow? A ghost. Nos- feratu. He is moving to
                    and fro, to and fro. From the cart to the castle. And back again. Carrying
                    boxes. Black coffin like boxes. From the back door of the castle to the carriage
                    He piles them up. Box on box. Into a gigantic pyramid. All this happens at an
                    uncanny speed. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="68">
                <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
                <loc>Poczamok</loc>
                <dir type="char">Part of the castle wall Hutter, staring at the phantom with glazed
                    eyes.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="69">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <loc>Poczamok Castle yard</loc>
                <dir type="stg">The carriage is now loaded. Suddenly the phan- tom jumps on to the
                    topmost box and dis- appears inside it. Instantly the horses dash off with the
                    cart at lightning speed. The big gate closes behind them with a bang.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="70">
                <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
                <dir type="char">The small castle room Hutter jumps back from the window. </dir>
                <title>Ellen!</title>
                <dir type="char">NOSFERATU is on his way. Ellen is in danger. He has to hurry. Save
                    Ellen. Ellen! Ellen!. Suddenly, he starts tearing down the wall-hangings and
                    tearing up the bedclothes . He tears them making long pieces and knotting them
                    into a rope. </dir>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="71">
                <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
                <loc>Poczamok The abyss</loc>
                <dir type="char">Hutter dangling from a window in the castle walls on a rope. But
                    the rope is too short. Beneath him, the abyss still opens up. And yet he risks
                    the drop - dead or alive.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up.</cam>
                <dir type="char"> So he hurls himself down. Hutter is lying at the bottom of the
                    abyss, between trees and boulders. Tossing and turning in fever and pain. So he
                    tries to lift himself up. But pain seizes him again. Then he faints.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="72">
                <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
                <loc>By the river Pruth Waag</loc>

                <dir type="stg"> The river flows majestically through the immense plain. The scenery
                    is bathed in sunshine. All is peaceful. Then a large raf t appear s around a
                    bend in the river and gloats slowly into view. Boatmen with long poles are
                    pushing it with considerable effort. At the stern a high pile of boxes. Black,
                    coffin like boxes. Stacked into a pyramid. An uncanny sight. Indefatigably, the
                    boatmen go on punting The raf t is coming closer and closer - like doom.</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
            </scene>

            <title>End of Act I</title>
        </act>
        <act num="3">
            <title>Act III </title>
            <scene num="73">
                <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>
                <title>A Budapest hospital</title>
                <loc>Hospital Ward</loc>
                <dir type="char"> A long line of white beds. In the foreground, Hutter. In bandages
                    ... his eyes closed. The doctor comes to him now. He examines him. Questions the
                    nurse She tells him about the case:</dir>
                <title>He was brought in yesterday by Huzules who said he had fallen down a
                    mountain. He is still feverish ...</title>
                <dir type="char">As the doctor continues his examination Hutter wakes up, opens his
                    eyes. There is fear in his feverish look still. The nurse hurries up to him to
                    hold him. Yet he crawls away to the end of the bed. Spreads out his hands to
                    defend himself. Suddenly his eyes go dead. He collapses. His lips are murmuring
                    something ... The doctor bends over to hear what he is saying. Hutter muttering
                    to himself</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Doctor and nurse look at each other without understanding.</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="74">
                <cam dis="18">18 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
                <loc>The port of Varna</loc>
                <dir type="stg">At the quayside, ready for loading, and next to other cargo the pile
                    of black coffins. Custom officials are examining the lettering and papers. They
                    are approaching the boxes. The man searches among the papers and hands over the
                    freight letters to his boss. </dir>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <loc>Freight letter</loc>
                <dir type="stg">Mixed cargo, from Varna to Whitby Content: garden soil for
                    experimental pur poses. </dir>
                <cam>Normal shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">The inspector smiles incredulously. He orders a search!! Barefooted
                    dock-workers drag up one of the apparently very heavy boxes, heaving and
                    swearing. The inspector gives an order. They open the lid with difficulty. There
                    is earth inside! The inspector gives another order: turn it out! The workers
                    obey. Sand is falling out nothing but earth . Satisfied, the inspector turns to
                    another pile of cargo. Yet in the earth . . .something moves violently
                    ...something is alive ...jumps out...horrible animals ...rats! One of the dock
                    workers, who bends over to scoop the scatters earth back hits out violently. Did
                    not one of the animals...reeling from the blow ... bite his foot? </dir>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="stg">The big hand pulley [steam crane] hauls up one of the boxes and
                    drops it into the belly of the sailing-boat that is anchored at the quay. At the
                    ship's stern one can discern a name, underneath the baroque figure head;
                    DEMETER</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="75">
                <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>
                <title> Professor Bulwer, a Paracelsian, explains the nature of carnivorous plants
                    to his students</title>
                <loc>The institute</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Professor Bulwer, surrounded by a few students, quiet and simple
                    people. They are listening to his lecture. Now he points emphatically to a plant
                    with a very strange shape. </dir>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="stg"> A flower. Its petals reaching out like tentacles. Motionless. Now.
                    And insect. Hovering, attracted by the scent . . . settles on the colorful
                    calyx. There in a flash the tentacles have gripped it. The insect is caught. Its
                    struggling is in vain. With irresistible force the flower has drawn it into the
                    recesses of the calyx . . . </dir>
                <cam>Medium- close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Bulwer pointing at the flower. Slowly his lips are moving:</dir>
                <title> The patient who came in yesterday has had an attack. </title>
            </scene>
            <scene num="77">
                <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>
                <dir type="char">Lunatic's cell Sievers and the attendant stop short at the door
                    way. Straining their eyes to see into the semi- darkness. There, in the corner.
                    Something moves slowly. It is a man. Now his face is in the light. Like a
                    panther preparing to leap, his ferocity re- strained, he raises himself up
                    slowly. His crazed burning eyes staring at Sievers. And now we re- cognize him
                    at last . . . it is Knock!!! Suddenly, in one leap, he is at the window. Sievers
                    is startled, says something to the attendant. Who prepares the straitjacket be
                    brought along. Yet the expected attack does not come. Knock remains at the
                    window, arms jerking, he begins . . . to catch flies which he puts into his
                    mouth. Horrible food. The madman's face twists into a grin that resembles
                    distant lightning. His swollen lips are murmuring something:</dir>
                <title>Blood is life! Blood is life!!!</title>
                <dir type="char"> Suddenly, the madman starts up and throws himself with all his
                    might on the unsuspecting Sievers. Who can barely ward him off. But the
                    attendant comes to his help quickly and throws the straightjacket over the
                    raging man's head. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="78">
                <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
                <loc>The Institute:</loc>
                <dir type="char">Bulwer, in a quiet, scholarly manner with his students. He points
                    to an aquarium.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="stg">On a piece of rock in the water hangs a small polyp. Now it
                    stretches out its tentacles, grabs a small fish and pulls it up to its mouth. It
                    is almost transparent, colorless and of a jelly-like consistency. </dir>
                <title>And this one . . .a polyp with tentacles . . . transparent . . . almost
                    incorporeal . . . almost a phantom . . . </title>
            </scene>
            <scene num="79">
                <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
                <loc>Lunatic's cell.</loc>
                <cam>Close-up</cam>
                <dir type="char">On the floor, in his straitjacket, whining pitifully, mad Knock.
                    His face. Turning his sad eyes upwards. He notices something there. His lips
                    form a word:</dir>
                <title> Spiders . . . !</title>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="stg">A spider-web with a live spider which clutches, vampire-like an
                    insect and is sucking its blood.</dir>
                <cam>Normal:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Knock in exultation. Sievers stands motionless . . . does not
                    understand. Brusquely, he gives an order and leaves. </dir>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="80">
                <cam dis="4">4 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade in. </cam>
                <loc>The graveyard of Whitby</loc>
                <dir type="stg">View from the pier-head towards the shore. In the fore- ground the
                    surging sea. Further back, where the shore rises steeply, the graveyard of
                    Whitby.</dir>
                <cam>Closer:</cam>
                <dir type="stg"> The graveyard. Afternoon light. In front of the graveyard a long
                    row of benches. People are strolling up and down looking out on to the sea . . .
                    sitting on the benches and enjoying the view.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">A bench, somewhat apart from the others. Ellen is sitting there.
                    Dreamily, her eyes searching a distant country beyond the sea. She seems to be
                    in an anxious day- dream about her distant lover. Now she shuts her eyes,
                    because tears are welling up.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="81">
                <cam dis="4">4 meters</cam>
                <title> Croquet?</title>
                <loc>In Harding's Park</loc>
                <dir type="char">Harding, youthful and athletic, is batting. The shuttlecock flies
                    high up into the air. Anny, in a light dress, shouts with joy . . . catches it .
                    . . throws it back. The shuttlecock flies backwards and forwards. It is a
                    picture of health and light.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="82">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <loc>At the park gates.</loc>
                <dir type="char">The postman, a small old man, rummages in his leather bag and
                    produces a letter which he hands with an air of importance to Harding's servant
                    who is as old and wizened as he. Before he leaves, the post- man points to the
                    stamp which seems to be of special value, lifting up his eyebrows: This letter
                    has travelled ar . . . it comes from a very remote country. The two old men bend
                    over the rare letter. Then the old servant takes it in.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="83">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <loc>In the park</loc>
                <dir type="char">As the servant approaches. Harding and Anny stop playing. Anny
                    takes the letter, reads the address and runs to her brother. It is for Ellen,
                    she says, point- ing into the distance. Shall we take it to her straight away.
                    Harding agrees, they hand their rackets over to the ser- and walk off.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="84">
                <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
                <loc>At the graveyard</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen is still sitting there, looking over the vast waters, lost in
                    her sad longing thoughts.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="85">
                <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
                <loc> Heligoland The sea</loc>
                <dir type="stg">Distant view over the sea. A sand bank skirted by rocks, jutting out
                    into the surf waters.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="86">
                <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>
                <loc>At the graveyard.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Harding and Anny are approaching. They are joining the lonely
                    Ellen. shak- ing hands and trying to cheer her up. Guess what we have brought
                    you! They show her the letter. Ellen trembles. She takes the letter quickly and
                    tries to open it! I cannot do it. Gladly and quickly, Anny takes over. You'll
                    see, he is safe and sound and sends you good news. She starts to read it gives a
                    joyful laugh, she was right. All is well. The worries were unfounded Happily she
                    gives Ellen the letter. But barely has she read the letter when Ellen's face
                    assumes an expression of hurt certainty. Does she derive evil premonitions from
                    these lines? </dir>
                <cam>Close up:</cam>
                <dir type="stg"> letter.</dir>

                <dir type="stg"> the mosquitoes are a real pest. I have been stung on the neck by
                    two at once, very close together, one on each side . . .</dir>
                <cam>Normal:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen's face is distorted as if she were suffering physical pain.
                    Harding and Anny are perplexed. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="87">
                <title>GALAZ</title>
                <loc>The port of Galaz at night.</loc>
                <dir type="stg"> The 'Demeter' is anchored off the jetty. Nobody is about on the
                    quay. A stormy night, strange uncertain light. Sud- denly - a gentle movement
                    from the ship down the gangway to the shore . . . rats . . .</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out: </cam>
                <dir type="stg">The coffins are reloaded</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="88">
                <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
                <loc>The hospital at Budapest</loc>
                <dir type="char">Hutter, dressed, stands in front of his bed. He looks pale and weak
                    still, yet full of resolution. The nurse notices his unsteady stance. She fusses
                    around him. You ought to stay a few more days! Have some more rest! But he wards
                    her off. His gestures are restless and fluttering, a strange force has taken
                    possession of him.</dir>
                <title> I have to get home by the shortest possible way! !</title>
                <dir type="char"> So he says goodbye, disregarding the nurse's advice, thanks her
                    for her care and goes out quickly. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="89">
                <title>Constantinople</title>
                <loc>The port. Night.</loc>
                <dir type="stg">Wild dogs are barking from the debris in the street up to the
                    distant firmament, writhing in the mud like snakes.</dir>
                <cam>Focus on quay:</cam>
                <dir type="stg">The "Demeter" at anchor. What's scuttling over there? . . . A shadow
                    from the ship to the land . . . rats. . . one. . . four. . . ten . . . and
                    endless stream . . .the carry terror with them.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="90">
                <cam dis="8">8 meters </cam>
                <loc> Polnischer Kamm Non-stop rain Entry to the Vratna Gorge</loc>
                <title> In the Hungarian plain.</title>
                <dir type="stg">Coach station in the Pusta The mail coach is arriving at top speed.
                    The coachman whips his exhausted horses into a last effort. The coach has barely
                    stopped when Hutter jumps off. He calls for more speed. Now fresh horses are
                    being brought along. Hutter joins the grooms and tells them to hurry on! To
                    hurry on! The tired horses have been taken out of harness and are being led to
                    the stable. Bring fresh horses! Hutter gives a helping hand. Now the straps are
                    done up. The coachman blows his horn. Some late-comers appear. They get into the
                    coach. Hutter is the last. And the heavy coach rumbles off, the horses gallop-
                    ing, sparks flying from the hooves, dust rising, into the pathless
                    country.</dir>
                <cam>Fade- out. </cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter leads a limping horse through </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="91">
                <cam>Fade-in:</cam>
                <loc>The port of Constantiople </loc>
                <cam>Long shot.</cam>
                <dir type="stg"> In a fresh breeze, the "Demeter" emerges from the confusion of
                    mast-heads and gains the open sea.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="92">
                <cam dis="15">15 meters</cam>
                <loc>Lunatic's cell </loc>
                <dir type="char">In a stupor, Knock is perching on his bunk. The attendant holding a
                    broom, is about to leave the cell. At this moment Knock lifts his eyes. With a
                    look of artful cunning and with rigid concentration he follows the attendant's
                    movements. Now, he seems to have discovered an opportunity; softly, he sneaks up
                    on the unsuspecting man and takes away the newspaper that sticks out of his
                    pocket. The attendant does not notice and shuts the door behind him. The moment
                    Knock is alone he unfolds the paper trembling with expectancy and starts read-
                    ing. searching for something with wide-open eyes. Now he has found what he was
                    looking for. He is riveted to this passage. </dir>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <title>The Newspaper</title>

                <dir type="stg"> PLAGUE In Transyvania and in the Black Sear ports of Varna and
                    Galaz a plague epidemic has started. Young women in particular fall victim to it
                    in large numbers. All the victims show the same peculiar wound marks on the neck
                    whose origin is still an enigma to the Doctors The Dardenelles have been closed
                    to all ships sus- pected of carrying the epidemic. It is out of the question
                    that the epidemic will reach Western Europe.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Knock's mocking, triumphant face assumes an expression of demonic
                    grandeur. He straightens himself up, lifts up his head, raises his arms as if
                    greeting the evil. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="93">
                <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
                <loc>North Sea</loc>
                <title>Open Sea</title>
                <dir type="stg"> The Mediterranean. In the distance the "Demeter" sailing through
                    the waters gleaming in the even- ing light. </dir>
                <cam>Dissolve. Medium close-up</cam>
                <loc> The ship's deck</loc>
                <dir type="char"> The ship's mate is running up the companion-way in great agitation
                    and crosses the deck on his way to the captain's cabin. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="94">
                <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
                <dir type="stg">In the captain's cabin The captain of the 'Demeter' bent over maps,
                    making en- tries in the log-book. The mater enters and reports excitedly: </dir>
                <title> Below deck a sailor has fallen ill. He is talking in a fever.</title>
                <dir type="char"> The captan looks up, shocked. He leaves his work and fol- low the
                    mate.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="95">
                <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>
                <loc>Below deck.</loc>
                <dir type="stg"> In the background the ship's hold. Among other cargo in the deep
                    darkness the coffins. To be seen through an open door. In the foreground the
                    crew's cabin with hammocks In one of them the delirious sailor. </dir>
                <cam>Medium Close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Captain and mate go up to the patient who stares at them as if they
                    were ghosts. He seems to listen intently. Every noise makes him start. Shot of
                    hold Brooding, intense darkness. The lid of one of the coffins seems to open a
                    little. </dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char"> The captain, more angry than concerned, advises the patient in his
                    uncouth sailor's way to have a strong drink. Promptly the mate produces his
                    bottle and give it to the patient. The smell seems to wake him up from his
                    lethargy and he takes a long sip. The captain tells him to have a good rest and
                    goes out again with the mate. The sailor alone. His eyes wandering . . .
                    Suddenly, they remain fixed, as if spellbound, on the door leading to the hold.
                    In horror he sits up and remains in a crouching position as if turned to stone.
                    Pan to the door lead- ing into the hold. There, horrible and awe-inspiring,
                    stands NOSFERATU And . . . he . . . approaches.</dir>
                <cam>Fade out</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="96">
                <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
                <loc>Hornunger Moor Lünebur ger Heide</loc>
                <dir type="stg">Wild and desolate scenery In the distance a galloping horseman on
                    the plain. He comes closer and closer . . . moving at tremendous speed. It is
                    Hutter. </dir>
                <cam>Dissolve</cam>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter, standing near his horse and examining its injured hoof.
                    With a desper ate gesture, he lets go of it. Yet he has made his decision. He
                    must go on. He takes the horse by the reins and walks on, dragging the limping
                    animal after him. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="97">
                <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>
                <title>The gulf of Biscay</title>
                <loc>On deck, the 'Demeter' Evening.</loc>
                <dir type="char">In the last light of the sun captain and mate are about to push the
                    shrouded corpse of the last sailor over the railing. They have covered their
                    mouths and noses with cloths for protection.</dir>
                <cam>Shot of ship's side </cam>
                <dir type="char">The corpse is slid down into the water by ropes. On deck. For a
                    moment the two last survivors pause in quiet contem- plation of the horror of
                    death. Suddenly, the mate's body stiffens, he has made a resolution. For a short
                    moment, he shuts his eyes and tries to master the horror that is rising up
                    inside him. Then he pulls himself together, tears the cloth off his face, takes
                    up an axe and, brandishing it in the air,</dir>
                <cam> calls out:</cam>
                <title> I'm going down!!! If I haven't come back in ten minutes . . .</title>
                <dir type="char"> With the courage of a desperate man he hurries over to the
                    companion-way. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="98">
                <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>
                <loc>Below deck. </loc>
                <dir type="char">There are the black boxes. They are the man's target. He lifts his
                    axe at the first one and shatters its lid. There it is: He is tempted to
                    retreat. Rats! All round his ankles he feels the crawling of horrible creatures.
                    Yet he pulls himself together for a second time. Another box, smashed by a
                    second blow. And the same thing happens again: rats! only rats! He is wading
                    through wriggling bodies which surround him from all sides. Yet he withstands
                    the horror. There, a third box. </dir>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">The mate. In despair, foaming at the lips, he prepares for the
                    third blow.</dir>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char"> The axe falls from his hand. His hair is standing on end. Quick as
                    lightning NOSFERATU rears up from the box. Now the mate is finally overcome by
                    horror . . . Covering his eyes with his hands he runs upstairs, crazy with fear.
                    Slowly and steadily, NOSFERATU is approaching. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="99">
                <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
                <loc>On deck </loc>
                <dir type="char">The captain is guarding the helm. Then from the hatch, the mate
                    emerges . . . his hair has turned grey . . . his face looks crazed . . . he is
                    foaming at the mouth . . trying to escape. . . he sways . . .turns deliriously
                    in a circle . . .loses his sense of direction. . .does not see the railing. . .
                    and overshoots it. Falling head first. The captain watches in horror. Now he is
                    lef t all alone. But his face remains determined. He picks up a rope and ties
                    himself to the helm, not to be tempted to leave. Thus he awaits the horror. . . </dir>
                <cam>Fade out. </cam>
            </scene>
            <title>End of Act III</title>
        </act>
        <act num="4">
            <title>ACT IV </title>
            <scene num="100">
                <cam dis="5">5 meters </cam>
                <loc> Heligoland</loc>
                <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
                <loc>A cliff by the coast Night</loc>
                <dir type="stg">, roaring surf. The storm is howling. A gigantic wave moves up,
                    breaks the water splashes high up.</dir>
                <dir type="stg">Moving coach</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="101">
                <cam dis="5">5 meters</cam>
                <cam>Anny's room. Night.</cam>
                <dir type="char">Anny is asleep. The storm is pushing against the windows, opening
                    them. The curtain is billowing and fluttering in the wind. Anny wakes up.
                    Confused, Terrified, she jumps up. She tries to shut the win- dow, yet cannot
                    bring herself to do it. The storm is pushing her back . . . she recoils. She
                    runs out of the room.</dir>

                <dir type="char">Waves Ellen Anny wakes up Carriage Ellen walking forward Waves
                    Carriage Hutter Anny wakes up Waves Ellen Anny Boat</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="102">
                <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
                <loc>Ellen's room at the Hardings </loc>
                <dir type="stg">The storm is sweeping through the open window. The bed is empty . .
                    . Anny enters. She knows at once what has happened, - rushes out.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="103">
                <cam dis="4">4 meters</cam>
                <loc>Roof of Harding's mansion</loc>
                <dir type="char"> Ellen, her clothes fluttering in the wind, her hair like a flag,
                    is sleeping in the storm. She stretches out her arms defensively. A white figure
                    against the black night sky. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="104">
                <annot>XXXXXXXXXX</annot>
                <dir type="char">(placement text) </dir>

            </scene>
            <scene num="105">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <loc> Contre jour North Sea</loc>
                <dir type="stg"> High Sea. The storm is raging, enormous tidal waves . . . In the
                    distance a sailing ship, the 'Demeter' at full sail, racing to its perdition.
                    Trick</dir>
                <gapMk>(Scenes 106 and 107 are missing)</gapMk>

            </scene>
            <scene num="108">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <loc>View across the town at night</loc>
                <dir type="stg"> The storm is tossing the trees. Sailing boat moving towards it
                    objective .</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="109">
                <annot>is missing</annot>
                <dir type="stg">(placement text)</dir>

            </scene>
            <scene num="110">
                <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>
                <loc> Wismar Sea</loc>
                <dir type="stg"> The storm rages violently. The sand bank threatens 'Demeter', the
                    fatal ship, has closer, still moving at full speed. </dir>
                <cam>View from the sea towards the harbor.</cam>
                <dir type="char"> Sailing ships are coming in at full sail. Contre jour (wismar).
                    Trick Ellen runs out from room Broken axle Ellen runs through garden Ship moves
                    towards objective Knock 1 Ship coming into the harbor Hutter running street.
                    Knock Ship in harbour. Nosferatu appears Hutter running through street Nosferatu
                    through gate with coffin Door Hutter Knock escape Nosferatu square or street
                    Room]</dir>
            </scene>
        </act>
        <act num="4">
            <scene num="111">
                <cam>4 meters</cam>
                <loc>Roof Balcony of</loc>
                <loc>Harding's mansion</loc>
                <dir type="char">Ellen in Anny's arm. Her hair is fluttering in the wind. Ellen
                    stretching her hands towards the sea, as if trying to defend herself.</dir>
                <annot><title> I must go home. He is coming.</title></annot>
            </scene>

            <scene num="112">
                <loc>At the graveyard</loc>
                <loc>View over the sea</loc>
                <loc>In the foreground the crosses. In the back sandbank and cliffs.</loc>
                <dir type="char">In the distance people, hurrying to rescue the ship- wrecked.</dir>
                <dir type="stg">The sand bank . The ship crashes into it . . . turns over on its
                    side.</dir>
                <annot><cam>View through archway:</cam>
                    <loc>the sailing boat is moving past. Weimar</loc></annot>
            </scene>

            <scene num="113">
                <annot><cam dis="4">4 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Lunatic's cell</loc>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Knock alone. He drags up a chair . . . to the window. He climbs up
                    on it.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Knock pulls himself up by the bars, trying to look out. The wind,
                    blowing in, makes his hair stand on end uncannily.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="113" sub="a">
                <annot><cam dis="10">10 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>The stranded ship Dead and forsaken. a rope is dangling from the deck. It is
                    swaying in the wind.</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
                <loc>An endless number of rats climbing down the swaying rope.</loc>
                <cam>Shot of deck.</cam>
                <dir type="stg">The hatch. It opens slowly.</dir>
                <dir type="char">NOSFERATU climbs out.</dir>
                <dir type="char">He carries the last coffin.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Remains standing. Motionless.</dir>
                <dir type="char">The image of death. Then he approaches slowly.</dir>
                <annot><loc>1) Ship anchored in the harbor.</loc>
                    <cam>Dissolve</cam>
                    <loc>2)Ship's hatch with a piece of deck.</loc>
                    <dir type="stg"> Trick: 1) Canvas glides away from hatch. 2) Hatch lid is
                        lifted. 3) Rats are rushing on deck.</dir>
                    <dir type="char">4) Nosferatu coffin in arms climbs out.</dir></annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="114">
                <annot><cam>8 meters</cam>
                    <loc>Lauenburg or Travemünde</loc></annot>
                <loc>Town center. Trees, shaken by storm.</loc>
                <dir type="stg">A carriage races up, stops abruptly.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter jumps from the carriage. </dir>
                <dir type="stg">An axle is broken.</dir>
                <dir type="char"> The coachman seems at a loss.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Hutter cannot wait. He leaves the carriage and runs of f.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="115">
                <annot><cam dis="5">5 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Archway with a view of the harbor: </loc>
                <annot><dir type="char">Nosferatu enters the town</dir></annot>
            </scene>

            <scene num="116">
                <annot><cam dis="6">6 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>The roof of Harding's mansion.</loc>
                <loc> Ellen's room at the Hardings' </loc>
                <dir type="char">Ellen and Anny. Ellen suddenly breaks away. Overjoyed as if she had
                    a happy vision she throws her arms up and shouts:</dir>
                <annot><title> I must go to him. He is coming!! </title></annot>
                <dir type="char">She moves off and vanishes.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Anny wrings her hands in despair.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="117">
                <annot><cam dis="4">4 meters </cam></annot>
                <loc>Storm-tossed trees.</loc>
                <dir type="char">A white figure comes out of the house. It is Ellen. She is running
                    through the park. </dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="118">
                <annot><loc>perhaps Lüneberg Street</loc></annot>
                <loc>Shuttered windows.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Nosferatu striding</dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="118" sub="a">
                <dir type="char">Hutter, running along the street.</dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="119">
                <annot><cam>8 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Lunatic's cell</loc>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="stg">Knock, moving away from the window wall</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">The madman is listening for outside noises, as if he had received a
                    signal from the other world . . . triumphantly . . . he whispers to himself: </dir>
                <annot><title>The master is near . . .the master is near . . .!</title></annot>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Suddenly, he listens attentively. He creeps over to the door. There
                    he waits expectantly . . . The door opens. The attendant appears. He looks
                    around the room. Not noticing that Knock is behind him. Knock creeps carefully
                    behind his back. Suddenly frightened, the attendant turns around. Knock makes
                    for his throat like a vampire. The attendant falls over. The madman is at his
                    throat <annot>for a moment only, then he lets go and sneaks out.</annot></dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="120">
                <annot><cam>5 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>In front of Hutter's house</loc>
                <dir type="char">Hutter comes running up. He looks up: no light. He is just about to
                    enter when - somebody is calling. He turns around Ellen!!!!! They fall into each
                    other's arms.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="121">
                <loc>Square with fountain</loc>
                <cam>5 meters</cam>
                <dir type="char">Nosferatu, cof˚n under his arm, is standing in the middle of the
                    square. Looking around to orientate himself. Then he strides on.</dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="122">
                <annot><cam dis="4" sync="2">4 meters 2x</cam></annot>
                <loc>Hutter's parlour Ellen's sitting room</loc>
                <dir type="stg">A lamp is shining. Hutter and Ellen. They are sitting on the chaise
                    lounge. The happiness of being reunited was too much. Overpowered by emotion, he
                    sinks down on her arm. </dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="123">
                <annot><cam>4 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>In front of Hutter's house</loc>
                <annot><dir type="char">Nosferatu, staring up</dir></annot>
            </scene>

            <scene num="124">
                <annot><cam dis="6">6 meters</cam></annot>
                <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter and Ellen, on the chaise lounge. He sits up, looking deep
                    into her eyes.</dir>
                <annot><title> Thank God . . . you are well . . .now everything has come all
                        right.</title></annot>
                <dir type="char">She does not understand him. But the joy of being to- gether again
                    is stronger than anything else. And the room is bright.</dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="125">
                <annot><cam dis="10">10 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Street in front of Hutter's House </loc>
                <dir type="char">There is nobody about. But in the middle of the street stands
                    NOSFERATU, hidden by the night, carrying the cof fin. Slowly, he turns his head
                    and looks over to Hutter's house.</dir>
                <cam>Shot of Hutter's house The deserted house </cam>
                <dir type="stg">[There is a friendly light in the window] </dir>
                <annot><dir type="char"> Empty! Carrying the coffin - Nosferatu appears in picture.
                    </dir></annot>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">NOSFERATU. Once more he turns his head. He looks over to the other
                    side. The deserted house is over there. He makes for that now, walking slow.
                        <annot>Then he goes into the house. </annot></dir>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="126">
                <annot><cam dis="12">12 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>On the stranded ship</loc>
                <dir type="char">The captain, collapsed in death, is tied to the helm. In the
                    foreground, some men, Harding among them, are climbing up on deck. They are
                    aghast at the terrible sight.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">The dead captain. Tied to the helm in discharge of his duty! One
                    hand is still on the helm. The other, holding a crucifix, clutches his chest in
                    mortal agony. His head sunk back, face distorted. There are two red marks on his
                    neck . . . </dir>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Harding. He cannot comprehend the horror . . .</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="127">
                <annot><cam dis="6">6 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Sandbank harbor The stranded ship is in sight.</loc>
                <time>It is night-time</time>
                <cam>Long shot: </cam>
                <dir type="stg">In the blowing wind nocturnal figures . . .townspeople</dir>
                <cam>Close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Down the tilted hulk a man is climbing along a rope. </dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">By the light of a torch! the captain of the harbor with a number of
                    old people . . . Looking like fishermen. The climber approaches and reports. </dir>
                <annot><title> Everything has been examined . . No living soul on board. The captain
                        receives the report . . . jots down some notes.</title></annot>
            </scene>

            <scene num="128">
                <annot><cam dis="10">10 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>On board ship.</loc>
                <time>Night</time>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <loc>Back-board with helm.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Some men are lifting up the dead captain, and carrying off the
                    corpse. </dir>
                <loc>Captain's cabin: </loc>
                <dir type="char">Harding alone . . . he finds a book next to a masthead that is
                    affixed to the helm. In the light of a dim lantern he reads: </dir>
                <cam>Close-up: A page of the book</cam>
                <p>Varna - July 12 Crew - apart from myself the captain - one helmsman mate and five
                    sailors. Departing - for the Dardanelles. </p>
                <cam>Normal Shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Harding shakes his head. He is puzzled.</dir>
                <annot><loc>On deck.</loc>
                    <dir type="char">Harding emerges from the cabin with the book in his
                    hand.</dir></annot>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="129">
                <annot><cam dis="15">15 meters</cam></annot>
                <cam>Fade-in: </cam>
                <annot>
                    <time>Daytime</time></annot>
                <loc>Port Authority building A large hall. On the walls a number of figure heads
                    Models of ships are suspended from the ceiling.</loc>
                <dir type="char">The dead captain [is carried] in lying in state.</dir>
                <cam>Medium Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Dr. Sievers is examining him. He notices the marks on his neck. Dr.
                    Sievers turns to Harding.</dir>
                <dir type="char"> He, too, cannot make sense of this case. Nevertheless he talks
                    incessantly. Harding comes closer shows him the log-book. Both of them are
                    reading: </dir>
                <cam>Close-up: The log-book.</cam>
                <dir type="stg"> A page: Second day: July 13 A sailor has fallen ill with a fever.
                    Course: SSW. Direction of wind: Third day: July 14 Mate is talking strangely. He
                    says there is an unknown passenger below deck. Course SE. Direction of wind NE.
                    Volume of wind 3.6. </dir>
                <cam>Normal shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Sievers and Harding are looking at each other. Sievers' white beard
                    is trembling. They continue reading. Tenth day: July 22 Rats in the ship's hold.
                    Danger of plague.</dir>
                <cam>Normal shot: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Harding has been reading this aloud. Now Sievers understands at
                    last. He points to the book with his finger. Danger of plague! That's what it
                    is. Dan- ger of plague, he calls out. </dir>
                <title> Danger of plague! Go home! Shut all your windows and doors!</title>
                <dir type="stg">Deeply frightened, the bystanders move away. The women put the ends
                    of their head-scarves into their mouths. Panic- stricken .the crowd leaves the
                    room.</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
                <annot>(Perhaps end of act)</annot>

            </scene>

            <scene num="130">
                <annot><cam dis="15">15 meters</cam></annot>
                <cam>Fade-in</cam>
                <loc>A deserted square: Nobody is about. Except in the center of the square, the
                    town-drummer with his large drum. </loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">The drummer. He beats a mighty roll.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <loc>A closed window.</loc>
                <dir type="char">The hatch opens and a woman's head appears: totally emaciated,
                    sunken cheeks, long dishevelled hair. The disease has gripped her too. On her
                    neck the ominous little marks. </dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">The drummer has produced a piece of paper and reads it aloud:</dir>
                <p>magistrate of this town prohibits any movement of plague-suspects into hospitals
                    to prevent the plague from spreading through the streets. </p>
                <dir type="char">The drummer has finished reading and goes off.</dir>
            </scene>

            <title>End of Act IV</title>
        </act>
        <act num="5">
            <title>Act V</title>
            <scene num="131">
                <annot><cam dis="15">15 meters</cam></annot>
                <cam>Fade in.</cam>
                <loc>A bend in a street</loc>
                <dir type="char">A man emerges from a front door. He shuts the door behind him.
                    Quickly and with circumspection he chalks a white cross on the door. Then goes
                    on.</dir>
                <cam>Panning shot:</cam>
                <loc>The adjoining house.</loc>
                <dir type="char">The man knocks hard on the door. From a window above a head looks
                    out. There are still people living here. The man moves on. </dir>
                <cam>Panning shot: </cam>
                <loc>The first house in the side-street.</loc>
                <dir type="char">A coffin is being carried out. Men carrying it have white bandages
                    over their mouths. The man comes along and dr aws a cross on this house, too.
                    Then he walks on, following his horrible business.</dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="132">
                <annot><cam dis="15" sync="2">15 meters 2x</cam>
                    <loc>shaded candle on table near armchair .</loc></annot>
                <loc>Ellen's bedroom</loc>
                <annot><cam>Close-up:</cam>
                    <dir type="stg">Book-cover Inscription (Vampire) See Chapter 1 of book.
                    </dir></annot>
                <annot><cam>Dissolve to: </cam>
                    <dir type="char">Ellen by the window, the book on her knees continues reading,
                        overcoming her aversion. </dir>
                    <dir type="stg">Chapter II appears.</dir></annot>
                <annot><cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                    <dir type="char">Ellen is pondering on what she has read. </dir>
                    <dir type="char">Hutter comes into the picture, with agitation almost hostility
                        he grabs the book.</dir>
                    <dir type="char">Ellen, standing now, looks straight into his eyes, turns and
                        points over to the deserted house.</dir>
                    <annot>Compare the following black dress and shawl</annot>
                    <cost>Hutter, black waist-coat and jacket.</cost></annot>
                <loc>Ellen's room.</loc>
                <cam>Long shot: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen by the window. Hutter approaches from the door</dir>
                <cam>Medium close</cam>
                <dir type="char">Suddenly, she grabs his arm, stares out of the window pointing out,
                    she shouts: There!!!</dir>
                <annot><dir type="char">Her body is tensed up like a bow trembling with
                        excitement.</dir></annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="133">
                <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
                <loc>The deserted house Seen through Ellen's window frame.</loc>
                <cam> Almost at once dissolve to window.</cam>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <loc>A window, divided into four rectangular panes. Light from behind.</loc>
                <dir type="stg">Stuck to the window, almost completely covering it, something
                    looking like a black fourlegged spider. It takes a moment before one can make
                    out Nos- feratu's fingers which are clawing the window frame. In the center of
                    the body, grinning lasciviously, the waxen face with ratlike teeth. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="134">
                <annot><cam dis="8" sync="2">8 meters 2x</cam></annot>
                <loc>Ellen's bedroom.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Ellen holds frantically on to Hutter's hand [shaken] breathing
                    heavily She bends her head back. towards him saying. </dir>
                <annot><title> This is how I see it- every evening. . .!!! </title></annot>
                <dir type="char">She bends her head back. She knows all she has to know. And there
                    is peace in the knowledge.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Hutter has not come to that yet. He finds her calm- ness
                    disturbing. He follows the retreating figure with his eyes.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen is swaying.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter, despairingly, presses his fist against his face. </dir>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="135">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <loc>In front of Hutter's house</loc>
                <time>It is now evening.</time>
                <dir type="char">The lamp-lighter comes down the darkening street and lights up the
                    street-lamps. The he walks on.</dir>
                <annot>! remains!</annot>
            </scene>

            <scene num="136">
                <annot><cam dis="10">10 meters</cam></annot>
                <cam>Fade-in:</cam>
                <loc>Anny's bedroom</loc>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Anny crouching on a chaise lounge.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Bent over her Harding who is holding her hands and trying to calm
                    down the struggling woman who is shaking fitfully.</dir>
                <dir type="char"> She collapses with exhaustion. Then pulls himself together and
                    decides: </dir>
                <annot><title> I will run over quickly . . . I shall get Sievers. And he is
                        gone.</title></annot>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Anny, having almost fainted with fear, comes to again. She opens
                    her eyes. She lifts her head. No- body around?? Is she all alone?? Isn't there
                    some- thing moving about in the corner? Something fluttering at the window? </dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="stg">The window, covered by the curtain. Behind it the shadow of a giant
                    bat. It grows and grows. Soon it isn't a bat any long- er. A vampire!
                    NOSTERATU?! </dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Anny's body hits the wall. She jumps up and pulls the bell. Then
                    half crazed with fear, she runs into the background.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="137">
                <loc>Anny's bedroom.</loc>
                <cam>Long shot: </cam>
                <time>Night.</time>
                <dir type="char">Servants running to and fro in the direc- tion of the bedroom.
                </dir>
            </scene>





            <scene num="137" sub="a">
                <annot><dir type="stg">The bell is ringing.</dir></annot>
            </scene>

            <scene num="137" sub="b">
                <annot>
                    <loc>Servant's room. </loc>
                    <dir type="char">A servant asleep doesn't hear, turns over in his
                    sleep</dir></annot>
            </scene>


            <scene num="138">

                <annot><loc>Anny's Bedroom</loc></annot>
                <annot><cam dis="3">3 meters</cam></annot>
                <dir type="char">Anny pressed close to the wall.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Servants are rushing in.</dir>
                <dir type="char">There! She shouts pointing to the window.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Like a flock of chicken the women are huddling together.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Anny rushes over to them, but they are already so gripped by fear
                    that they imagine her fingers, which they are trying to push back, to be the
                    vampire's claws. Shrieking, they run off in all directions. The door is slammed
                    shut. Anny beats against the door. She is waiting for the horror, but she
                    doesn't want to see it, much rather die first. She grabs a table cloth and
                    covers her head and neck. Then she collapses.</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="139">
                <annot><cam dis="3">3 meters</cam></annot>
                <cam>Fade-in. </cam>
                <loc>Ellen's bedroom</loc>
                <time>Daytime.</time>
                <dir type="char">Ellen by the window . . .looking out. She stands motionless.
                    Paralysed by misery she witnesses the daily scene of wretchedness.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="140">
                <annot><cam dis="8">8 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Street in front of Hutter's's house</loc>
                <dir type="char">Ascending. In the distance, a strange procession is wandering
                    across the street. One coffin after another carried by survivors. Past Hutter's
                    house, towards the procession, a man is dragging himself along, tired to death.
                    She supports himself by a stick. He catches sight of the distant procession and
                    lifts up his hands to heaven in misery. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="141">
                <loc>Ellen's room.</loc>
                <annot><dir type="char">with window -frame Ellen</dir></annot>
                <dir type="char">Ellen, on the point of fainting, turns away from the window She
                    cannot bear the sight of this wretchedness any longer. She sinks into a chair,
                    resting her head in her hands. </dir>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">The book, open. She has been reading it for days </dir>
                <cam>Close up: A page of the book:</cam>
                <p> ONLY IF A CHASTE WOMAN CAN FEARLESSLY MAKE HIM MISS THE FIRST CROWING OF THE
                    COCK WILL HE DISINTEGRATE IN THE LIGHT OF DAWN</p>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen lifts up her head, staring into space like a visionary. She
                    knows. She shuts her eyes.</dir>
                <cam>Fade out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="142">
                <annot><cam>3 meters</cam></annot>
                <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
                <loc>In front of Harding's mansion..</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <loc>The porch.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Harding - haggard - a broken man, comes out. He closes the door and
                    supports himself against the door-post. His hand reaches up, paints a black
                    cross on the door . . .and falls down. His hollow eyes refrain from looking at
                    his work . . . again . . . they cannot bear to see the symbol. He moves forward
                    with a glazed look in his eyes. </dir>
                <cam>Fade-out. </cam>
                <annot><cost>Harding: black cape, dark trousers</cost></annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="143">
                <annot><cam dis="7">7 meters</cam></annot>
                <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
                <loc>In front of deserted house Street</loc>
                <dir type="char"> A group of emaciated men with a fanatical look about them are
                    standing around. An unkept-looking woman is haranguing them. They are raising
                    their fists.</dir>
                <annot><title> He has been seen! He ran out of the house! He strangled the
                        attendant!</title></annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="144">
                <annot><cam dis="8">8 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Well in the market-place</loc>
                <dir type="char">Two ancient women are sitting by the well. Death has no terrors for
                    them. Since every new day is a present to them. </dir>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">The are whispering to each other; their heads are trembling.</dir>
                <title> In the deserted house. . . that's where it is hiding. He strangled him. The
                    vampire. </title>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Further back agitated people are running across the square,
                    shouting excitedly to one another. The two woman turn around gesturing ˚ercely.
                    The clench their bony fists threateningly. Harding can be seen behind the well.
                    He has heard everything. </dir>
                <cam>Close up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">He utters a bitter and mocking laugh.</dir>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Harding walks on.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="144" sub="a">
                <annot><cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
                    <cam>Street shot from above: </cam>
                    <dir type="char">Crossing. Crowd gathering from all sides, then moving in one
                        direction.</dir>
                    <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                    <dir type="char">A street-corner with a man who points at something above.
                        People rush up to him; they all turn to face the same way, look up, make
                        threatening gestures Somebody throws stones. </dir></annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="145">
                <annot>
                    <loc>Gable of a house</loc>
                    <dir type="char">A figure is crouching on a roof-top</dir></annot>
            </scene>

            <scene num="146">
                <annot><cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                    <dir type="char">It is Knock. He is looking down with a sneer on his face and
                        pokes out his tongue A stone whizzes part him. He suddenly gets up and
                        clambers off.</dir></annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="147">
                <annot><cam dis="8">8 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Ellen's bedroom</loc>
                <dir type="char">Ellen in an old armchair, busy embroidering a cushion in the
                    cross-stitch manner of the 1840s An inscription reading: I LOVE YOU She puts
                    down her work, resting her head. Tired, she falls to day-dreaming. <annot>Then
                        she lights a lamp.</annot>
                </dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen takes up her work again, determined to finish it.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="148">
                <annot><time>Evening</time>
                    <cam dis="4">4 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Back of deserted house.</loc>
                <dir type="stg">The street is empty.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Knock jumps down a wall and runs off. In the distance some men
                    appear, chasing him. They catch sight of him and rush af ter him.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="149">
                <annot><cam dis="8">8 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Meadows outside the town</loc>
                <cam>Shot against a wide expanse of sky.</cam>
                <dir type="char">In the distance running figures, no more then silhouettes (Turn
                    slowly) Knock in front. His pursuers following a long way behind.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="150">
                <annot><cam dis="3">3 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Fields. Evening mists. Cornfields waving in the wind.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Suddenly, right in front between the ears of corn head. Dishevelled
                    hair. Then a bony back The heads turn around slowly. It is Knock.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="151">
                <annot><cam dis="3">3 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>A lane between fields.</loc>
                <time>The landscape has grown dim in the evening light. </time>
                <dir type="char">The men chasing Knock are approaching. They stop. They seem to have
                    lost the tr ail. Suddenly, one of them sees something. He opens his eyes wide,
                    shouting: there!!! They all look one way. They dash off in that direction.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="152">
                <annot><cam dis="10">10 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Cornfield,</loc>
                <cam>Long-shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">In the distance one can still the back and dis- hevelled head. Is
                    it Knock? He seems not to hear or see his pursuers. The men are coming near,
                    rushing towards him across the field. They lift their sticks and fists.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
                <loc>A scare-crow. A black coat is dangling on a stick. Bits of straw and tattered
                    rags.</loc>
                <dir type="char">The men fall on it in the disappointment. Suddenly they stop.
                    There! What can that be !!!</dir>
                <cam>Long-shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">A hundred feet away a head has appeared. Then the f igure of a man.
                    It is moving away quickly. The chase starts up again.</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="153">
                <annot><cam dis="3">3 meters</cam></annot>
                <title> Night</title>
                <loc>Deserted house.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Medium Nosferatu at the window.</dir>
                <cam>close-up:</cam>
                <cam>Dissolve</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="154">
                <annot><cam dis="8" sync="2">8 meters 2x</cam></annot>
                <loc>Ellen's bedroom</loc>
                <annot><cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                    <dir type="char">Ellen wakes up. She sits up in bed, listening as if she had
                        heard somebody calling her. She gets up, walking as if pulled by invisible
                        threads.</dir>
                    <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                    <dir type="char">She goes over to the window. In the fore- ground Hutter asleep
                        in an armchair, look- ing worn out.</dir>
                    <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                    <dir type="char">Ellen is clinging to the window. She sees. </dir></annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="155">
                <annot><cam dis="3"> 3 meters</cam>
                    <loc>Deserted house.</loc>
                    <dir type="char">Nosferatu at the window. He raises his arms
                    slowly.</dir></annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="156">
                <annot><loc>Ellen's room</loc>
                    <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                    <dir type="char">Ellen is about to collapse by the window. Shaking with fear she
                        struggles violently with herself. The last battle. Twice her hands comes up
                        to open the window and drops down again weakly; then, with sudden
                        determination, she pulls herself up dead straight and deliberately throws
                        the window wide open. </dir></annot>
            </scene>

            <scene num="157">
                <annot><cam dis="4">4 meters</cam>
                    <loc>Deserted house.</loc>
                    <cam>Medium close-up: Window</cam>
                    <dir type="char">Nosferatu moves away from the window, turns around and
                        disappears.</dir></annot>
            </scene>

            <scene num="158">
                <annot><cam dis="4">4 meters</cam>
                    <loc>Ellen's room.</loc>
                    <cam>Close-up: </cam>
                    <dir type="char">Ellen trembling with fear and apprehension</dir></annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="159">
                <annot><loc>Deserted house</loc>
                    <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
                    <loc>Locked-up gates</loc>
                    <dir type="stg">Suddenly the gates swing open:</dir>
                    <dir type="char">Nosferatu appears </dir></annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="160">
                <annot><cam dis="12" sync="2">12 meters 2x</cam>
                    <loc>Ellen's room.</loc>
                    <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                    <dir type="char">Ellen is covering her face with her hands, seized with mortal
                        fear. </dir>
                    <cam>Long shot; window moves out of picture</cam>
                    <dir type="char">Ellen at window. She wants to call for help. She staggers
                        forward. She stops in front of Hutter. One last moment of indecision. Then
                        she wakes him up. Hutter jumps to his feet. He catches the trembling figure
                        in his arms. and carries her over to the sofa. She begs him, hands raised as
                        if in prayer:</dir>
                    <time> Bulwer . . . Fetch Bulwer!</time>
                    <dir type="char">She entreats him to go. Hutter takes her hands, she quickly
                        kisses his head, Then he rushes out.</dir></annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="161">
                <annot><cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
                    <loc>In front of Hutter's House. A path bordered by flowers. </loc>
                    <dir type="char">Hutter rushes out.</dir>
                    <cost>Trousers, pleated shirt, collar without tie. No hat no waist coat.</cost>
                </annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="162">
                <annot><cam dis="5">5 meters</cam>
                    <loc>Ellen's room</loc>
                    <cam>Long shot.</cam>
                    <dir type="char">Ellen is still looking in the direction she saw Hutter leave,
                        then she gets up and walks toward the window.</dir></annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="163">
                <annot><loc>Deserted house.</loc>
                    <cam>Long Shot:</cam>
                    <dir type="char">Nosferatu is walking forward and moves out of the
                        picture.</dir>
                    <dir type="stg">The house looks more deserted than ever!</dir></annot>
            </scene>

            <scene num="164">
                <loc>In front of Hutter's house</loc>
                <annot><dir type="stg">Nobody is about.</dir>
                    <dir type="char">Nosferatu is approaching. He comes to a halt. (He is preparing
                        to jump, looks up) He enters the house.</dir></annot>
            </scene>

            <scene num="165">
                <annot><loc>Ellen's room</loc>
                    <dir type="char">Ellen turns around suddenly. She is shaking with fear,
                        anticipating the horror about to happen. And it is coming - - slowly, tensed
                        like a predatory animal. She recoils, moves backwards step by step, and step
                        by step it follows her Heart! - Hand</dir></annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="166">
                <annot><cam dis="6">6 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Bulwer's laboratory</loc>
                <loc>(Living room)</loc>
                <loc>In addition to the already familiar fish tanks there is a large telescope by a
                    window. A profusion of antiquated scientific gadgets, globes etc. A lamp is
                    burning.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Bulwer asleep in <cost>dressing-gown and night-cap</cost> in the
                    armchair. Cages with birds and all kinds of animals. Hutter rushes in. He wakes
                    Bulwer, begs him to come with him. Bulwer starts to get dressed.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="167">
                <loc>A municipal building on the period (town hall)</loc>
                <dir type="char">A large crowd is gathering in front of the town hall. Knock has
                    been captured. More people keep pouring in from all sides.</dir>
                <annot>Omitted</annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="168">
                <cam dis="5">5 meters</cam>
                <loc>An office room inside the town hall</loc>
                <dir type="char">Sievers rushes in excitedly from the adjoining room accompanied by
                    a man who has brought him the news. From the other side Knock is being brought
                    in. The lunatic is trembling with fear. exit</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="169">
                <annot><cam dis="4">4 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Ellen's room</loc>
                <time>Night.</time>
                <dir type="char">Ellen in bed, the strangler is at her throat, his fingers clawing
                    her arms. Her eyes, widened in mortal fear, have a glazed look. Then she seems
                    to have heard something.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="170">
                <dir type="stg">A cock jumps on to a still-life farm implements. He flaps his wings,
                    puffs up his throat and her- alds the morning.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="171">
                <annot><cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                    <loc>Siever's lunatic's cell</loc> Knock</annot>
                <dir type="char">Knock Inside the town hall Knock at the window, held by two men.
                    Trying to ward them off, he shouts anxiously:</dir>
                <annot><title> The master . . . the master . . .!</title></annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="172">
                <loc>Ellen's room.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Nosferatu raises his head. He looks drunk with pleasure. Ellen eyes
                    are full of terrible fear. She must not allow Nosferatu just to go. She pulls
                    her arms around him: he cannot resist and bends his head over her again.</dir>
                <annot>Omitted</annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="173">
                <annot><cam>3 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>The sun is rising over the small town.</loc>
            </scene>
            <scene num="174">
                <loc>Ellen's room</loc>
                <dir type="char">Ellen's last moment of apprehension.</dir>
                <loc>There, isn't that a flicker of sunlight on the wall over her bed?</loc>
                <dir type="char">Here eyes light up hopefully and remain fixed on this first sign of
                    the new day. She stretches out her hand for it. And look: it is moving
                    downwards.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="175">
                <annot><cam dis="5">5 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Street with front gardens</loc>
                <loc>The long shadows of sunrise.</loc>
                <loc>Nobody is about</loc>
                <dir type="char"> Then shoulders of Hutter and Bulwer appear. They are hurrying on
                    and turning into a side street.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="176">
                <annot><cam dis="8">8 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Ellen's room</loc>
                <loc>The bed is bathed in sunlight.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Ellen's eyes are full of anticipation</dir>
                <dir type="char">. Has she sacrificed herself in vain? Suddenly the horrible figure
                    jerks himself up. He looks about in amazement. He clutches his heart. The
                    bestial tenseness of his bearing relaxes. For a moment he stands, legs apart, as
                    if trying to regain his balance. He clutches his heart again and falls on his
                    knees, his face turned to the sun, distorted by pain.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="177">
                <annot>Siever's lunatic cell <cam dis="5">Knock 5 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Town hall</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Knock, in a <cost>straitjacket</cost>, alone in the sunlight which
                    is falling through a barred window. He is mumbling disconnected words:</dir>
                <title> The master . . .the master . . . is dead.</title>
                <dir type="char">His head sinks on to his chest.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="178">
                <annot><cam dis="8">8 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Ellen's room</loc>
                <dir type="char">Nosferatu on his knees, supporting himself with one hand on the
                    ground. He raises the other in the direction of the sun to shield himself from
                    the light that brings him death. But he cannot hold out against the sun. His
                    fingers, his hand, his arm are dissolving in the light. The sun seems about to
                    strike his heart. Now his body is dis- integrating in the light. Ellen throws up
                    her hands triumphantly calling:</dir>
                <title> Hutter!</title>
            </scene>
            <scene num="179">
                <cam>4 meters</cam>
                <loc>In front of Hutter's House</loc>
                <cam>Shot looking out from the doorway into the distance.</cam>
                <dir type="char">Bulwer and Hutter are running, not just walking into the
                    house.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="180">
                <cam>8 meters</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen in bed.</dir>
                <dir type="char"> In anticipation, her hand reaches out for Hutter. Hutter comes
                    rushing in, falls on his knees by the bed. He t akes hold of her hand.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char"> Her hand grasps his, the it lets go weakly and drops away. Ellen's
                    head falls over - - - - Bulwer is standing at the window, hands behind his back
                    looking out.</dir>
            </scene>
            <title>THE END</title>
        </act>
    </script>
</root>
