<?xml-model href="nosferatu_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
    <script>
        <head><title>...</title>.... <note>....</note>
        </head>
        <act num="4"><!--ebb: I think this is act 4 continued, yes?  -->
            <scene num="111">
                <cam>4 meters</cam> Roof Balcony of <loc>Harding's mansion</loc>
                <dir>Ellen in Anny's arm. Her hair is fluttering in the wind. Ellen stretching her
                    hands towards the sea, as if trying to defend herself.</dir> Title: <title>I
                    must go home. He is coming.</title>
            </scene>
            <scene num="112">
                <loc>At the graveyard</loc>
                <loc>View over the sea In the foreground the crosses. In the back sandbank and
                    cliffs. In the distance people, hurrying to rescue the ship- wrecked. The sand
                    bank . The ship crashes into it . . . turns over on its side.</loc>
                <cam>View through archway</cam> : <loc>the sailing boat is moving past. Weimar</loc>
            </scene>
            <scene num="113"> 4 meters Lunatic's cell <cam>Long shot</cam>: <dir>Knock alone. He
                    drags up a chair . . . to the window. He climbs up on it.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam><dir type="char">Knock pulls himself up by the bars,
                    trying to look out. The wind, blowing in, makes his hair stand on end
                    uncannily.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="113a"> 10 meters <loc>The stranded ship Dead and forsaken. a rope is
                    dangling from the deck. It is swaying in the wind.</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
                <loc>An endless number of rats climbing down the swaying rope.</loc>
                <cam>Shot of deck.</cam>
                <dir>The hatch. It opens slowly.</dir>
                <dir>NOSFERATU climbs out.</dir>
                <dir>He carries the last coffin.</dir>
                <dir>Remains standing. Motionless.</dir> The image of death. Then he approaches
                slowly. 1) Ship anchored in the harbor. Dissolve 2)Ship's hatch with a piece of
                deck. Trick: 1) Canvas glides away from hatch. 2) Hatch lid is lifted. 3) Rats are
                rushing on deck. 4) Nosferatu coffin in arms climbs out. </scene>
            <scene num="114">
                <cam>8 meters</cam>
                <loc>Lauenburg or Travemünde</loc> Town center. Trees, shaken by storm. A carriage
                races up, stops abruptly. Medium close-up: Hutter jumps from the carriage. An axle
                is broken. The coachman seems at a loss. Hutter cannot wait. He leaves the carriage
                and runs of f. </scene>
            <scene num="115"> 5 meters Archway with a view of the harbor: Nosferatu enters the town </scene>
            <scene num="116"> 6 meters <loc>The roof of Harding's mansion.</loc> Ellen's room at the
                Hardings' Ellen and Anny. Ellen suddenly breaks away. Overjoyed as if she had a
                happy vision she throws her arms up and shouts: Title: <title>I must go to him. He
                    is coming!!</title> She moves off and vanishes. Anny wrings her hands in
                despair. </scene>
            <scene num="117"> 4 meters <loc>Storm-tossed trees.</loc> A white figure comes out of
                the house. It is Ellen. She is running through the park. 118 <loc>perhaps Lüneberg
                    Street</loc>
                <loc>Shuttered windows.</loc>
                <dir>Nosferatu striding</dir> 118a <dir>Hutter, running along the street.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="119">
                <cam>8 meters</cam> Lunatic's cell <cam>Long shot</cam>: Knock, moving away from the
                window wall <cam>Medium close-up</cam>: The madman is listening for outside noises,
                as if he had received a signal from the other world . . . triumphantly . . . he
                whispers to himself: Titles: <title>The master is near . . .the master is near . .
                    .!</title>
                <cam>Long shot</cam>: Suddenly, he listens attentively. He creeps over to the door.
                There he waits expectantly . . . The door opens. The attendant appears. He looks
                around the room. Not noticing that Knock is behind him. Knock creeps carefully
                behind his back. Suddenly frightened, the attendant turns around. Knock makes for
                his throat like a vampire. The attendant falls over. The madman is at his throat for
                a moment only, then he lets go and sneaks out. </scene>
            <scene num="120">
                <cam>5 meters</cam>
                <loc>In front of Hutter's house</loc> Hutter comes running up. He looks up: no
                light. He is just about to enter when - somebody is calling. He turns around
                Ellen!!!!! They fall into each other's arms. </scene>
            <scene num="121">
                <loc>Square with fountain</loc>
                <cam>5 meters</cam> Nosferatu, cof˚n under his arm, is standing in the middle of the
                square. Looking around to orientate himself. Then he strides on. </scene>
            <scene num="122">
                <cam>4 meters 2x</cam> Hutter's parlour Ellen's sitting room A lamp is shining.
                Hutter and Ellen. They are sitting on the chaise lounge. The happiness of being
                reunited was too much. Overpowered by emotion, he sinks down on her arm. </scene>
            <scene num="123">
                <cam>4 meters</cam>
                <loc>In front of Hutter's house</loc> Nosferatu, staring up </scene>
            <scene num="124"> 6 meters <cam>Fade-in</cam>. Hutter and Ellen, on the chaise lounge.
                He sits up, looking deep into her eyes. Title: <title>Thank God . . . you are well .
                    . .now everything</title> has come all right. She does not understand him. But
                the joy of being to- gether again is stronger than anything else. And the room is
                bright. </scene>
            <scene num="125">
                <cam>10 meters</cam> Street in front of Hutter's House There is nobody about. But in
                the middle of the street stands NOSFERATU, hidden by the night, carrying the cof
                fin. Slowly, he turns his head and looks over to Hutter's house. Shot of Hutter's
                house [There is a friendly light in the window] The deserted house Empty! Carrying
                the coffin - Nosferatu appears in picture. Medium close-up: NOSFERATU. Once more he
                turns his head. He looks over to the other side. The deserted house is over there.
                He makes for that now, walking slow. Then he goes into the house. Fade-out. </scene>
            <scene num="126"> 12 meters On the stranded ship The captain, collapsed in death, is
                tied to the helm. In the foreground, some men, Harding among them, are climbing up
                on deck. They are aghast at the terrible sight. Close-up: The dead captain. Tied to
                the helm in discharge of his duty! One hand is still on the helm. The other, holding
                a crucifix, clutches his chest in mortal agony. His head sunk back, face distorted.
                There are two red marks on his neck . . . Close-up: Harding. He cannot comprehend
                the horror . . . </scene>
            <scene num="127"> 6 meters Sandbank harbor The stranded ship is in sight. It is
                night-time Long shot: In the blowing wind nocturnal figures . . .townspeople
                Close-up: Down the tilted hulk a man is climbing along a rope. Medium close-up: By
                the light of a torch! the captain of the harbor with a number of old people . . .
                Looking like fishermen. The climber approaches and reports. Title: Everything has
                been examined . . No living soul on board. The captain receives the report . . .
                jots down some notes. </scene>
            <scene num="128"> 10 meters [Is inserted below] On board ship. Night Long shot:
                Back-board with helm. Some men are lifting up the dead captain, and carrying off the
                corpse. Captain's cabin: Harding alone . . . he finds a book next to a masthead that
                is affixed to the helm. In the light of a dim lantern he reads: Close-up: A page of
                the book Varna - July 12 Crew - apart from myself the captain - one helmsman mate
                and five sailors. Departing - for the Dardanelles. Normal Shot: Harding shakes his
                head. He is puzzled. On deck. Harding emerges from the cabin with the book in his
                hand. Fade-out. </scene>
            <scene num="129"> 15 meters Fade-in: Daytime Port Authority building A large hall. On
                the walls a number of figure heads Models of ships are suspended from the ceiling.
                The dead captain [is carried] in lying in state. Medium Close-up: Dr. Sievers is
                examining him. He notices the marks on his neck. Dr. Sievers turns to Harding. He,
                too, cannot make sense of this case. Nevertheless he talks incessantly. Harding
                comes closer shows him the log-book. Both of them are reading: Close-up: The
                log-book. A page: Second day: July 13 A sailor has fallen ill with a fever. Course:
                SSW. Direction of wind: Third day: July 14 Mate is talking strangely. He says there
                is an unknown passenger below deck. Course SE. Direction of wind NE. Volume of wind
                3.6. Normal shot: Sievers and Harding are looking at each other. Sievers' white
                beard is trembling. They continue reading. Tenth day: July 22 Rats in the ship's
                hold. Danger of plague. Normal shot: Harding has been reading this aloud. Now
                Sievers understands at last. He points to the book with his finger. Danger of
                plague! That's what it is. Dan- ger of plague, he calls out. Title: Danger of
                plague! Go home! Shut all your windows and doors! Deeply frightened, the bystanders
                move away. The women put the ends of their head-scarves into their mouths. Panic-
                stricken .the crowd leaves the room. Fade-out. (Perhaps end of act) </scene>
            <scene num="130"> 15 meters Fade-in A deserted square: Nobody is about. Except in the
                center of the square, the town-drummer with his large drum. Medium close-up: The
                drummer. He beats a mighty roll. Medium close-up: A closed window. The hatch opens
                and a woman's head appears: totally emaciated, sunken cheeks, long dishevelled hair.
                The disease has gripped her too. On her neck the ominous little marks. Medium
                close-up: The drummer has produced a piece of paper and reads it aloud: magistrate
                of this town prohibits any movement of plague-suspects into hospitals to prevent the
                plague from spreading through the streets. The drummer has finished reading and goes
                off. </scene>
            <title>End of Act I</title>
        </act>
        <act num="5"><title>Act V </title>
            <scene num="131"> 15 meters Fade in. A bend in a street A man emerges from a front door.
                He shuts the door behind him. Quickly and with circumspection he chalks a white
                cross on the door. Then goes on. Panning shot: The adjoining house. The man knocks
                hard on the door. From a window above a head looks out. There are still people
                living here. The man moves on. Panning shot: The first house in the side-street. A
                coffin is being carried out. Men carrying it have white bandages over their mouths.
                The man comes along and dr aws a cross on this house, too. Then he walks on,
                following his horrible business. </scene>
            <scene num="132"> 15 meters 2x shaded candle on table near armchair . Ellen's bedroom
                Close-up: Book-cover Inscription (Vampire) See Chapter 1 of book. Dissolve to: Ellen
                by the window, the book on her knees continues reading, overcoming her aversion.
                Chapter II appears. Medium close-up: Ellen is pondering on what she has read. Hutter
                comes into the picture, with agitation almost hostility he grabs the book. Ellen,
                standing now, looks straight into his eyes, turns and points over to the deserted
                house. Compare the following black dress and shawl Hutter, black waist-coat and
                jacket. Ellen's room. Long shot: Ellen by the window. Hutter approaches from the
                door Medium close Suddenly, she grabs his arm, stares out of the window pointing
                out, she shouts: There!!! Her body is tensed up like a bow trembling with
                excitement. </scene>
            <scene num="133"> 3 meters The deserted house Seen through Ellen's window frame. Almost
                at once dissolve to window. Medium close-up: A window, divided into four rectangular
                panes. Light from behind. Stuck to the window, almost completely covering it,
                something looking like a black fourlegged spider. It takes a moment before one can
                make out Nos- feratu's fingers which are clawing the window frame. In the center of
                the body, grinning lasciviously, the waxen face with ratlike teeth. </scene>
            <scene num="134"> 8 meters 2x Ellen's bedroom. Ellen holds frantically on to Hutter's
                hand [shaken] breathing heavily She bends her head back. towards him saying. Title:
                This is how I see it- every evening. . .!!! She bends her head back. She knows all
                she has to know. And there is peace in the knowledge. Hutter has not come to that
                yet. He finds her calm- ness disturbing. He follows the retreating figure with his
                eyes. Medium close-up: Ellen is swaying. Medium close-up: Hutter, despairingly,
                presses his fist against his face. Fade-out. </scene>
            <scene num="135"> 6 meters In front of Hutter's house It is now evening. The
                lamp-lighter comes down the darkening street and lights up the street-lamps. The he
                walks on. ! remains! </scene>
            <scene num="136"> 10 meters Fade-in: Anny's bedroom Long shot: Anny crouching on a
                chaise lounge. Bent over her Harding who is holding her hands and trying to calm
                down the struggling woman who is shaking fitfully. She collapses with exhaustion.
                Then pulls himself together and decides: Title: I will run over quickly . . . I
                shall get Sievers. And he is gone. Medium close-up: Anny, having almost fainted with
                fear, comes to again. She opens her eyes. She lifts her head. No- body around?? Is
                she all alone?? Isn't there some- thing moving about in the corner? Something
                fluttering at the window? Medium close-up: The window, covered by the curtain.
                Behind it the shadow of a giant bat. It grows and grows. Soon it isn't a bat any
                long- er. A vampire! NOSTERATU?! Medium close-up: Anny's body hits the wall. She
                jumps up and pulls the bell. Then half crazed with fear, she runs into the
                background. </scene>
            <scene num="137"> Anny's bedroom. Long shot: Night. Servants running to and fro in the
                direc- tion of the bedroom. 137a The bell is ringing. 137b Servant's room. A servant
                asleep doesn't hear, turns over in his sleep </scene>
            <scene num="138"> 3 meters Anny's Bedroom Anny pressed close to the wall. Servants are
                rushing in. There! She shouts pointing to the window. Like a flock of chicken the
                women are huddling together. Anny rushes over to them, but they are already so
                gripped by fear that they imagine her fingers, which they are trying to push back,
                to be the vampire's claws. Shrieking, they run off in all directions. The door is
                slammed shut. Anny beats against the door . She is waiting for the horror, but she
                doesn't want to see it, much r ather die first. She grabs a table cloth and covers
                her head and neck. Then she collapses. Fade-out. </scene>
            <scene num="139"> 3 meters Fade-in. Ellen's bedroom Daytime. Ellen by the window . .
                .looking out. She stands motionless. Paralysed by misery she witnesses the daily
                scene of wretchedness. </scene>
            <scene num="140"> 8 meters Street in front of Hutter's's house Ascending. In the
                distance, a strange procession is wandering across the street. One coffin after
                another carried by survivors. Past Hutter's house, towards the procession, a man is
                dragging himself along, tired to death. She supports himself by a stick. He catches
                sight of the distant procession and lifts up his hands to heaven in misery. </scene>
            <scene num="141"> with window -frame Ellen Ellen's room. Ellen, on the point of
                fainting, turns away from the window She cannot bear the sight of this wretchedness
                any longer. She sinks into a chair, resting her head in her hands. Close-up: The
                book, open. She has been reading it for days Close up: A page of the book: ONLY IF A
                CHASTE WOMAN CAN FEARLESSLY MAKE HIM MISS THE FIRST CROWING OF THE COCK WILL HE
                DISINTEGRATE IN THE LIGHT OF DAWN Close-up: Ellen lifts up her head, staring into
                space like a visionary. She knows. She shuts her eyes. Fade out. </scene>
            <scene num="142"> 3 meters Fade-in. In front of Harding's mansion.. Medium close-up: The
                porch. Harding - haggard - a broken man, comes out. He closes the door and supports
                himself against the door-post. His hand reaches up, paints a black cross on the door
                . . .and falls down. His hollow eyes refrain from looking at his work . . . again .
                . . they cannot bear to see the symbol. He moves forward with a glazed look in his
                eyes. Fade-out. Harding: black cape, dark trousers </scene>
            <scene num="143"> 7 meters Fade-in. In front of deserted house Street A group of
                emaciated men with a fanatical look about them are standing around. An
                unkept-looking woman is haranguing them. They are raising their fists. Title: He has
                been seen! He ran out of the house! He strangled the attendant! </scene>
            <scene num="144"> 8 meters Well in the market-place Two ancient women are sitting by the
                well. Death has no terrors for them. Since every new day is a present to them.
                Close-up: The are whispering to each other; their heads are trembling. Title: In the
                deserted house. . . that's where it is hiding. He strangled him. The vampire. Medium
                close-up: Further back agitated people are running across the square, shouting
                excitedly to one another. The two woman turn around gesturing ˚ercely. The clench
                their bony fists threateningly. Harding can be seen behind the well. He has heard
                everything. Close up: He utters a bitter and mocking laugh. Long shot: Harding walks
                on. 144a 10 meters Street shot from above: Crossing. Crowd gathering from all sides,
                then moving in one direction. Close-up: A street-corner with a man who points at
                something above. People rush up to him; they all turn to face the same way, look up,
                make threatening gestures Somebody throws stones. </scene>
            <scene num="145"> Gable of a house A figure is crouching on a roof-top </scene>
            <scene num="146"> (?) Medium close-up: It is Knock. He is looking down with a sneer on
                his face and pokes out his tongue A stone whizzes part him. He suddenly gets up and
                clambers off. </scene>
            <scene num="147"> 8 meters Ellen's bedroom Ellen in an old armchair, busy embroidering a
                cushion in the cross-stitch manner of the 1840s An inscription reading: I LOVE YOU
                She puts down her work, resting her head. Tired, she falls to day-dreaming. Then she
                lights a lamp. Medium close-up: Ellen takes up her work again, determined to finish
                it. </scene>
            <scene num="148"> Evening 4 meters Back of deserted house. The street is empty. Knock
                jumps down a wall and runs off. In the distance some men appear, chasing him. They
                catch sight of him and rush af ter him. </scene>
            <scene num="149"> 8 meters Meadows outside the town Shot against a wide expanse of sky.
                In the distance running figures, no more then silhouettes (Turn slowly) Knock in
                front. His pursuers following a long way behind. </scene>
            <scene num="150"> 3 meters Fields. Evening mists. Cornfields waving in the wind.
                Suddenly, right in front between the ears of corn head. Dishevelled hair. Then a
                bony back The heads turn around slowly. It is Knock. </scene>
            <scene num="151"> 3 meters A lane between fields. The landscape has grown dim in the
                evening light. The men chasing Knock are approaching. They stop. They seem to have
                lost the tr ail. Suddenly, one of them sees something. He opens his eyes wide,
                shouting: there!!! They all look one way. They dash off in that direction. </scene>
            <scene num="152"> 10 meters Cornfield, Long-shot: In the distance one can still the back
                and dis- hevelled head. Is it Knock? He seems not to hear or see his pursuers. The
                men are coming near, rushing towards him across the field. They lift their sticks
                and fists. </scene>
            <scene num="152 continued"> Medium close-up A scare-crow. A black coat is dangling on a
                stick. Bits of straw and tattered rags. The men fall on it in the disappointment.
                Suddenly they stop. There! What can that be !!! Long-shot: A hundred feet away a
                head has appeared. Then the f igure of a man. It is moving away quickly. The chase
                starts up again. Fade-out. </scene>
            <scene num="153"> 3 meters Title: Night Deserted house. Medium Nosferatu at the window.
                close-up: Dissolve </scene>
            <scene num="154"> 8 meters 2x Ellen's bedroom Medium close-up: Ellen wakes up. She sits
                up in bed, listening as if she had heard somebody calling her. She gets up, walking
                as if pulled by invisible threads. Long shot: She goes over to the window. In the
                fore- ground Hutter asleep in an armchair, look- ing worn out. Medium close-up:
                Ellen is clinging to the window. She sees. </scene>
            <scene num="155">. 3 meters Deserted house. Nosferatu at the window. He raises his arms
                slowly. </scene><scene num="156"> Ellen's room Medium close-up: Ellen is about to
                collapse by the window. Shaking with fear she struggles violently with herself. The
                last battle. Twice her hands comes up to open the window and drops down again
                weakly; then, with sudden determination, she pulls herself up dead straight and
                deliberately throws the window wide open. </scene><scene num="157"> 4 meters
                Deserted house. Medium close-up: Window Nosferatu moves away from the window, turns
                around and disappears. </scene>
            <scene num="158"> 4 meters Ellen's room. Close-up: Ellen trembling with fear and
                apprehension </scene>
            <scene num="159"> Deserted house Medium close-up Locked-up gates Suddenly the gates
                swing open: Nosferatu appears </scene>
            <scene num="160"> 12 meters 2x Ellen's room. Medium close-up: Ellen is covering her face
                with her hands, seized with mortal fear. Long shot; window moves out of picture
                Ellen at window. She wants to call for help. She staggers forward. She stops in
                front of Hutter. One last moment of indecision. Then she wakes him up. Hutter jumps
                to his feet. He catches the trembling figure in his arms. and carries her over to
                the sofa. She begs him, hands raised as if in prayer: Title: Bulwer . . . Fetch
                Bulwer! She entreats him to go. Hutter takes her hands, she quickly kisses his head,
                Then he rushes out. </scene>
            <scene num="161"> 3 meters In front of Hutter's House. A path bordered by flowers.
                Hutter rushes out. Trousers, pleated shirt, collar without tie. No hat no waist
                coat. </scene>
            <scene num="162"> 5 meters Ellen's room Long shot. Ellen is still looking in the
                direction she saw Hutter leave, then she gets up and walks toward the window. </scene>
            <scene num="163"> Deserted house. Long Shot: Nosferatu is walking forward and moves out
                of the picture. The house looks more deserted than ever! In front of Hutter's house
                Nobody is about. Nosferatu is approaching. He comes to a halt. (He is preparing to
                jump, looks up) He enters the house. Ellen's room Ellen turns around suddenly. She
                is shaking with fear, anticipating the horror about to happen. And it is coming - -
                slowly, tensed like a predatory animal. She recoils, moves backwards step by step,
                and step by step it follows her Heart! - Hand </scene>
            <scene num="166"> 6 meters Bulwer's laboratory (Living room) In addition to the already
                familiar fish tanks there is a large telescope by a window. A profusion of
                antiquated scientific gadgets, globes etc. A lamp is burning. Bulwer asleep in
                dressing-gown and night-cap in the armchair. Cages with birds and all kinds of
                animals. Hutter rushes in. He wakes Bulwer, begs him to come with him. Bulwer starts
                to get dressed. </scene>
            <scene num="167"> A municipal building on the period (town hall) A large crowd is
                gathering in front of the town hall. Knock has been captured. More people keep
                pouring in from all sides. Omitted </scene>
            <scene num="168"> 5 meters An office room inside the town hall Sievers rushes in
                excitedly from the adjoining room accompanied by a man who has brought him the news.
                From the other side Knock is being brought in. The lunatic is trembling with fear.
                exit </scene>
            <scene num="169"> 4 meters Ellen's room Night. Ellen in bed, the strangler is at her
                throat, his fingers clawing her arms. Her eyes, widened in mortal fear, have a
                glazed look. Then she seems to have heard something. </scene>
            <scene num="170"> A cock jumps on to a still-life farm implements. He flaps his wings,
                puffs up his throat and her- alds the morning. </scene>
            <scene num="171"> 6 meters Siever's lunatic's cell Knock Inside the town hall Knock at
                the window, held by two men. Trying to ward them off, he shouts anxiously: Title:
                The master . . . the master . . .! </scene>
            <scene num="172">
                <loc>Ellen's room</loc>. <dir>Nosferatu raises his head. He looks drunk with
                    pleasure. Ellen eyes are full of terrible fear. She must not allow Nosferatu
                    just to go. She pulls her arms around him: he cannot resist and bends his head
                    over her again.</dir> Omitted </scene>
            <scene num="173">
                <cam>3 meters</cam>
                <loc>The sun is rising over the small town.</loc>

            </scene>
            <scene num="174">
                <loc>Ellen's room</loc> Ellen's last moment of apprehension. <loc>There, isn't that
                    a flicker of sunlight on the wall over her bed?</loc>
                <dir>Here eyes light up hopefully and remain fixed on this first sign of the new
                    day. She stretches out her hand for it. And look: it is moving downwards.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="175"> 5 meters <loc>Street with front gardens</loc>
                <loc>The long shadows of sunrise</loc>. <loc>Nobody is about</loc> Then
                    <dir>shoulders of Hutter and Bulwer appear. They are hurrying on and turning
                    into a side street.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="176"> 8 meters <loc>Ellen's room</loc>
                <loc>The bed is bathed in sunlight</loc>. <dir>Ellen's eyes are full of
                    anticipation</dir>. Has she sacrificed herself in vain? Suddenly the horrible
                figure jerks himself up. He looks about in amazement. He clutches his heart. The
                bestial tenseness of his bearing relaxes. For a moment he stands, legs apart, as if
                trying to regain his balance. He clutches his heart again and falls on his knees,
                his face turned to the sun, distorted by pain. </scene>
            <scene num="177"> Siever's lunatic cell Knock <cam>5 meters</cam>
                <loc>Town hall</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up</cam>: Knock, in a straitjacket, alone in the sunlight which is
                falling through a barred window. He is mumbling disconnected words: Title:
                    <title>The master . . .the master . . . is dead.</title>
                <dir>His head sinks on to his chest.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="178"> 8 meters <loc>Ellen's room</loc>
                <dir>Nosferatu on his knees, supporting himself with one hand on the ground. He
                    raises the other in the direction of the sun to shield himself from the light
                    that brings him death. But he cannot hold out against the sun. His fingers, his
                    hand, his arm are dissolving in the light. The sun seems about to strike his
                    heart. Now his body is dis- integrating in the light. Ellen throws up her hands
                    triumphantly calling</dir>: Title: <title>Hutter!</title>
            </scene>
            <scene num="179">
                <cam>4 meters</cam>
                <loc>In front of Hutter's House</loc>
                <cam>Shot looking out from the doorway into the distance</cam>. <dir>Bulwer and
                    Hutter are running, not just walking into the house</dir>. </scene>
            <scene num="180">
                <cam>8 meters</cam> Ellen in bed. In anticipation, her hand reaches out for Hutter.
                Hutter comes rushing in, falls on his knees by the bed. He t akes hold of her hand.
                    <cam>Close-up</cam>: Her hand grasps his, the it lets go weakly and drops away.
                Ellen's head falls over - - - - Bulwer is standing at the window, hands behind his
                back looking out. <title>THE END</title>
            </scene>
        </act>
    </script>
</root>
