<!--<?xml-model href="nosferatu_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>-->
<root>
<script>
<head>
<title>N O S F E R A T U</title>
by
Henrik Galeen
<note>
(F.W. Murnau's hand annotations and scenes additions and location markers are in Bold Print)
</note>
</head>
<act num="1"><title>ACT 1</title>
    
<scene><annot>8 meters    location shot: Wismar</annot>
<sn>Fade in.</sn>    <p>Townscape

    View over the roof's of a small old-fashioned

    town built in the style of the 1840s.  The sun 

    shines peacefully on pointed gables and

    leafy squares.</p>        

<sn>Fade out</sn>    <p>Two shot, one from the church tower onto the town the

    other from the harbour over towards the town.

    1st: view of Lübeck.

    Dissolve to harbour of Wismar</p></scene>


<scene num="23">    4 meters    2x

Fade-in

Outside a window   There are flowers in green window-boxes.  On the 

    window sill a kitten is playing in the morning sun. 

    With graceful movements she tries to catch a ball 

    that dangles from a thread.  Now the ball is being 

    pulled in through the window.  The cat jumps in

    af ter it.

</scene>
<scene num="34">    Ellen's sitting room    7 meters    2x

Small neat kitchen   The morning sun casts the shadow of a window 

    frame onto the floor.  Ellen, by the window, is 

    pulling the thread with the ball, the cat follows it 

    with a leap.  Then she puts the little animal on her 

    arm. 
Playing with it she sits down on the window      
    sill bathed in sunshine and looks out dreamily. 

    She squats on the floor opposite the animal and 

    plays with it. Her dressing gown moves in the breeze, 

    her big  child-like eyes a laughing.

</scene>
<scene num="34a">   20 meters    Hutter    white jabot    blue waist coat.

A small sitting room (attic)  Poor-looking and tidy. A bed, a chair in the

    period style.  Hutter is standing in front

    of the mirror.  He is about to put his jack-

    et on.  He pauses to listen, takes a look 

    through the side window. Smiling happily

    he finishes dressing and goes out.

4a  A small ˜ower garden   
Shot from above. Hutter appears, gardening 
    knife in hand, looks up  front of Hutter's house  

    beaming with joy. He finds a clump of carn-

    ations, cuts the flowers with a quick gesture 

    and makes a bouquet.

</scene>
<scene num="5">
The small kitchen   Ellen, still playing with the kitten, hears Hutter  

    coming and jumps up.

Shot of cooker  Ellen comes over and begins to busy herself with 

   the sauce pans, with a childlike earnestness towards 

   her house-wifely duties.

Shot of door:  Hutter is standing in the doorway and laughs and laughs.

   
Hiding the bouquet behind his back, he laughs and laughs
Shot of cooker  Ellen turns around, catches sight of her husband 

   and seems a little ashamed that she hasn't yet made 

   breakfast.  Now Hutter moves closer to her, looks 

   into the sauce pan holds it upside down indicating 

   that it is empty, and looks at her reproachfully.

Title:   Ellen!

   
She is sulking now and trying to placate him. But 
   he pulls out his watch; it is late already; he has to go.  

   He kisses her good-bye, but she calls him back again 

   to confess that she hasn't got any money left to do 

   the shopping.  He pulls out his purse with a sad look 

   and holds it up: there is nothing in it!  They both sigh.  

   He leaves with a heavy heart.  The moment she is

   alone she takes a small basket of potatoes, which  

   is all she can find, the last resort of the poor

   house-wife, and starts peeling them.  A potato 

   drops on the floor, the kitten comes up and

    plays with it.

Fade-out   They are rushing towards each other, Ellen throws 

   herself into Hutter's arms

Long Shot  He produces the bouquet, hands it to her beaming 

   all over his face. She is touched then, saddening, 

   she takes the glowers looking at the stems and 

   stroking them.  His voice asks for the reasons of her 

   behavior she says:

Title   Why have you killed them ...

   the beautiful flowers?

   Hutter is taken aback for a moment. He apologizes 

   and kisses her.

   Then she forgives him, they stand in an embrace.

Fade-out   2x
   
</scene>
<scene num="5a">   10 meters Lauenburg

Fade in

Street with front gardens  

Title:   Professor Bulwer

   Professor Bulwer is walking vigorously, yet slowly along the road, enjoying the morning

   and the sunshine.  His stick strikes the ground energetically.

   Suddenly he stops and turns around. Who is following him in such haste? Isn't it Hutter?

   He grasps the passing man by his sleeve; he holds on to it.  Hutter greets him,

   looking pleased.  Bulwer laughs and looking deep into his eyes says:

Title:   Why so hasty , my young friend?  One 

   reaches one's goal soon enough.

   

   

   Hutter, of course, doesn't understand him.  He has to get 

   to office quickly.  He greets him again and again.  Until he 

   manages at last to break free with a laugh and rushes off.  

   Bulwer stands there for a moment, then he resumes the 

   regular rhythm of his walk.

</scene>
<scene num="6">   6 meters Caption:  Knock - a house agent

Fade-in

Dusty cramped office Pale light is falling through tiny blind window-panes 

   into the strange room which is eccentrically 

   decorated with bits of old-fashioned furniture.

   KNOCK is standing at a high desk. People

   call him a house agent.

Close-up   Knock's spindly hunch-backed figure.  Grey hair, weather-

   beaten face full of wrinkles.  Around his mouth throbs the 

   ugly tic of the epileptic. In his eyes burns a sombre fire.  

   He is reading a letter.

Close-up   The letter.  On a sheet of paper decorated on the margin 

   with grotesque vignettes a medley of intricate and quite ill-

   egible signs.

Med. Close-up  Knock seems to be able to make sense of the strange letter,

   for his ugly mouth sets into an understanding smile.  Then 

   he turns and opens the door.

</scene>
<scene num="7">   5 meters

Small room ad-

joining the office  Very narrow and dark, totally without sun. Hutter, 

   buried in files.  Knock looks through the door and

   calls him in.

   
Another clerk is present
</scene>
<scene num="8">   30 meters

The dusty and

cramped office  Knock and Hutter enter.  Knock points to the letter

   with mysterious gestures and tells Hutter:

Title   Count Orlock - His grace - From Transylvania

   wants to buy a beautiful house in our little

   Town

 
Close-up   Knock's demonic face with wide open eyes

Title   You could make a nice bit of money . . .

   It will take some effort, however . . .

   a few drops of sweat and blood. . .

   Perhaps a little blood
.
Closeup   In Hutter's face expressions of mounting joy and

   strange apprehension are fighting each other.

   Yet joy wins in the end.

  

Long shot  Knock digs up and old atlas from the depths

   of the cabinet and opens it. His finger runs

   over a page.

Closeup   The route from England to Transyvania on

   the map.

Long shot  Transylvania? asks Hutter, his eyes suddenly shin-

   ing at the thought of a journey.  Yet Knock has

   turned back to the letter, now reading the 

   last page.

Closeup   The back page of the letter, covered with the

   same illegible squiggles.

Long shot  Knock seems to be able to make sense of this 

   page too.  He turns back to Hutter who is al-

   ready day-dreaming about his journey.

Title   He wants a handsome deserted house.

Long shot  For a moment Knock is lost in thought, then he 

   has an idea.  He limps over to the window.

</scene>
<scene num="9">   4 meters    Window fr ame, take in Knock
  
Section of window View down the street

   The deserted house.  A dilapidated facade. Black 

   and hollow windows.  Not a sign of life. Shadows

   on it.

   
Daytime - Sun
</scene>
<scene num="10">  15 meters

The dusty and 

cramped office  Knock walks back from the window and says to Hutter:

Title   That house...just opposite yours.

   Offer him that!

   Hutter seems to be a little taken aback, but he rallies

   around quickly.  Knock urges him to set out on the

   journey at once, hands him some money and doc-

   uments and pushes him to the door.

Fade-out

   
18 meters     2x   As in scene 8
</scene>
<scene num="11">   Ellen is sitting by the window.  Now she can see him

Room in  Hutter's  coming.  She waves to him.  Her face lights up with joy.

House   She hurries over to the door.  Presently Hutter enters.

   Moved and happy, he puts his arms around her and tells

   her his great news:

Title   I shall go on a journey far far away

   to the country of mountains where

   there are bandits and ghosts still.

   Ellen is startled.  A shadow passes over

   her forehead.  She wants to hold him back.

   But he is not listening.  He has got to

   pack; already he is leaving her.

Fade-out

</scene>
<scene num="12">   15 meters    Frau Schroeder without shawl    saddlebags

The attic room

Fade-in   Hutter is packing his little travelling bag.

   Ellen appears in the door behind him. Sud-

   denly she starts to beg him tearfully, en-

   treating: Do not go!  I am worried about you!

   But he rejects her remonstrations.  Now he

   has finished packing.  He gets up.  Ellen

   realizing that he has made up his mind steps

   back, resigning herself.  But there is fear

   in her eyes.  Seeing her like this he hes-

   itates for a moment.  But then he embraces her

   again with determination, takes up his bag and 

   leaves the room with her.

Fade out </scene><scene num="13"> 15 meters

(Lord)Harding's park Hutter, all ready for the journey, takes his leave

   from Harding and his sister Anny.  Ellen, weeping

   is supported by Anny.

Close-up   The two men.  Hutter, taking both of Harding's

   hands and looking deep into his eyes:

Title   I entrust Ellen to your care.

   Harding promises his friend to look after Ellen,

   she can live here, she will never be alone.

Long shot of

all characters  Hutter gives his hand to Anny and then to Ellen

   One last farewell kiss. At this moment her grief

   is over.  As if she had a premonition she says:

Title   Farewell!  There is no escape left.

   At first they are all startled by these words.  

   Then Hutter breaks away.  Another farewell, another 

   wave of the hand and Hutter vanishes into the park.

   Ellen is staring vacantly into the distance. 

</scene>
<scene num="14">   A number of healthy-looking people are walking

Square with fountain about in the sunshine. Tied to the fountain a lonely

   sattled horse. Hutter appears, mounts the horse

   gives one last backward look and gallops off.

Fade out   

</scene>
<scene num="15">   9 meters Schlesische Hutte

Title   The Carpathian Mountains

   Wild and rocky mountains. Contre jour

Fade-out   
Evening
</scene>
<scene num="16">   10 meters

Long shot  

Outside the Carpathian

inn.   The big mail coach drawn by four horses drives 

   up and comes to a halt.

Shot of door of inn The inn-keeper, a small old Jew, comes out and 

   sees the coach.

Shot of coach:  Hutter jumps out first. He looks around.

Long shot:  The house.  One part of brick-walled living area, the

   other coach house and open stables Shot of coach  

   In the meantime the other passengers have got

   out. Long-haired, black Huzules.  All identically 

   dressed and of identical appearance like ghosts.

   they go into the house.

   The inn-keeper has gone up to Hutter and greets 

   him with an inviting gesture.

Shot of coach  The horses are now unharnessed, the coach is 

   being pushed into the coach house. Night is falling.

</scene>
<scene num="17">   8 meters    servant:  Frau Kurz

Inside the Inn.  A large smoky room with an enormous tiled stove. 

   A central hanging lamp throws out dazzling light

   At tables in the background  the passengers. Hutter

   who came in last, is standing in the foreground, he

   looks around and sits down right in front. At once

   the old servant approaches with a glass and puts it

   down in front of him.  He overcomes a strange anxiety

   that was brought on by the evening mood in a

   strange country and puts on a sudden show of 

   liveliness. He knocks on the table and says:

Title   Quickly, my meal - 

   I must be off to Count Orlock's

   castle.
 
   The servant recoils in horror. The strangely identical

   looking passengers, sitting in the background rise up

   abruptly to stare at him.

Shot of bar  The old hunch-backed Jew pricks up his ears.

   

Long shot  Hutter looks around in embarrassment, then takes up his 

   glass resolutely and downs it in one gulp.

</scene>
<scene num="18">   4 meters    Walddorfsenke

A grassy slope behind the The ground falls away towards the back. Night mists are

inn   creeping up from the valley.  The horses are put out here 

   to graze. Suddenly, they r aise their heads, as if frightened 

   and, scattering, gallop away.

</scene>
<scene num="19">   

Inside the inn
Shot of window:  The passengers, seen from behind are standing by the win-

   dow, looking out apprehensively.  The old servant has not

   go the courage to go up to where they stand and makes the 

   sign of the cross.  Hutter stands alone, looking around. He

   is perplexed and wants to ask what is happening. The old

   servant comes up to him and whispers into his ear.

Title
   
You mustn't go there now
   there are wolves about

   Spend the night here.

   Hutter understands and decides to stay.

Fade-out19a  
Hyena
19b   Horses, panicking

</scene>
<scene num="20">   6 meters

A room at the inn. A tiny white-washed room with sharp angles: a flickering 

   light from the old servant's candle.  Now Hutter enters.

   She puts the candle down, goes out without a word. Her 

   eyes expressing concern for him.

   Hutter alone.  He goes over to the window, throws it open 

   and looks into the starless night.

</scene>
<scene num="21">   (missing from script)

</scene>
<scene num="22">   5 meters

Inside the inn  The pale passengers, now without Hutter in the enormous

   room, look frightened. They, too, are listening to the hor-

   rible howling. They look at each other and are crossing

   themselves in terror!

</scene>
<scene num="23">   20 meters

The tiny white-washed In the light of the candle Hutter, shivering, closes the win-

room   dow. He is no longer sleepy. He walks up and down the 

   room restlessly, stopping in front of a little bookcase.

Medium close-up  Looking for something to distract him Hutter pulls 

   out a book at random.

Long shot  He moves back to the candle, sits down on his bed

   and opens the book. He gets interested in it.

Close up   The book's title page: VAMPIRE

   The page os being turned over.

   THE NOSFERATU

   From the bloody sins of mankind a creature will be born

   which will seek revenge for the sin committed by the 

   parents and visited on their children and children's

   children. Whosoever lusts after blood without reason

   in under his spell, the spell of the vampire NOSFERATU.

Shot of bed Close-up 
Hutter, shaking his head, continues reading
   Book:...grown up on his native soil - from

   which alone he draws his power.

   Hutter shuts the book, having lost interest. It seems confused

   to him. He yawns and puts out the candle.

Fade-out

</scene>
<scene num="24">   12 meters

Fade-in   

Small white room

at the inn  Morning sun is flooding in from the window. Hutter

   wakes up. Yawning like someone who has slept deeply

   but not well. He sits up rubbing his eyes. They fall on

   the book on the bedside table. He reads the title

Close-up   VAMPIRE

Normal shot:  spits on the floor in contempt of the confused rubbish

   and throws the book playfully into a corner.  Then he 

   pauses to listen, goes over to the window to open it. He

   takes a deep breath of the morning air.

</scene>
<scene num="25">   6 meters    Walddorf
   The grassy slope in the morning light. Coachmen and grooms

   are rounding up the horses with long whips and lots of shout-

   ing.

</scene>
<scene num="26">   5 meters
The small room  Hutter steps back from the window. His eyes are laughing, as

   he turns round. He stretches himself happily; then he takes 

   off his shirt, goes over to the washstand, pours water over his

   body. He has a proper wash.

</scene>
<scene num="27">
   Dolny Kubin
In the yard  The old servant, mother to all animals, throws corn to her

   chickens.  There are sparrows, too. Everything is bathed in

   sunlight.

</scene>
<scene num="28">   10 meters
Outside the Inn  The bustle of departure. The horses are in harness. The

   passengers have got into the coach. Now, in the morning

   light, one can see their differences. They are much less uni-

   form than they had seemed the previous nightfall. They

   are chattering noisily to the people who are staying be-

   hind and with the peasants and nosy children who are

   gathered around the coach.

Close-up   The coachman is about to climb onto his seat, but the

   small Jewish inn-keeper holds him back: one passenger

   is missing. They look up to the windows; angry about

   the delay the coachman cracks his whip a few times.

Shot of inn:  Hutter appears in an upstairs window, still only half

   dressed; he gives a wave: I am coming. And disappears

   again.

Shot of door  Hutter comes rushing out with his travelling bag.

    

Shot of coach  He climbs to his seat on the coach-box, the horses 

   start moving.

</scene>
<scene num="29">
Outside the inn  The Huzules take off their hats. The children are waving.

   The old servant has joined them. God bless the travellers. 

   May he guard them against evil spirits. They stretch out their

   hands as if warding them off.

Medium close-up  Hutter breaks into loud laughter.

Fade-out

</scene>
<scene num="30">   12 meters Westerheim
A Mountain range

Long-range shot  In the distance a steep path cutting through the wild

   scenery, on it the mail coach creeping slowly upwards.

</scene>
<scene num="31"> 
  10 meters    road to the Schlesische Hütte
The mail coach

Medium close-up  The mail coach is moving into the setting sun

Medium close-up  A coach window, and old woman. Hutter leans

   out, giving the coachman a push with an umbrella

Title   Drive on!

The sun is setting  Next to her another old woman, identical looking

   She is staring into the abyss. Now the first one turns

   to look in the same direction: two identical faces.

</scene>
<scene num="32">   4 meters   View from Schlesische Hütte

The rocky gorge  Wisps of mist are rising and falling in the last 

   rays of the setting sun. Patches of sun and shade

Fade-out

</scene>
<scene num="33">   10 meters    Close to Arler Hütte

Title   At the crossroad
 
   A carved madonna casts a long shadow across

   the road.  Behind it an old woman on her knees,

   deep in prayer. She lifts her head and looks down

   the road.  The mail coach approaches, the horses

   are pulling with difficulty, breathing hard. She

   seems to ask herself: do they want to drive to the 

   haunted castle? and gets into the middle of the

   road to warn them off. The mail coach stops. 

   Hutter gets off the coach box. Now he stands at

   the crossroad. The passengers are anxious to move

   on gesturing violently to him not to take the

   left fork. But Hutter disregards their shouting

   He waves farewell with his hat and walks briskly off.

33a   Hutter walking past the carved madonna

</scene>
<scene num="34">   8 meters    Vratna Pass

Distant mountains View through the cut made into the rock by the road 

   into the far distance. In the background the fantastic

    castle of Count Orlok in the evening light. One can see

    a steep road leading straight up into the sky. Something

   comes racing down. A coach? A phantom? It moves with 

   unearthly speed and disappears behind a ground swell.

1) Castle Orlok, dissolve 

2) Steep road between

boulders

</scene>
<scene num="35">   4 meters    Near Schlesische Hütte

At the crossroad

Angle as in Scene 33 Mortally fightened, the coachman beats the horses. The

   old woman has disappeared as if swallowed up by the

   ground. Astonished, Hutter follows the vanishing

   coach with his eyes. He is all alone now, standing like this 

   for a while. Then he pulls himself together and walks

   resoltuely along the road on the left.

Fade-out

</scene>
<scene num="36">   Vratna Pass

Fade-in

Carpathian virgin

forest.   The trees are castling long shadows on the forest

   path. Hutter appears. He halts: what's that? Some-

   thing comes racing up, turns around as if moved

   by a hidden force and moving jerkily. Stops dead.

   Hutter likewise. A black carriage. No wheels? Two 

   black horses - griffins? Their legs are invisible, covered 

   by a black funeral cloth. Their eyes like pointed

   stars. Puffs of steam from their open mouths, re-

   vealing white teeth. The coachman is wrapped up

   in black cloth. His face pale as death. His eyes are

   staring at Hutter. Raising his whip he makes an

   inviting, almost commanding gesture. He waits.

   Hutter cannot r ally enough strength to follow 

   the invitation. Yet those eyes assert their power.

   Step by step, as if pulled by invisible threads, 

   Hutter approaches the uncanny creature. He gets

   into the carriage. It reverses quick as lightning,

   dashes off a disappears.   

</scene>
<scene num="37">
   5 meters    At the Vratna Pass, behind Tyer Hora
A fairy-t ale forest  Empty. By the roadside a wise, man-sized raven.

    Its shoulders hunched up. It turns its head listening. 

   Then takes two hops forward and looks down the 

   road. Who's coming? The familiar vehicle sweeps 

   up and past. A young man, holding on desperately,

    sits inside, looking terrified. 
The raven
 follow him 
   with mocking eyes behind glasses.

   
Coach drives at top speed through a white forest
</scene>
<scene num="38">
   5 meters
Long shot of a snake-

like bend.  Valley. Deserted lane. Only a lonely twisted will-tree

    with a straggly top can be seen. Again the carriage

    races past. Like an ancient man who has been 

   disturbed in his rest the tree looks after the vehicle    

   with blank eyes. Isn't there a grin on its mouth?

   Drives over stone bridge across deep gorge

</scene>
<scene num="39"> 
  15  meters    Poczamok
Count Orlock's castle

39a   The arch of a gate in the shade. The silhouette of the 

   carriage drives underneath it at a sharp angle and disappears 

   in the moonlit spacious castle yard. Shot of castle yard

Medium close-up  The porch. The carriage stops in front of it. Al

   -most in a faint, Hutter slides down. As if in a

   whirlpool, the carriage circles round him and

   disappears. Hutter turns around and follows

   it with his eyes. He stands in front of the closed 

   gate, holding his bag.

39b   Then, very very slowly the two wings of 

   the gate open up. Somewhere far back

   in the dark corridor a man can be seen

   standing motionless. He is holding a 

   candle which lights up his chalk-white

   face. He is waiting. Who is that? Hutter 

   bounds up the two steps and stands in

   the doorway. He would still like to go

   back. Yet it is too late now. Hesitantly

   he walks towards the stranger. Behind

   him the gate closes

    </scene><title>End of Act 1</title></act>
<act><title>Act II
</title>
<scene num="40">

Hall.
Medium close-up  In the center Orlok, the candle in his hand. The

    walls of the hall are plunged in darkness from 

   which Hutter's back emerges. He faces the mot-

   ionless figure. It is pale, ghostly creature with

   hollow eyes and thin mouth the lord of the cas-

   tle himself?

Close-up   The face twists into a polite grimace. Sharp r atlike

   teach appear over the lower lip.

Medium Close-up  They are now face to face. It must be the count for 

   this is no servant's gesture with which he now takes

   hold of his visitor's bag.

Title   The servants are asleep

   It is almost after midnight.

  

   Hutter's clenched fingers let go. Bag in hand,

    Orlok turns around. He holds up the candle

   and walks ahead. Hutter follows.

</scene>
<scene num="41">

Gallery of ancestor's

portraits

Medium Close-up  One of the castle owner's ancestors , frontal

   view. For centuries he has been asleep like this

   with his eyes closed. Now something approaches.

   His eyes begin to move. Two figures are passing:

   Orlok and his visitor.   

Long shot panorama He follows them with his eyes.  They walk close to the 

   wall where portrait follows portrait.

</scene>
<scene num="42">   25 meters

Dining room.  Gigantic dimensions. In the center a massive Renaissance 

   table. Somewhere in the distance a fire place. Flanked by

   two armoured figures. Black and motionless. In older 

   times this must have been used by knights for their drinking 

   bouts. Are these their armour? Is that long line that runs

   across the wall a crack in the old structure? Or a lance

   left hanging there? Suddenly, Hutter notices that the count

   is waiting. Quickly he hands him the plans of the deserted 

   house and Knock's letters. With a smile Orlok takes

   them and begs him to take a seat. The meal is waiting.

   Hutter sits down. Orlok lifts up the papers and studies

   them.

Close-up   Orlok reading. The back page of the letter shows a con- 

   fusion of numbers, legible and illegible letters. The holy 

   number seven is repeated several times. In between, cab-

   balistic signs. The spindly fingers holding the letter cover

   up the rest like claws.

Close-up   Hutter is spell bound, his eyes wide-open

Closeup   Over the top margin of the letter Orlok's eyes appear. He

   is looking over to Hutter like a snake about to hypnotize

   it's victim.

Close-up   Hutter eating. He puts a morsel into his mouth. He lifts

   up his eyes. His look turns into a stare. He is unable to swallow

Long shot  The hall with the halo of light in the center; the

   figures are looming above the table.

Close-up   An antique clock with a pendulum. A hammer 

   strikes the hour. The big hand points to 12

   o'clock.

Medium close-up:  Hutter staring into space as if transfixed. After

    the twelfth stroke he drops his knife and fork. 

    The knife grazes his hand, it is bleeding.

Medium Close-up  Quick as lightning the count rushes up to him 

   offering his help. He prevents Hutter from wiping 

   off the blood. The knife might have been poisoned

   The sticky blood should be removed from the cut.

   His lips are sucking at the hand hastily. Frightened,

   Hutter pulls away his hand from his grip. He moves

   backwards 
towards the fireplace.
Medium Close-up  By the fireplace. The Count is polite; he has lost 

   his ghostlike appearance. He is asking for something 

   in a friendly, almost sad manner.

Title   Shall we stay up together

   for a little while? It's a

   long time to go till sunrise . . .

   And during the day I am always 

   out and about.

   The Count sits down. And Hutter cannot resist

   his chivalrous manner. He sinks back into the

   massive chair.

</scene>
<scene num="43">   18 meters
Fade-in

The same hall  Hutter wakes up in the large armchair near the

   fireplace. He can hardly remember the events of 

   the night. The armchair opposite seems to be 

   empty. But there is light on it. Hutter's gaze wanders

   across the hall over to the window.

Shot of window  It is very high and divided up into small panes. 

   Morning light is streaming in.

Shot as before  An old-fashioned window. An ancient hall, very dusty.

   Nothing strange about it. Hutter yawns. His eyes 

   fall on the cut in his hand and he remembers

   a few more things. What has he got on his neck? 

   He touches his throat. Must have been mosquitoes. 

   A mirror! His bag is nearby on the floor. He takes 

   out his mirror and looks at his neck.

Close-up   The mirror shows two red spots on his neck, 

   very close together.

Normal close-up  Why should he worry about a few little spots? he

   thinks and puts the mirror away. He yawns once

   more. But suddenly he stops. What's this? He looks

   at the table, astonished. 

   

Close up:  A still-life of food: fruit, a joint, all kinds

    of gastronomic delicacies.

Normal:   He is overjoyed. He rushes over to the table and begins 

   to eat as if he were starved.

</scene>
<scene num="44">   22 meters    Poczamok

The dilapidated terrace Still eating, Hutter steps out into the sunlight. He looks

   around, seeming relaxed. He holds a sheet of paper

   and a pencil in his hands. Then he casts about for a suit-

   able place and, leaning against the stone wall He begins

   to write a letter.

Close-up:  The beginning of the letter: My dearest, my only one. . .

Normal:   Hutter stands upright, looking at the clouds. Why does

   that stupid mosquito buzzing around his nose stop him

   from concentrating? He catches it quickly. And now he 

   knows how to continue. He puts pencil to paper again.

Close-up:   Part of the letter:...the mosquitoes are a real pest. I have

   been stung at the next by two at once, very close to-

   gether, one on each side...

Long shot:  Hutter keeps writing

</scene>
<scene num="45">   14 meters    Poczamok

Forest near the castle A man on horseback is approaching. He stops occasionally

   and peers over to the castle as if he were scared of it.

Outside the porch: Hutter stands there, waving with the letter. The rider comes

   up cautiously and takes the letter without dismounting

   The he dashes off at a gallop showing signs of great fear.

</scene>
<scene num="46">   15    meters

Fade-in.

Dining room  Orlok is sitting by the fireplace bent over some plans.

   Hutter is standing behind him. Orlok shows more 

   interest in the young man than in the papers lying

   in front of him. Looking over his shoulder he asks for 

   some more information. Hutter rummages among

   the papers in his bag. A little picture falls on the table.

   He wants to hide it quickly, yet Orlok was quicker. He has

   picked it up and is looking at it.

Close up   A miniature portrait of Ellen.

Medium close-up  Orlock asks about the person in the picture. And Hutter

   is forced to answer him.

Close up:  Orlok's eyes open wide. His lips look even thinner than

   before. Contemplating the picture he whispers:

Title   What a beautiful throat your wife has...

Medium close-up:  Hutter is breathing hard. The fear which grips 

   him in the count's presence is replaced by a sud-

   den fear for his wife. He forgets himself and rea-

   ches for the miniature. For the first time he 

   touches Orlok's body. The count jumps up. He 

   raises himself to his full height with triumphant

   determination and a glazed look in his eyes, and 

   says, anticipating the horrors to come with pleasure.

Title   I shall buy the house...

   The handsome deserted

   house opposite yours.

   Quickly, he takes up the contract and signs it. He

   hands it back to Hutter. Hutter bows uneasily and

   retires.  Orlok watches him go, a satanic look has

   come into his eyes. His hands have turned into

   claws.

   
Hutter takes his bag with him
Fade- out:  

</scene>
<scene num="47">   15 meters

Fade-in:   
Candle is burning
A small room in castle Hutter is standing in the middle of the room, 

   quite dazed. He shakes off his misgivings. He de-

   cides to leave tomorrow. He kisses the picture

   and starts to undress, when to his amazement

   he discovers a book in his pocket. The old book

   from the inn. Did the in-keepers wife put it there? 

   Mechanically, he opens it.

Close-up:  The book

   Chapter II

   Night is the vampire's element.

   He can see in the dark

   which is a wonderful ability to have in this world

   half of which is night.

   We humans, however, are helpless and blind at night

Normal   Hutter shuts the book. A horrible thought has 

   occurred to him. He is feverish. Is it this book, 

   these ancient walls which make him believe in

   the existence of ghosts? Did not the count seem

   to have vampire-like claws and rat's teeth. He

   jumps up, first running, the sneaking to the door.

</scene>
<scene num="48">   4 meters
Dining hall

View from door deep 

into the dining hall By the fireplace Count Orlok, no, not Orlock but

   a gigantic vampire, a motionless, sombre watcher

   in the night.

Medium close-up  He looks at Hutter with a fixed glaze.

   

</scene>
<scene num="49">
   6 meters
The small room.

Shot of door:  Hutter. He supports himself against the doorpost. A ter-

   rible realization has dawned on him. Shut the door, shut 

   it quickly! There is no bolt. No lock. He looks around, 

   puts the heavy oak-chair against the door. Is it possible

   to escape?

Medium close-up:  Window. Hutter rushes up and flings it open.

</scene>
<scene num="50">   3 meters    Tegeler Forest
   Night. Undergrowth. A pack of wolves, raising their heads

   howling.

</scene>
<scene num="51"> 
  8 meters
The small room

Long shot:  Hutter falls on his knees by the side of the bid. Hutter 

   clutching the bedclothes, he stares at the door behind which 

   the horror is waiting.

   What is this?

Medium close-up:  Moved by an invisible hand the door opens to half its

   width in one single jerk.

Long shot:  Hutter. Terrified, he covers his eyes with his arms, pulls at

   the bedclothes and shields his eyes. He mustn't see it. He

   mustn't look!

Fade out.

</scene>
<scene num="52">  
6 meters
Title   The same night

Ellen's bedroom at 

the Hardings  She wakes up suddenly. She has been dreaming. As if she

   had seen a vision ... She has a premonition of danger ...

   Now she gets up. Moves over to the window and steps

   out on  to the balcony.

</scene>
<scene num="53">   
6 meters
Harding's study  Night. Harding is sitting at his desk. He hears a noise

   Rushes out.

</scene>
<scene num="54">   

Ellen's bedroom

Medium close-up of door Ellen is perching on the edge of the balcony. Harding  

leading to the balcony rushes into the room. Discovers that the bed is empty.

   He shouts: Ellen!  

Title   Ellen!

   He catches sight of the sleepwalker at the moment when,

   woken up by his shouts, she loses her balance and falls

   over. He runs up to her and gathers her in his arms. He 

   carries her over to the bed. A servant, alerted by the noise

   appears in the door. A doctor! shouts Harding. The ser-

   vant disappears.

</scene>
<scene num="55">  
6 meters
Fade-in.

The small castle room

Long Shot  Hutter in bed, tense and doubled up. Slowly, 

   Nosferatu creeps up on him.

   Irresistible, he bends over the terrified and help-

   less man and buries his fangs in his throat.

Fade-out.

</scene>
<scene num="56">  
7 meters
Fade in.

Ellen's bedroom

Long shot:  Ellen shouts:

Title   Hutter!!!

Long shot:  Ellen in bed ...in delirium. Anny is kneeling by her 

   side. A doctor. Professor Sievers, is taking her pulse.

   Harding

   Ellen trembles like a wounded bird. She doubles 

   up throws herself about and retreats into a corner 

   of the bed.

</scene>
<scene num="57">  
8 meters
The small castle room Night

Medium close-up  NOSTERATU turns his head. He is listening intently 

   as if he could feel - hear the 
terrified
 shouting in
   the distance.

Long shot  NOSTERATU moves away from Hutter's bed. 

   He dissolves into the air! 
leaves the room
</scene>
<scene num="58">  
8 meters
Ellen's bedroom  Ellen is calming down slowly. Her terror turns 

   into apathy. Breathing weakly.

Medium close-up:  She settles back listlessly into her pillows. Sievers 

   can tell the improvement from the pulse-rate 

   and says to Harding:

Title:   Normal congestion of the blood. . .

   caused by an awkward position

   during sleep...

   He has assumed an academic air. His beard

   trembles in his eagerness.

Fade-out.

</scene>
<scene num="59">  
3 meters   Poczamok
   Behind a pointed gable of the castle the sun is

   rising slowly.

Fade-out.

</scene>
<scene num="60">  
7 meters
Fade-in.

The small castle room  The light of dawn is falling through the window

   as though a sky-light and moving along the wall 

   until it reaches Hutter's face, looking half-faint

   -ing, half asleep.

   Suddenly he wakes up 

</scene>
<scene num="60 continued">

   He starts up and clutches his throat. He jumps out of bed,

   clenching his fists, runs over. To the door. Carefully ...he

   looks out

</scene>
<scene num="61">   
6 meters
Dining hall  Daytime.

   The room is empty ...Hutter, pale and hollow-eyed, staggers

   in. He looks around ...nothing. Shaking his head, fists

   clenched with wild determination, he drags himself forward.

</scene>
<scene num="62">   
6 meters
Portrait gallery with 

flight of stairs  Hutter is dragging himself along with difficulty. He goes

   down a few stairs. At the end of the corridor he finds a

   door. He opens it.

62a. A curving gallery Hutter opens one door after the other

exterior

</scene>
<scene num="63">  
15 meters
A vault   Empty and dark.

   In the center of the darkness a black coffin. Hutter has

   pushed the door open and enters. He starts back. He stares

   without understanding. Fear grips him. But he must make 

   certain. Trembling heavily, he lifts up the coffin lid. He

   recoils in horror. Dropping the lid, he retreats into the

   darkest corner. For inside the coffin he has seen, black and

   long, the lifeless body of NOSFERATU. Horror-stricken,

   Hutter almost collapses. Then he rushes out.

Fade-out.

</scene>
<scene num="64">  
3 meters    Poczamok   Vratna Pass   Tatra
Fade in.

Sunset.   Between a line of bizarre tree-trunks evening approaches

   like a ghost...

</scene>
<scene num="65">  
6 meters
Fade-in.

A niche inside the castle 
The small castle room
.
   Hutter is crouched on the floor. His body is twisted with 

   fear. His hair is standing on end ...his eyes are staring. Sud-

   denly, he starts up and listens. Can he hear a noise in this

   desolate place? Could it mean his salvation? With difficulty

   he drags his weakened body over to the window.

</scene>
<scene num="66">  Window frame for out-door shot

   
3 meters    Poczamok
The walls of the castle

seen from outside  Hutter stares from a window.

   He refuses to believe what he sees.

   
The crossbar of a window
</scene>
<scene num="67">  [
12] meters 6 meters Poczamok
   One can see a low-wheeled cart with the two fantastic horses

   harnessed to it. And now:  is it a shadow? A ghost. Nos-  

   feratu. He is moving to and fro, to and fro. From the cart

   to the castle. And back again. Carrying boxes. Black coffin

   like boxes. From the back door of the castle to the carriage

   He piles them up. Box on box. Into a gigantic pyramid.

   All this happens at an uncanny speed.  

   

   

</scene>
<scene num="68">  
3 meters Poczamok
Part of the castle wall Hutter, staring at the phantom with glazed eyes.

</scene>
<scene num="69">  
6 meters Poczamok
Castle yard  The carriage is now loaded. Suddenly the phan-

   tom jumps on to the topmost box and dis- 

   appears inside it. Instantly the horses dash off

   with the cart at lightning speed. The big gate

   closes behind them with a bang.

</scene>
<scene num="70">  
8 meters
The small castle room Hutter jumps back from the window.

Title   Ellen!

   

   NOSFERATU is on his way.  Ellen is in danger. 

   He has to hurry. Save Ellen. Ellen! Ellen!.

   Suddenly, he starts tearing down the wall-hangings

   and tearing 
up the bedclothes
. He tears them
   making long pieces and knotting them into a rope.

Fade-out.

</scene>
<scene num="71">  
10 meters Poczamok
The abyss  Hutter dangling from a window in the castle walls

   on a rope. But the rope is too short.

   Beneath him, the abyss still opens up.

   And yet he risks the drop - dead or alive.

Medium close-up.  So he hurls himself down. Hutter is lying at the

   bottom of the abyss, between trees and boulders.

   Tossing and turning in fever and pain. So he

   tries to lift himself up. But pain seizes him again. 

   Then he faints.

</scene>
<scene num="72">  
10 meters
Fade-in.

By the river Pruth

Waag

   The river flows majestically through the immense

   plain. The scenery is bathed in sunshine.

   All is peaceful.

   Then a large raf t appear s around a bend in the

   river and gloats slowly into view. Boatmen with

   long poles are pushing it with considerable effort.

   At the stern a high pile of boxes. Black, coffin

   like boxes. Stacked into a pyramid. An uncanny

   sight. Indefatigably, the boatmen go on punting

   The raf t is coming closer and closer - like doom.

Fade-out.
</scene><title>End of Act I</title></act>
<act><title>Act III
</title>
<scene num="73">   
12 meters
Title   A Budapest hospital

Hospital Ward  A long line of white beds.

   In the foreground, Hutter. In bandages ...

   his eyes closed.

   The doctor comes to him now.

   He examines him. Questions the nurse

   She tells him about the case:

Title   He was brought in yesterday

   by Huzules who said he had

   fallen down a mountain.

   He is still feverish ...

   As the doctor continues his examination Hutter wakes

   up, opens his eyes.

   There is fear in his feverish look still.

   The nurse hurries up to him to hold him.

   Yet he crawls away to the end of the bed.

   Spreads out his hands to defend himself.

   Suddenly his eyes go dead. He collapses.

   His lips are murmuring something ...

   The doctor bends over to hear what he is saying.

   Hutter muttering to himself

 

Medium close-up:  Doctor and nurse look at each other without 

   understanding.

Fade-out.

</scene>
<scene num="74">  
18 meters
Fade-in.

The port of Varna  At the quayside, ready for loading, and next to other cargo

   the pile of black coffins. Custom officials are examining

   the lettering and papers. They are approaching the boxes.

   The man searches among the papers and hands over the

   freight letters to his boss.

Close-up:   Freight letter

   
Mixed cargo, from Varna to Whitby
   Content: garden soil for experimental pur poses.

Normal shot:  The inspector smiles incredulously. He orders a search!!

   Barefooted dock-workers drag up one of the apparently

   very heavy boxes, heaving and swearing. The inspector

   gives an order.

   They open the lid with difficulty. There is 
earth
 inside!
   The inspector gives another order: turn it out! The workers

   obey.  Sand is falling out nothing but 
 earth
.
   Satisfied, the inspector turns to another pile of cargo.

   Yet in the earth . . .something moves violently ...something is

   alive ...jumps out...horrible animals ...rats!  One of the dock

   workers, who bends over to scoop the scatters earth back

   hits out violently. Did not one of the animals...reeling from

   the blow ... bite his foot? 

Long shot:  The big 
hand pulley
 [steam crane] hauls up one 
   of the boxes and drops it into the belly of the 

   sailing-boat that is anchored at the quay. At the

   ship's stern one can discern a name, underneath

   the baroque figure head; DEMETER

</scene>
<scene num="75">  
12 meters
Title   Professor Bulwer, a Paracelsian, explains

   the nature of carnivorous plants

   to his students

The institute

Medium close-up:  Professor Bulwer, surrounded by a few students, 

   quiet and simple people. They are listening to his

   lecture. Now he points emphatically to a plant

   with a very strange shape.

Close-up:  A flower. Its petals reaching out like tentacles.

   Motionless. Now. And insect. Hovering, attracted 

   by the scent . . . settles on the colorful calyx.

   There in a flash the tentacles have gripped it.

   The insect is caught. Its struggling is in vain. With

   irresistible force the flower has drawn it into the

   recesses of the calyx . . . 

Medium- close-up: Bulwer pointing at the flower. Slowly his

   lips are moving:

Title:   The patient who came in

   yesterday has had an attack.

</scene>
<scene num="77">   
12 meters
Lunatic's cell  Sievers and the attendant stop short at the door

   way. Straining their eyes to see into the semi-

   darkness. There, in the corner. Something moves

   slowly. It is a man. Now his face is in the light.

   Like a panther preparing to leap, his ferocity re-

   strained, he raises himself up slowly. His crazed

   burning eyes staring at Sievers. And now we re-

   cognize him at last . . . it is Knock!!!

   Suddenly, in one leap, he is at the window. Sievers

   is startled, says something to the attendant. Who

   prepares the straitjacket be brought along.

   Yet the expected attack does not come.

   Knock remains at the window, arms jerking, he 

   begins . . . to catch flies which he puts into his 

   mouth. Horrible food. The madman's face twists

   into a grin that resembles distant lightning. His

   swollen lips are murmuring something:

Title:   Blood is life! Blood is life!!!

  

   Suddenly, the madman starts up and throws himself

   with all his might on the unsuspecting Sievers. Who 

   can barely ward him off. But the attendant comes to

   his help quickly and throws the straightjacket over

   the raging man's head.

</scene>
<scene num="78">  
8 meters
The Institute:  Bulwer, in a quiet, scholarly manner with his students. He 

   points to an aquarium.

Close-up:  On a piece of rock in the water hangs a small polyp. Now 

   it stretches out its tentacles, grabs a small fish and pulls it 

   up to its mouth. It is almost transparent, colorless and of 

   a jelly-like consistency.

Title:   And this one . . .a polyp with tentacles . . . 

   transparent . . . almost incorporeal . . .

   almost a phantom . . .
 
</scene>
<scene num="79">  
8 meters
Lunatic's cell.

Close-up   On the floor, in his straitjacket, whining pitifully, mad Knock.

   His face. Turning his sad eyes upwards. He notices something 

   there. His lips form a word:

Title:   Spiders . . . !

Close-up:  A spider-web with a live spider which clutches, vampire-like

   an insect and is sucking its blood.

Normal:   Knock in exultation.

   Sievers stands motionless . . . does not understand.

   Brusquely, he gives an order and leaves.

Fade-out.

</scene>
<scene num="80">  
4 meters
Fade in.  

The graveyard of

Whitby   View from the pier-head towards the shore. In the fore-  

   ground the surging sea. Further back, where the shore rises 

   steeply, the graveyard of Whitby.

Closer:   The graveyard. Afternoon light. In front of the graveyard 

   a long row of benches. People are strolling up and down 

   looking out on to the sea . . . sitting on the benches and

   enjoying the view.

Medium close-up:  A bench, somewhat apart from the others. Ellen is

   sitting there. Dreamily, her eyes searching a distant country 

   beyond the sea. She seems to be  in an anxious day-

   dream about her distant lover. Now she shuts her eyes, 

   because tears are welling up.

</scene>
<scene num="81">  
4 meters    Croquet?
In Harding's Park  Harding, youthful and athletic, is batting. The shuttlecock

   flies high up into the air. Anny, in a light dress, shouts with 

   joy . . . catches it . . .  throws it back. The shuttlecock

   flies backwards and forwards. It is a picture of health

   and light.

</scene>
<scene num="82">   
6 meters
At the park gates.   The postman, a small old man, rummages

    in his leather bag and produces a letter 

    which he hands with an air of importance

    to Harding's servant who is as old and 

    wizened as he. Before he leaves, the post-

    man points to the stamp which seems to 

    be of special value, lifting up his eyebrows:

    This letter has travelled ar . . . it comes

    from a very remote country. The two old 

    men bend over the rare letter. Then the

    old servant takes it in.

</scene>
<scene num="83">   
6 meters
In the park   As the servant approaches. Harding 

    and Anny stop playing. Anny takes the

    letter, reads the address and runs to her

    brother. It is for Ellen, she says, point-

    ing into the distance. Shall we take it

    to her straight away. Harding agrees,

    they hand their rackets over to the ser-

    and walk off.

</scene>
<scene num="84">   
3 meters
   
At the graveyard

Medium close-up:   Ellen is still sitting there, looking over 

    the vast waters, lost in her sad longing

    thoughts.

</scene>
<scene num="85">   
3 meters    Heligoland
The sea    Distant view over the sea. A sand bank 

    skirted by rocks, jutting out into the 

    surf waters.

</scene>
<scene num="86">   
12 meters
At the graveyard.   Harding and Anny are approaching.

    They are joining the lonely Ellen. shak-

    ing hands and trying to cheer her up.

    Guess what we have brought you! They

    show her the letter. Ellen trembles.

    She takes the letter quickly and tries to

    open it! I cannot do it. Gladly and quickly,

    Anny takes over. You'll see, he is safe and 

    sound and sends you good news. She 

    starts to read it gives a joyful laugh, she

    was right. All is well. The worries were 

    unfounded Happily she gives Ellen the 

     letter. But barely has she read the letter

    when Ellen's face assumes an expression

    of hurt certainty. Does she derive evil 

    premonitions from these lines?

Close up:   The letter.

    the mosquitoes are a real pest. I have been

    stung on the neck by two at once, very

    close together, one on each side . . .

Normal:   Ellen's face is distorted as if she were suffering  physical

   pain. Harding and Anny are perplexed.

</scene>
<scene num="87">

Title:   GALAZ

The port of Galaz

at night.   The 'Demeter' is anchored off the jetty. Nobody is about

   on the quay. A stormy night, strange uncertain light. Sud-

   denly - a gentle movement from the ship down the gangway

   to the shore . . . rats . . .

Fade-out:  
The coffins are reloaded
</scene>
<scene num="88">  
10 meters
The hospital at Budapest Hutter, dressed, stands in front of his bed. He looks pale 

   and weak still, yet full of resolution. The nurse notices his

   unsteady stance. She fusses around him. You ought to stay 

   a few more days! Have some more rest! But he wards her

   off. His gestures are restless and fluttering, a strange force

   has taken possession of him.

Title:   I have to get home by

   the shortest possible way!
!
   So he says goodbye, disregarding the nurse's advice, thanks 

   her for her care and goes out quickly.

</scene>
<scene num="89">
Title:   Constantinople

The port.  Night. Wild dogs are barking from the debris in the street 

   up to the distant firmament, writhing in the mud like snakes.

Focus on quay:  The "Demeter" at anchor. What's scuttling over there? . . . 

   A shadow from the ship to the land . . . rats. . . one. . . 

   four. . . ten . . . and endless stream . . .the carry terror 

   with them.

</scene>
<scene num="90">  
8 meters    Polnischer Kamm    Non-stop rain
   Entry to the Vratna Gorge

Title:   In the Hungarian plain.

Coach station in the Pusta The mail coach is arriving at top speed. The coachman whips

   his exhausted horses into a last effort. The coach has barely

   stopped when Hutter jumps off. He calls for more speed. Now

   fresh horses are being brought along.

   Hutter joins the grooms and tells them to hurry on! To hurry

   on!

   The tired horses have been taken out of harness and are being

   led to the stable. Bring fresh horses! Hutter gives a helping

   hand. Now the straps are done up. The coachman blows his

   horn. Some late-comers appear. They get into the coach. Hutter

   is the last. And the heavy coach rumbles off, the horses gallop-

   ing, sparks flying from the hooves, dust rising, into the pathless

   country.

Fade- out.  
Hutter leads a limping horse through
 

</scene>
<scene num="91">   

Fade-in:

The port of Constantiople  

Long shot.   In a fresh breeze, the "Demeter" emerges from 

    the confusion of mast-heads and gains the open 

    sea.

</scene>
<scene num="92">    
15 meters
Lunatic's cell   In a stupor, Knock is perching on his bunk. The

    attendant holding a broom, is about to leave the cell.

    At this moment Knock lifts his eyes. With a look

    of artful cunning and with rigid concentration he 

    follows the attendant's movements. Now, he seems

    to have discovered an opportunity; softly, he 

    sneaks up on the unsuspecting man and takes away

    the newspaper that sticks out of his pocket. The

    attendant does not notice and shuts the door behind

    him. The moment Knock is alone he unfolds the

    paper trembling with expectancy and starts read-

    ing. searching for something with wide-open eyes.

    Now he has found what he was looking for. He

    is riveted to this passage.

Close-up:   The Newspaper

                            PLAGUE

    In Transyvania and in the Black Sear ports of

    Varna and Galaz a plague epidemic has started. 

    Young women in particular fall victim to it in

    large numbers. All the victims show the same

    peculiar wound marks on the neck whose origin

    is still an enigma to the Doctors

    The Dardenelles have been closed to all ships sus-

    pected of carrying the epidemic. It is out of the

    question that the epidemic will reach Western 

    Europe.

Medium close-up:   Knock's mocking, triumphant face assumes an 

    expression of demonic grandeur. He straightens

    himself up, lifts up his head, raises his arms as if

    greeting the evil.

</scene>
<scene num="93">   
8 meters    North Sea
Title:    Open Sea

Sea.    The Mediterranean. In the distance the "Demeter"

    sailing through the waters gleaming in the even-

    ing light.

Dissolve. Medium close-up  The ship's deck

    The ship's mate is running up the companion-way

    in great agitation and crosses the deck on his way 

    to the captain's cabin.

</scene>
<scene num="94">   
8 meters
In the captain's cabin The captain of the 'Demeter' bent over maps, making en-

   tries in the log-book. The mater enters and reports excitedly:

   

Title:   Below deck a sailor has fallen ill.

   He is talking in a fever.

   The captan looks up, shocked. He leaves his work and fol-

   low the mate.

</scene>
<scene num="95">   
12 meters
Below deck.  In the background the ship's hold. Among other cargo in

   the deep darkness the coffins. To be seen through an open

   door. In the foreground the crew's cabin with hammocks

   In one of them the delirious sailor.

Medium Close-up:  Captain and mate go up to the patient who stares at them 

   as if they were ghosts. He seems to listen intently. Every 

   noise makes him start.

Shot of hold  Brooding, intense darkness. The lid of one of the coffins

   seems to open a little.

Medium close-up:  The captain, more angry than concerned, advises the patient 

   in his uncouth sailor's way to have a strong drink. Promptly

   the mate produces his bottle and give it to the patient. The

   smell seems to wake him up from his lethargy and he takes

    a long sip. The captain tells him to have a good rest and

   goes out again with the mate.

   The sailor alone. His eyes wandering . . . 

   Suddenly, they remain fixed, as if spellbound, on the door

   leading to the hold.

   In horror he sits up and remains in a crouching position

   as if turned to stone.

Pan to the door lead-

ing into the hold.  There, horrible and awe-inspiring, stands NOSFERATU

   And . . . he . . . approaches.

Fade out

</scene>
<scene num="96">  
10 meters  Hornunger Moor    Lünebur ger Heide
Wild and desolate scenery In the distance a galloping horseman on the plain. He

   comes closer and closer . . . moving at tremendous speed.

   It is Hutter.

Dissolve

Medium close-up:  Hutter, standing near his horse and examining its injured

   hoof. With a desper ate gesture, he lets go of it. Yet he has

   made his decision. He must go on. He takes the horse by

   the reins and walks on, dragging the limping animal after him.     

</scene>
<scene num="97">   
12 meters
Title:   The gulf of Biscay

On deck, the 'Demeter' Evening. In the last light of the sun captain and mate are about

   to push the shrouded corpse of the last sailor over the railing.

   They have covered their mouths and noses with cloths for

   protection.

Shot of ship's side  The corpse is slid down into the water by ropes.

On deck.   For a moment the two last survivors pause in quiet contem-

   plation of the horror of death. Suddenly, the mate's body

   stiffens, he has made a resolution. For a short moment, he 

   shuts his eyes and tries to master the horror that is rising up

   inside him. Then he pulls himself together, tears the cloth 

   off his face, takes up an axe and, brandishing it in the air,

   calls out:

Title:   I'm going down!!!

   If I haven't come back

   in ten minutes . . .
 
   With the courage of a desperate man he hurries over to the

   companion-way.

</scene>
<scene num="98">   
12 meters
Below deck.  There are the black boxes. They are the man's target. He 

   lifts his axe at the first one and shatters its lid. There it is:

   He is tempted to retreat.

   Rats! All round his ankles he feels the crawling of horrible

   creatures. Yet he pulls himself together for a second time.

   Another box, smashed by a second blow. And the same

   thing happens again: rats! only rats! He is wading through 

   wriggling bodies which surround him from all sides. Yet he 

   withstands the horror. There, a third box.

Close-up:  The mate. In despair, foaming at the lips, he prepares for the

   third blow.

Long shot:  The axe falls from his hand. His hair is standing on end.

   Quick as lightning NOSFERATU rears up from the box.

   Now the mate is finally overcome by horror . . . Covering

   his eyes with his hands he runs upstairs, crazy with fear.

   Slowly and steadily, NOSFERATU is approaching.

</scene>
<scene num="99">   
8 meters
Fade-in.

On deck   The captain is guarding the helm. Then from the hatch, the 

   mate emerges . . . his hair has turned grey . . . his face looks

   crazed . . . he is foaming at the mouth . . trying to escape. . . 

   he sways . . .turns deliriously in a circle . . .loses his sense of

   direction. . .does not see the railing. . . and overshoots it.

   Falling head first.

   The captain watches in horror. Now he is lef t all alone. But his

   face remains determined. He picks up a rope and ties himself to

   the helm, not to be tempted to leave. Thus he awaits the horror. . .

Fade out. 
</scene><title>End of Act I</title></act>
<act><title>ACT IV
</title>
<scene num="100">  
5 meters    Heligoland
Fade-in.

A cliff by the coast Night, roaring surf.

   The storm is howling. A gigantic wave moves up, breaks

   the water splashes high up.

   
Moving coach
</scene>
<scene num="101">  
5 meters
Anny's room.  Night. Anny is asleep.

   The storm is pushing against the windows, opening them. The

   curtain is billowing and fluttering in the wind. Anny wakes up.

   Confused, Terrified, she jumps up. She tries to shut the win-

   dow, yet cannot bring herself to do it. The storm is pushing

   her back . . . she recoils. She runs out of the room.

   

   
Waves
   Ellen

   Anny wakes up    Carriage

   Ellen walking forward

   Waves

   Carriage Hutter    Anny wakes up

   Waves

   Ellen Anny

   Boat

</scene>
<scene num="102">  
3 meters
Ellen's room at the

Hardings  The storm is sweeping through the open window. The bed

   is empty . . . Anny enters. She knows at once what has

   happened, - rushes out.

</scene>
<scene num="103">  
4 meters
Roof of Harding's

mansion   Ellen, her clothes fluttering in the wind, her hair like a flag, 

   is sleeping in the storm. She stretches out her arms defensi-

   vely. A white figure against the black night sky.

</scene>
<scene num="104">  XXXXXXXXXX

</scene>
<scene num="105">  
6 meters    Contre jour   North Sea
   High Sea.

Sea.   The storm is raging, enormous tidal waves . . . 

   In the distance a sailing ship, the 'Demeter'

   at full sail, racing to its perdition.

   
Trick
(Scenes 106 and 107

are missing)

</scene>
<scene num="108">  
6 meters
View across the town 

at night   The storm is tossing the trees.

   
Sailing boat moving towards it objective
.
</scene>
<scene num="109"> is missing

</scene>
<scene num="110">  
12 meters    Wismar
Sea   The storm rages violently. The sand bank threatens

   'Demeter', the fatal ship, has closer, still moving at

   full speed.     

   
View from the sea towards the harbor.
   Sailing ships are coming in at full sail.

   Contre jour (wismar). Trick

   Ellen runs out from room

   Broken axle

   Ellen runs through garden

   Ship moves towards objective

   Knock 1

   Ship coming into the harbor

   Hutter running street. Knock

   Ship in harbour. Nosferatu appears

   Hutter running through street

   Nosferatu through gate with coffin

   Door Hutter

   Knock escape

   Nosferatu square or street

   Room]

</scene>
<scene num="111">  
4 meters
Roof Balcony of

Harding's mansion Ellen in Anny's arm. Her hair is fluttering in the wind.

   Ellen stretching her hands towards the sea, as if trying to 

   defend herself.

Title:   I must go home. He is coming.

</scene>
<scene num="112">  

At the graveyard

View over the sea  In the foreground the crosses. In the back sandbank and 

   cliffs. In the distance people, hurrying to rescue the ship-

   wrecked. The sand bank . The ship crashes into it . . . 

   turns over on its side. 

   
View through archway : the sailing boat is moving 
   past.        Weimar

</scene>
<scene num="113">  
4 meters
Lunatic's cell

Long shot:  Knock alone. He drags up a chair . . . to the window. He 

   climbs up on it.

Medium close-up:  Knock pulls himself up by the bars, trying to look out.

   The wind, blowing in, makes his hair stand on end uncannily.

</scene>
<scene num="113a">  
10 meters
The stranded ship  Dead and forsaken. a rope is dangling from the deck. It is

   swaying in the wind.

Medium close-up  An endless number of rats climbing down the swaying rope.

Shot of deck.  The hatch. It opens slowly. NOSFERATU climbs out. He

   carries the last coffin. Remains standing. Motionless. The

   image of death. Then he approaches slowly.

   

   
1) Ship anchored in the harbor. Dissolve
   2)Ship's hatch with a piece of deck.

   Trick:   1) Canvas glides away from hatch.

               2) Hatch lid is lifted.

               3) Rats are rushing on deck.

               4) Nosferatu coffin in arms climbs out.

   

</scene>
<scene num="114">  
8 meters    Lauenburg or Travemünde
Town center.  Trees, shaken by storm. A carriage races up, stops abruptly.

Medium close-up:  Hutter jumps from the carriage.

   An axle is broken.

   The coachman seems at a loss.

   Hutter cannot wait. He leaves the carriage and runs of f.

</scene>
<scene num="115">  
5 meters
Archway with a view of

the harbor:  
Nosferatu enters the town
</scene>
<scene num="116">  
6 meters
The roof of Harding's

mansion.  Ellen's room at the Hardings'

   Ellen and Anny. Ellen suddenly breaks away. Overjoyed 

   as if she had a happy vision she throws her arms up and 

   shouts:

Title:   I must go to him. He is coming!!

   

   She moves off and vanishes.

   Anny wrings her hands in despair.

</scene>
<scene num="117">  
4 meters 
   
   Storm-tossed trees. A white figure comes out of the house. 

   It is Ellen. She is running through the park.

118   
perhaps Lüneberg Street
   Shuttered windows.     Nosferatu striding

118a   Hutter, running along the street. 

</scene>
<scene num="119">  
8 meters
Lunatic's cell

Long shot:  Knock, moving away from the window wall

Medium close-up:  The madman is listening for outside noises, as if he had

   received a signal from the other world . . . triumphantly . . . 

   he whispers to himself:

Titles:   The master is near . . .the master is near . . .!

Long shot:  Suddenly, he listens attentively.

   He creeps over to the door. There he waits expectantly . . .

   The door opens. The attendant appears. He looks around

   the room. Not noticing that Knock is behind him. Knock

   creeps carefully behind his back. Suddenly frightened, the 

   attendant turns around. Knock makes for his throat like 

   a vampire. The attendant falls over. The madman is at his

   throat

   
for a moment only, then he lets go and sneaks out.
</scene>
<scene num="120">  
5 meters
In front of Hutter's house Hutter comes running up. He looks up: no light. He is just

   about to enter when - somebody is calling. He turns around

   Ellen!!!!! They fall into each other's arms.

</scene>
<scene num="121">  Square with fountain    5 meters

   Nosferatu, cof˚n under his arm, is standing in the

   middle of the square. Looking around to orientate 

   himself. Then he strides on.

</scene>
<scene num="122">  
4 meters    2x
Hutter's parlour  Ellen's sitting room

   A lamp is shining. Hutter and Ellen. They are sitting on the

   chaise lounge.  The happiness of being reunited was too much.

   Overpowered by emotion, he sinks down on her arm.

</scene>
<scene num="123">  
4 meters
In front of Hutter's

house   
Nosferatu, staring up
</scene>
<scene num="124">  
6 meters
  
Fade-in.   Hutter and Ellen, on the chaise lounge. He sits up, looking 

   deep into her eyes.

Title:   Thank God . . . you are well  . . .now everything

   has come all right.

   She does not understand him. But the joy of being to-

   gether again is stronger than anything else. And the

   room is bright.

[Scene 125]  
10 meters
Street in front of Hutter's

House   There is nobody about. But in the middle of the street 

   stands NOSFERATU, hidden by the night, carrying the 

   cof fin. Slowly, he turns his head and looks over to Hutter's

   house.

Shot of Hutter's house [There is a friendly light in the window]

The deserted house Empty! Carrying the coffin - Nosferatu appears
   in picture.

Medium close-up:  NOSFERATU. Once more he turns his head. He looks over

   to the other side. The deserted house is over there. He 

   makes for that now, walking slow.

   
Then he goes into the house.
Fade-out.

</scene>
<scene num="126">  
12 meters
On the stranded ship The captain, collapsed in death, is tied to the helm. In the

   foreground, some men, Harding among them, are climbing

   up on deck. They are aghast at the terrible sight.

Close-up:  The dead captain. Tied to the helm in discharge of his duty!

   One hand is still on the helm. The other, holding a crucifix,

   clutches his chest in mortal agony.

   His head sunk back, face distorted. There are two red marks

   on his neck . . . 

Close-up:  Harding. He cannot comprehend the horror . . .

</scene>
<scene num="127">  
6 meters
Sandbank harbor  The stranded ship is in sight. It is night-time

Long shot:  In the blowing wind nocturnal figures . . .townspeople

Close-up:  Down the tilted hulk a man is climbing along a rope.

Medium close-up:  By the light of a torch! the captain of the harbor with a

   number of old people . . . Looking like fishermen. The

   climber approaches and reports.

Title:   Everything has been examined . . 

   No living soul on board.

   The captain receives the report . . .  jots down some notes.

</scene>
<scene num="128">  
10 meters   [Is inserted below]
On board ship.  Night

Long shot:  Back-board with helm.

   Some men are lifting up the dead captain, and carrying

   off the corpse.

Captain's cabin:  Harding alone . . . he finds a book next to a masthead that

   is affixed to the helm. In the light of a dim lantern

   he reads:

Close-up:  A page of the book

   Varna - July 12

   Crew - apart from myself the captain - one helmsman

   mate and five sailors.

   Departing  - for the Dardanelles.

Normal Shot:  Harding shakes his head.

   He is puzzled.

   
On deck. Harding emerges from the cabin
   with the book in his hand.

Fade-out.

</scene>
<scene num="129">  
15 meters
Fade-in:   
Daytime
Port Authority building A large hall. On the walls a number of figure heads

   Models of ships are suspended from the ceiling. The

   dead captain [is carried] in lying in state.

Medium Close-up: Dr. Sievers is examining him. He notices the marks on

   his neck.

   Dr. Sievers turns to Harding. He, too, cannot make 

   sense of this case. Nevertheless he talks incessantly.

   Harding 
comes closer
 shows him the log-book. Both
   of them are reading:

Close-up:  The log-book. A page:

   Second day: July 13

   A sailor has fallen ill with a fever.

   Course: SSW. Direction of wind:

   

   Third day: July 14

   Mate is talking strangely. He says there is an unknown

   passenger below deck.

   Course SE. Direction of wind NE.

   Volume of wind 3.6.

Normal shot:  Sievers and Harding are looking at each other.

   Sievers' white beard is trembling. They continue reading.

   Tenth day: July 22

   Rats in the ship's hold.

   Danger of plague.

Normal shot:  Harding has been reading this aloud.

   Now Sievers understands at last. He points to the book 

   with his finger. Danger of plague! That's what it is. Dan-

   ger of plague, he calls out.

Title:   Danger of plague!

   Go home!

   Shut all your windows and doors!

   Deeply frightened, the bystanders move away. The women 

   put the ends of their head-scarves into their mouths. Panic-

   stricken .the crowd leaves the room.

Fade-out.

   
(Perhaps end of act)
</scene>
<scene num="130">  
15 meters
Fade-in

A deserted square: Nobody is about. Except in the center of the square, the

   town-drummer with his large drum.

Medium close-up:  The drummer. He beats a mighty roll.

Medium close-up:  A closed window.  The hatch opens and a woman's head

   appears: totally emaciated, sunken cheeks, long dishevelled

   hair. The disease has gripped her too. On her neck the 

   ominous little marks.

Medium close-up:  The drummer has produced a piece of paper and reads

   it aloud:

 

   magistrate of this town prohibits any movement

   of plague-suspects into hospitals to prevent

   the plague from spreading through the streets.

  

   The drummer has finished reading and goes off.

    </scene><title>End of Act I</title></act>
<act><title>Act V
</title>
<scene num="131">   
15 meters
Fade in.

A bend in a street   A man emerges from a front door. He shuts the

    door behind him. Quickly and with circumspection 

    he chalks a white cross on the door. Then goes on.

Panning shot:   The adjoining house. The man knocks hard on 

    the door. From a window above a head looks out.

    There are still people living here. The man moves on.

Panning shot:   The first house in the side-street. A coffin is being

    carried out. Men carrying it have white bandages 

    over their mouths. The man comes along and 

    dr aws a cross on this house, too. Then he walks

    on, following his horrible business.

</scene>
<scene num="132">   
15 meters    2x    shaded candle on table 
    near armchair
.
Ellen's bedroom

Close-up:   Book-cover Inscription

    (Vampire) See Chapter 1 of book.

Dissolve to:   Ellen by the window, the book on her knees

    continues reading, overcoming her aversion.

    Chapter II appears.

Medium close-up:  Ellen is pondering on what she has read.

    Hutter comes into the picture, with agitation

    almost hostility he grabs the book.

    Ellen, standing now, looks straight into his

    eyes, turns and points over to the deserted

    house.

    
Compare the following
    black dress and shawl

    Hutter, black waist-coat and jacket.

Ellen's room.

Long shot:   Ellen by the window. Hutter approaches from 

    the door

Medium close   Suddenly, she grabs his arm, stares out of the 

    window pointing out, she shouts: There!!!

    
Her body is tensed up like a bow trembling
    with excitement.

</scene>
<scene num="133">   3 meters

The deserted house  Seen through Ellen's window frame.

Almost at once dissolve

to window.

Medium close-up:   A window, divided into four rectangular panes.

    Light from behind. Stuck to the window, almost

    completely covering it,

    something looking like a black fourlegged spider.

    It takes a moment before one can make out Nos-

    feratu's fingers which are clawing the window frame.

    In the center of the body, grinning lasciviously, 

    the waxen face with ratlike teeth.  

</scene>
<scene num="134">   
8 meters 2x
Ellen's bedroom.   Ellen holds frantically on to Hutter's hand [shaken]

    breathing heavily

    She bends her head back. towards him saying.

Title:    This is how I see it- every evening. . .!!!

    She bends her head back. She knows all she has

     to know. And there is peace in the knowledge.

    Hutter has not come to that yet. He finds her calm-

    ness disturbing. He follows the retreating figure 

    with his eyes.

Medium close-up:   Ellen is swaying.

Medium close-up:   Hutter, despairingly, presses his fist against his face.

Fade-out.

</scene>
<scene num="135">   6 meters

In front of Hutter's house  It is now evening. The lamp-lighter comes down 

    the darkening street and lights up the street-lamps.

    The he walks on.

    
! remains!
</scene>
<scene num="136">   
10 meters
Fade-in:

Anny's bedroom

Long shot:   Anny crouching on a chaise lounge. Bent over her 

    Harding who is holding her hands and trying to 

    calm down the struggling woman who is shaking fitfully.

    She collapses with exhaustion. Then pulls himself

    together and decides:

Title:    I will run over quickly . . . 

    I shall get Sievers.

    And he is gone.

Medium close-up:   Anny, having almost fainted with fear, comes to

    again. She opens her eyes. She lifts her head. No-

    body around?? Is she all alone?? Isn't there some-

    thing moving about in the corner? Something

    fluttering at the window?

Medium close-up:   The window, covered by the curtain. Behind it

    the shadow of a giant bat.

    It grows and grows. Soon it isn't a bat any long-

    er. A vampire! NOSTERATU?!

Medium close-up:   Anny's body hits the wall. She jumps up and pulls

    the bell. Then half crazed with fear, she runs

    into the background.

</scene>
<scene num="137">
Anny's bedroom.

Long shot:   Night. Servants running to and fro in the direc-

    tion of the bedroom.

   

 
    

   

137a   The bell is ringing.

137b   Servant's room. A servant asleep doesn't hear, turns

   over in his sleep
</scene>
<scene num="138">   
3 meters
Anny's 
Bedroom
  Anny pressed close to the wall. Servants are rushing in.
   There!

   She shouts pointing to the window. Like a flock of 

   chicken the women are huddling together. Anny rushes

   over to them, but they are already so gripped by fear that

   they imagine her fingers, which they are trying to push back,  

   to be the vampire's claws. Shrieking, they run off in all

   directions. The door is slammed shut. Anny beats against 

   
the door
. She is waiting for the horror, but she doesn't
   want to see it, much r ather die first. She grabs a table cloth 

   and covers her head and neck. Then she collapses.

Fade-out.

</scene>
<scene num="139">  
3 meters
Fade-in.

Ellen's bedroom  Daytime. Ellen by the window . . .looking out. She stands

   motionless. Paralysed by misery she witnesses the daily

   scene of wretchedness.

</scene>
<scene num="140">  
8 meters
Street in front of

Hutter's's house  Ascending. In the distance, a strange procession is wandering

   across the street. One coffin after another carried by 

   survivors. Past Hutter's house, towards the procession, a 

   man is dragging himself along, tired to death. She supports

   himself by a stick. He catches sight of the distant procession

   and lifts up his hands to heaven in misery.

</scene>
<scene num="141">  
with window -frame    Ellen
Ellen's room.   Ellen, on the point of fainting, turns away from the window

   She cannot bear the sight of this wretchedness any longer.

   She sinks into a chair, resting her head in her hands.

Close-up:  The book, open. She has been reading it for days

Close up:  A page of the book:

   ONLY IF A CHASTE WOMAN

   CAN FEARLESSLY MAKE

   HIM

   MISS THE FIRST CROWING

   OF THE COCK WILL HE DISINTEGRATE

   IN THE LIGHT OF 

   DAWN

Close-up:  Ellen lifts up her head, staring into space like a visionary.

   She knows. She shuts her eyes. 

Fade out.

</scene>
<scene num="142">   
3 meters 
 
Fade-in.

In front of Harding's

mansion..
Medium close-up:   The porch. Harding - haggard - a broken man, 

    comes out. He closes the door and supports himself

    against the door-post. His hand reaches up, paints

    a black cross on the door . . .and falls down. His

    hollow eyes refrain from looking at his work . . .  

    again . . . they cannot bear to see the symbol. He 

    moves forward with a glazed look in his eyes.

Fade-out.   
Harding: black cape, dark trousers
</scene>
<scene num="143">   
7 meters
Fade-in.

In front of deserted house  Street

    A group of emaciated men with a fanatical look

    about them are standing around. An unkept-looking

    woman is haranguing them. They are raising

    their fists.

Title:    He has been seen!

    He ran out of the house!

    He strangled the attendant!

</scene>
<scene num="144">   
8 meters
Well in the market-place  Two ancient women are sitting by the well. Death 

    has no terrors for them. Since every new day is a 

    present to them. 

Close-up:   The are whispering to each other; their heads

    are trembling.

Title:    In the deserted house. . .

    that's where it is hiding.

    He strangled him. The vampire.

Medium close-up:  Further back agitated people are running

    across the square, shouting excitedly to 

    one another. The two woman turn around

    gesturing ˚ercely.

    The clench their bony fists threateningly. Harding

    can be seen behind the well. He has heard everything. 

Close up:   He utters a bitter and mocking laugh.

Long shot:   Harding walks on.

144a    
10 meters
Street shot from above:  
Crossing. Crowd gathering from all sides,
    then moving in one direction.

Close-up:   A street-corner with a man

    who points at something above. People

    rush up to him; they all turn to face the same

    way, look up, make threatening gestures

    Somebody throws stones.

    

</scene>
<scene num="145">

Gable of a house   A figure is crouching on a roof-top

</scene>
<scene num="146"> (?)
Medium close-up:  It is Knock. He is looking down with a 

    sneer on his face and pokes out his tongue

    A stone whizzes part him. He suddenly gets 

    up and clambers off.

</scene>
<scene num="147">   
8 meters
Ellen's bedroom   Ellen in an old armchair, busy embroidering a 

    cushion in the cross-stitch manner of the 1840s

    An inscription reading:

     I LOVE YOU

    She puts down her work, resting her head.

    Tired, she falls to day-dreaming. 
Then she lights
    a lamp. 

Medium close-up:   Ellen takes up her work again, determined

    to finish it.

</scene>
<scene num="148">   
Evening    4 meters
Back of deserted house.  The street is empty. Knock jumps down a wall 

    and runs off. In the distance some men appear, 

    chasing him. They catch sight of him and rush

    af ter him.

</scene>
<scene num="149">   
8 meters
Meadows outside the town  Shot against a wide expanse of sky. In the distance

    running figures, no more then silhouettes (Turn

    slowly) Knock in front. His pursuers following

    a long way behind.

</scene>
<scene num="150">   
3 meters
Fields.    Evening mists. Cornfields waving in the wind.

    Suddenly, right in front between the ears of

    corn head. Dishevelled hair. Then a bony back

    The heads turn around slowly.

    It is Knock.

</scene>
<scene num="151">   
3 meters
A lane between fields.  The landscape has grown dim in the evening light.

    The men chasing Knock are approaching. They stop. 

    They seem to have lost the tr ail.

    Suddenly, one of them sees something. He opens 

    his eyes wide, shouting: there!!!

    They all look one way. They dash off in that 

    direction.

</scene>
<scene num="152">   
10 meters
 
Cornfield, Long-shot:  In the distance one can still the back and dis-

    hevelled head. Is it Knock? He seems not to hear

    or see his pursuers. The men are coming near,

    rushing towards him across the field.

    They lift their sticks and fists.

</scene>
<scene num="152 continued">

Medium close-up   A scare-crow. A black coat is dangling on a stick.

    Bits of straw and tattered rags. The men fall on

    it in the disappointment. Suddenly they stop.

    There! What can that be !!!

Long-shot:   A hundred feet away a head has appeared. Then

    the f igure of a man. It is moving away quickly. 

    The chase starts up again.

Fade-out.

</scene>
<scene num="153">   
3 meters
Title:    Night

Deserted house. Medium Nosferatu at the window.

close-up:
Dissolve

</scene>
<scene num="154">   
8 meters    2x
Ellen's bedroom

Medium close-up:  Ellen wakes up. She sits up in bed, listening

    as if she had heard somebody calling her.

    She gets up, walking as if pulled by invisible

    threads.

Long shot:   She goes over to the window. In the fore-

    ground Hutter asleep in an armchair, look-

    ing worn out.

Medium close-up:  Ellen is clinging to the window. She sees.

</scene>
<scene num="155">.   3 meters

Deserted house.   Nosferatu at the window.

    He raises his arms slowly.

</scene><scene num="156">  

Ellen's room

Medium close-up:  Ellen is about to collapse by the window.

    Shaking with fear she struggles violently 

    with herself. The last battle.

    Twice her hands comes up to open the window

    and drops down again weakly; then, with

    sudden determination, she pulls herself up

    dead straight and deliberately throws the 

    window wide open.

</scene><scene num="157">    
4 meters
Deserted house.

Medium close-up:  
Window
    Nosferatu moves away from the window, turns 

    around and disappears.

</scene>
<scene num="158">   4 meters

Ellen's room. Close-up:  
Ellen trembling with fear and apprehension
</scene>
<scene num="159">

Deserted house

Medium close-up   Locked-up gates

    Suddenly the gates swing open:

    Nosferatu appears 

</scene>
<scene num="160">  12 meters    2x

Ellen's room.

Medium close-up: Ellen is covering her face with her hands, seized

   with mortal fear.

Long shot; window

moves out of picture Ellen at window. She wants to call for help.

   She staggers forward. She stops in front of Hutter.

   One last moment of indecision.

   Then she wakes him up. Hutter jumps to his feet.

   He catches the trembling figure in his arms.

   and carries her over to the sofa.

   She begs him, hands raised as if in prayer:

Title:   Bulwer . . . Fetch Bulwer!

   She entreats him to go. Hutter takes her hands, she

   quickly kisses his head,

   Then he rushes out.

</scene>
<scene num="161">  3 meters

In front of Hutter's

House.   A path bordered by flowers.

   Hutter rushes out.

   Trousers, pleated shirt, collar without tie. No hat

   no waist coat.

</scene>
<scene num="162">  5 meters

Ellen's room

Long shot.  Ellen is still looking in the direction she saw Hutter

   leave, then she gets up and walks toward the 

   window.

</scene>
<scene num="163"> 

Deserted house. 

Long Shot:  Nosferatu is walking forward and moves out of the

   picture. The house looks more deserted than ever!



In front of Hutter's

house   Nobody is about. Nosferatu is approaching. He comes

   to a halt. (He is preparing to jump, looks up)

   He enters the house.



Ellen's room  Ellen turns around suddenly. She is shaking with 

   fear, anticipating the horror about to happen.

   And it is coming -  - slowly, tensed like a predatory

   animal. She recoils, moves backwards step by step,

   and step by step it follows her

    Heart! - Hand

</scene>
<scene num="166">   6 meters

Bulwer's laboratory

(Living room)   In addition to the already familiar fish tanks there 

    is a large telescope by a window. A profusion of 

    antiquated scientific gadgets, globes etc. A lamp

    is burning. Bulwer asleep in dressing-gown and

    night-cap in the armchair. Cages with birds and

    all kinds of animals. Hutter rushes in. He wakes

    Bulwer, begs him to come with him. Bulwer starts 

    to get dressed.

</scene>
<scene num="167">

A municipal building on the
period (town hall)   A large crowd is gathering in front of the town

    hall. Knock has been captured. More people

    keep pouring in from all sides.

    
Omitted
</scene>
<scene num="168">   5 meters
 
An office room inside

the town hall   Sievers rushes in excitedly from the adjoining 

    room accompanied by a man who has brought

    him the news. From the other side Knock is being

    brought in. The lunatic is trembling with fear.

    exit

</scene>
<scene num="169">   4 meters

Ellen's room   Night. Ellen in bed, the strangler is at her throat, 

    his fingers clawing her arms. Her eyes, widened in 

    mortal fear, have a glazed look. Then she seems to 

    have heard something.

</scene>
<scene num="170">   A cock jumps on to a still-life farm implements.

    He flaps his wings, puffs up his throat and her-

    alds the morning.

</scene>
<scene num="171">   6 meters

Siever's lunatic's cell  Knock

Inside the town hall  Knock at the window, held by two men. Trying

    to ward them off, he shouts anxiously:

Title:    The master . . . the master . . .!

</scene>
<scene num="172">

Ellen's room.   Nosferatu raises his head. He looks drunk with

    pleasure. Ellen eyes are full of terrible fear. She

    must not allow Nosferatu just to go. She pulls

    her arms around him: he cannot resist and 

    bends his head over her again.

    
Omitted
</scene>
<scene num="173">   
3 meters
    The sun is rising over the small town.

</scene>
<scene num="174">

Ellen's room   Ellen's last moment of apprehension. There, 

    isn't that a flicker of sunlight on the wall over

    her bed? Here eyes light up hopefully and remain

    fixed on this first sign of the new day. She stretches

    out her hand for it. And look: it is moving

    downwards.

   

</scene>
<scene num="175">   5 meters

Street with front gardens  The long shadows of sunrise. Nobody is about

    Then shoulders of Hutter and Bulwer appear.

    They are hurrying on and turning into a side

    street.

</scene>
<scene num="176">   
8 meters
Ellen's room   The bed is bathed in sunlight. Ellen's eyes are 

    full of anticipation. Has she sacrificed herself in 

    vain? Suddenly the horrible figure jerks himself

    up. He looks about in amazement. He clutches

    his heart. The bestial tenseness of his bearing relaxes.

    For a moment he stands, legs apart, as if trying 

    to regain his balance. He clutches his heart again

    and falls on his knees, his face turned to the sun,

    distorted by pain.

</scene>
<scene num="177">
Siever's lunatic cell  Knock    5 meters

Town hall

Medium close-up:   Knock, in a straitjacket, alone in the sunlight 

    which is falling through a barred window. He

    is mumbling disconnected words:

Title:    The master . . .the master . . . is dead.

    His head sinks on to his chest.

</scene>
<scene num="178">   
8 meters
Ellen's room   Nosferatu on his knees, supporting himself with

    one hand on the ground. He raises the other in 

    the direction of the sun to shield himself from

    the light that brings him death. But he cannot

    hold out against the sun. His fingers, his hand, 

    his arm are dissolving in the light. The sun seems 

    about to strike his heart. Now his body is dis-

    integrating in the light. Ellen throws up her hands

    triumphantly calling:

Title:    Hutter!

</scene>
<scene num="179">   4 meters

In front of Hutter's House  Shot looking out from the doorway into the

    distance. Bulwer and Hutter are running, not

    just walking into the house.

</scene>
<scene num="180">   8 meters

    Ellen in bed. In anticipation, her hand reaches

    out for Hutter. Hutter comes rushing in, falls

    on his knees by the bed.  He t akes hold of her

    hand.

Close-up:   Her hand grasps his, the it lets go weakly and 

    drops away.

    Ellen's head falls over - - - - 

    Bulwer is standing at the window, hands behind 

    his back looking out.

     

      <title>THE END</title>

</scene>
</act>
</script>
</root>