<?xml-model href="../nosferatu_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
    <script>
        <head><title>...</title>.... <note>....</note>
        </head>
        <act num="4">
            <scene num="111">
                <cam>4 meters</cam>
                <loc>Roof Balcony of</loc>
                <loc>Harding's mansion</loc>
                <dir type="char">Ellen in Anny's arm. Her hair is fluttering in the wind. Ellen
                    stretching her hands towards the sea, as if trying to defend herself.</dir>
                <annot><title> I must go home. He is coming.</title></annot>
            </scene>

            <scene num="112">
                <loc>At the graveyard</loc>
                <loc>View over the sea</loc>
                <loc>In the foreground the crosses. In the back sandbank and cliffs.</loc>
                <dir type="char">In the distance people, hurrying to rescue the ship- wrecked.</dir>
                <dir type="stg">The sand bank . The ship crashes into it . . . turns over on its
                    side.</dir>
                <annot><cam>View through archway:</cam>
                <loc>the sailing boat is moving past. Weimar</loc></annot>
            </scene>

            <scene num="113">
                <annot><cam dis="4">4 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Lunatic's cell</loc>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Knock alone. He drags up a chair . . . to the window. He climbs up
                    on it.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Knock pulls himself up by the bars, trying to look out. The wind,
                    blowing in, makes his hair stand on end uncannily.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="113" sub="a">
                <annot><cam dis="10">10 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>The stranded ship Dead and forsaken. a rope is dangling from the deck. It is
                    swaying in the wind.</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
                <loc>An endless number of rats climbing down the swaying rope.</loc>
                <cam>Shot of deck.</cam>
                <dir type="stg">The hatch. It opens slowly.</dir>
                <dir type="char">NOSFERATU climbs out.</dir>
                <dir type="char">He carries the last coffin.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Remains standing. Motionless.</dir>
                <dir type="char">The image of death. Then he approaches slowly.</dir>
                <annot><loc>1) Ship anchored in the harbor.</loc>
                <cam>Dissolve</cam>
                <loc>2)Ship's hatch with a piece of deck.</loc>
                <dir type="stg"> Trick: 1) Canvas glides away from hatch. 2) Hatch lid is lifted. 3)
                    Rats are rushing on deck.</dir>
                <dir type="char">4) Nosferatu coffin in arms climbs out.</dir></annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="114">
                <annot><cam>8 meters</cam>
                <loc>Lauenburg or Travemünde</loc></annot>
                <loc>Town center. Trees, shaken by storm.</loc>
                <dir type="stg">A carriage races up, stops abruptly.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter jumps from the carriage. </dir>
                <dir type="stg">An axle is broken.</dir>
                <!-- not sure what this falls under -->
                <dir type="char"> The coachman seems at a loss.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Hutter cannot wait. He leaves the carriage and runs of f.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="115">
                <annot><cam dis="5">5 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Archway with a view of the harbor: </loc>
                <annot><dir type="char">Nosferatu enters the town</dir></annot>
            </scene>

            <scene num="116">
                <annot><cam dis="6">6 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>The roof of Harding's mansion.</loc>
                <loc> Ellen's room at the Hardings' </loc>
                <dir type="char">Ellen and Anny. Ellen suddenly breaks away. Overjoyed as if she had
                    a happy vision she throws her arms up and shouts:</dir>
                <annot><title> I must go to him. He is coming!! </title></annot>
                <dir type="char">She moves off and vanishes.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Anny wrings her hands in despair.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="117">
                <annot><cam dis="4">4 meters </cam></annot>
                <loc>Storm-tossed trees.</loc>
                <dir type="char">A white figure comes out of the house. It is Ellen. She is running
                    through the park. </dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="118">
                <annot><loc>perhaps Lüneberg Street</loc></annot>
                <loc>Shuttered windows.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Nosferatu striding</dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="118" sub="a">
                <dir type="char">Hutter, running along the street.</dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="119">
                <annot><cam>8 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Lunatic's cell</loc>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="stg">Knock, moving away from the window wall</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">The madman is listening for outside noises, as if he had received a
                    signal from the other world . . . triumphantly . . . he whispers to himself: </dir>
                <annot><title>The master is near . . .the master is near . . .!</title></annot>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Suddenly, he listens attentively. He creeps over to the door. There
                    he waits expectantly . . . The door opens. The attendant appears. He looks
                    around the room. Not noticing that Knock is behind him. Knock creeps carefully
                    behind his back. Suddenly frightened, the attendant turns around. Knock makes
                    for his throat like a vampire. The attendant falls over. The madman is at his
                    throat <annot>for a moment only, then he lets go and sneaks out.</annot></dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="120">
                <cam>5 meters</cam>
                <loc>In front of Hutter's house</loc>
                <dir type="char">Hutter comes running up. He looks up: no light. He is just about to
                    enter when - somebody is calling. He turns around Ellen!!!!! They fall into each
                    other's arms.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="121">
                <loc>Square with fountain</loc>
                <cam>5 meters</cam>
                <dir type="char">Nosferatu, cof˚n under his arm, is standing in the middle of the
                    square. Looking around to orientate himself. Then he strides on.</dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="122">
                <cam dis="4" sync="2">4 meters 2x</cam>
                <loc>Hutter's parlour Ellen's sitting room</loc>
                <dir type="stg">A lamp is shining. Hutter and Ellen. They are sitting on the chaise
                    lounge. The happiness of being reunited was too much. Overpowered by emotion, he
                    sinks down on her arm. </dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="123">
                <cam>4 meters</cam>
                <loc>In front of Hutter's house</loc>
                <dir type="char">Nosferatu, staring up</dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="124">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter and Ellen, on the chaise lounge. He sits up, looking deep
                    into her eyes.</dir>
                <title> Thank God . . . you are well . . .now everything has come all right.</title>
                <dir type="char">She does not understand him. But the joy of being to- gether again
                    is stronger than anything else. And the room is bright.</dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="125">
                <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
                <loc>Street in front of Hutter's House </loc>
                <dir type="char">There is nobody about. But in the middle of the street stands
                    NOSFERATU, hidden by the night, carrying the cof fin. Slowly, he turns his head
                    and looks over to Hutter's house.</dir>
                <cam>Shot of Hutter's house </cam>
                <dir type="stg">[There is a friendly light in the window] </dir>
                <dir type="char">The deserted house Empty! Carrying the coffin - Nosferatu appears
                    in picture. </dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">NOSFERATU. Once more he turns his head. He looks over to the other
                    side. The deserted house is over there. He makes for that now, walking slow.
                    Then he goes into the house. </dir>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="126">
                <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>
                <loc>On the stranded ship</loc>
                <dir type="char">The captain, collapsed in death, is tied to the helm. In the
                    foreground, some men, Harding among them, are climbing up on deck. They are
                    aghast at the terrible sight.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">The dead captain. Tied to the helm in discharge of his duty! One
                    hand is still on the helm. The other, holding a crucifix, clutches his chest in
                    mortal agony. His head sunk back, face distorted. There are two red marks on his
                    neck . . . </dir>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Harding. He cannot comprehend the horror . . .</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="127">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <loc>Sandbank harbor The stranded ship is in sight.</loc>
                <time>It is night-time</time>
                <cam>Long shot: </cam>
                <dir type="stg">In the blowing wind nocturnal figures . . .townspeople</dir>
                <cam>Close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Down the tilted hulk a man is climbing along a rope. </dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">By the light of a torch! the captain of the harbor with a number of
                    old people . . . Looking like fishermen. The climber approaches and reports. </dir>
                <title> Everything has been examined . . No living soul on board. The captain
                    receives the report . . . jots down some notes.</title>
            </scene>

            <scene num="128">
                <cam dis="10">10 meters [Is inserted below]</cam>
                <loc>On board ship.</loc>
                <time>Night</time>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <loc>Back-board with helm.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Some men are lifting up the dead captain, and carrying off the
                    corpse. </dir>
                <loc>Captain's cabin: </loc>
                <dir type="char">Harding alone . . . he finds a book next to a masthead that is
                    affixed to the helm. In the light of a dim lantern he reads: </dir>
                <cam>Close-up: A page of the book</cam>
                <p>Varna - July 12 Crew - apart from myself the captain - one helmsman mate and five
                    sailors. Departing - for the Dardanelles. </p>
                <cam>Normal Shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Harding shakes his head. He is puzzled.</dir>
                <loc>On deck.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Harding emerges from the cabin with the book in his hand.</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="129">
                <cam dis="15">15 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in: </cam>
                <time>Daytime</time>
                <loc>Port Authority building A large hall. On the walls a number of figure heads
                    Models of ships are suspended from the ceiling.</loc>
                <dir type="char">The dead captain [is carried] in lying in state.</dir>
                <cam>Medium Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Dr. Sievers is examining him. He notices the marks on his neck. Dr.
                    Sievers turns to Harding.</dir>
                <dir type="char"> He, too, cannot make sense of this case. Nevertheless he talks
                    incessantly. Harding comes closer shows him the log-book. Both of them are
                    reading: </dir>
                <cam>Close-up: The log-book.</cam>
                <!-- not sure what this would me notated as. Kind of a stage direction but also a camera direction -->
                <dir type="stg"> A page: Second day: July 13 A sailor has fallen ill with a fever.
                    Course: SSW. Direction of wind: Third day: July 14 Mate is talking strangely. He
                    says there is an unknown passenger below deck. Course SE. Direction of wind NE.
                    Volume of wind 3.6. </dir>
                <cam>Normal shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Sievers and Harding are looking at each other. Sievers' white beard
                    is trembling. They continue reading. Tenth day: July 22 Rats in the ship's hold.
                    Danger of plague.</dir>
                <cam>Normal shot: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Harding has been reading this aloud. Now Sievers understands at
                    last. He points to the book with his finger. Danger of plague! That's what it
                    is. Dan- ger of plague, he calls out. </dir>
                <title> Danger of plague! Go home! Shut all your windows and doors! Deeply
                    frightened, the bystanders move away. The women put the ends of their
                    head-scarves into their mouths. Panic- stricken .the crowd leaves the room. </title>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
                <annot>(Perhaps end of act)</annot>
                <!-- verify this -->
            </scene>

            <scene num="130">
                <cam dis="15">15 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in</cam>
                <loc>A deserted square: Nobody is about. Except in the center of the square, the
                    town-drummer with his large drum. </loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">The drummer. He beats a mighty roll.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <loc>A closed window.</loc>
                <dir type="char">The hatch opens and a woman's head appears: totally emaciated,
                    sunken cheeks, long dishevelled hair. The disease has gripped her too. On her
                    neck the ominous little marks. </dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">The drummer has produced a piece of paper and reads it aloud:</dir>
                <p>magistrate of this town prohibits any movement of plague-suspects into hospitals
                    to prevent the plague from spreading through the streets. </p>
                <dir type="char">The drummer has finished reading and goes off.</dir>
            </scene>

            <title>End of Act IV</title>
        </act>

        <act num="5">
            <title>Act V</title>
            <scene num="131">
                <cam dis="15">15 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade in.</cam>
                <loc>A bend in a street</loc>
                <dir type="char">A man emerges from a front door. He shuts the door behind him.
                    Quickly and with circumspection he chalks a white cross on the door. Then goes
                    on.</dir>
                <cam>Panning shot:</cam>
                <loc>The adjoining house.</loc>
                <dir type="char">The man knocks hard on the door. From a window above a head looks
                    out. There are still people living here. The man moves on. </dir>
                <cam>Panning shot: </cam>
                <loc>The first house in the side-street.</loc>
                <dir type="char">A coffin is being carried out. Men carrying it have white bandages
                    over their mouths. The man comes along and dr aws a cross on this house, too.
                    Then he walks on, following his horrible business.</dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="132">
                <cam dis="15" sync="2">15 meters 2x</cam>
                <loc>shaded candle on table near armchair .</loc>
                <loc>Ellen's bedroom</loc>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="stg">Book-cover Inscription (Vampire) See Chapter 1 of book. </dir>
                <cam>Dissolve to: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen by the window, the book on her knees continues reading,
                    overcoming her aversion. </dir>
                <dir type="stg">Chapter II appears.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen is pondering on what she has read. </dir>
                <dir type="char">Hutter comes into the picture, with agitation almost hostility he
                    grabs the book.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Ellen, standing now, looks straight into his eyes, turns and points
                    over to the deserted house.</dir>
                <!-- need to verify what this is supposed to be  -->
                <annot>Compare the following black dress and shawl</annot>
                <cost>Hutter, black waist-coat and jacket.</cost>
                <loc>Ellen's room.</loc>
                <cam>Long shot: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen by the window. Hutter approaches from the door</dir>
                <cam>Medium close</cam>
                <dir type="char">Suddenly, she grabs his arm, stares out of the window pointing out,
                    she shouts: There!!!</dir>
                <dir type="char">Her body is tensed up like a bow trembling with excitement.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="133">
                <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
                <loc>The deserted house Seen through Ellen's window frame.</loc>
                <cam> Almost at once dissolve to window.</cam>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <loc>A window, divided into four rectangular panes. Light from behind.</loc>
                <dir type="stg">Stuck to the window, almost completely covering it, something
                    looking like a black fourlegged spider. It takes a moment before one can make
                    out Nos- feratu's fingers which are clawing the window frame. In the center of
                    the body, grinning lasciviously, the waxen face with ratlike teeth. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="134">
                <cam dis="8" sync="2">8 meters 2x</cam>
                <loc>Ellen's bedroom.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Ellen holds frantically on to Hutter's hand [shaken] breathing
                    heavily She bends her head back. towards him saying. </dir>
                <title> This is how I see it- every evening. . .!!! </title>
                <dir type="char">She bends her head back. She knows all she has to know. And there
                    is peace in the knowledge.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Hutter has not come to that yet. He finds her calm- ness
                    disturbing. He follows the retreating figure with his eyes.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen is swaying.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Hutter, despairingly, presses his fist against his face. </dir>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="135">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <loc>In front of Hutter's house</loc>
                <time>It is now evening.</time>
                <dir type="char">The lamp-lighter comes down the darkening street and lights up the
                    street-lamps. The he walks on.</dir>
                <!-- need to verify if this is actually annotation -->
                <annot>! remains!</annot>
            </scene>

            <scene num="136">
                <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in:</cam>
                <loc>Anny's bedroom</loc>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Anny crouching on a chaise lounge.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Bent over her Harding who is holding her hands and trying to calm
                    down the struggling woman who is shaking fitfully.</dir>
                <dir type="char"> She collapses with exhaustion. Then pulls himself together and
                    decides: </dir>
                <title> I will run over quickly . . . I shall get Sievers. And he is gone.</title>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Anny, having almost fainted with fear, comes to again. She opens
                    her eyes. She lifts her head. No- body around?? Is she all alone?? Isn't there
                    some- thing moving about in the corner? Something fluttering at the window? </dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="stg">The window, covered by the curtain. Behind it the shadow of a giant
                    bat. It grows and grows. Soon it isn't a bat any long- er. A vampire!
                    NOSTERATU?! </dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Anny's body hits the wall. She jumps up and pulls the bell. Then
                    half crazed with fear, she runs into the background.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="137">
                <loc>Anny's bedroom.</loc>
                <cam>Long shot: </cam>
                <time>Night.</time>
                <dir type="char">Servants running to and fro in the direc- tion of the bedroom.
                </dir>
            </scene>






            <scene num="137" sub="a">
                <dir type="stg">The bell is ringing.</dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="137" sub="b">
                <loc>Servant's room. </loc>
                <dir type="char">A servant asleep doesn't hear, turns over in his sleep</dir>
            </scene>


            <scene num="138">
                <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
                <loc>Anny's Bedroom</loc>
                <dir type="char">Anny pressed close to the wall.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Servants are rushing in.</dir>
                <dir type="char">There! She shouts pointing to the window.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Like a flock of chicken the women are huddling together.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Anny rushes over to them, but they are already so gripped by fear
                    that they imagine her fingers, which they are trying to push back, to be the
                    vampire's claws. Shrieking, they run off in all directions. The door is slammed
                    shut. Anny beats against the door. She is waiting for the horror, but she
                    doesn't want to see it, much rather die first. She grabs a table cloth and
                    covers her head and neck. Then she collapses.</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="139">
                <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in. </cam>
                <loc>Ellen's bedroom</loc>
                <time>Daytime.</time>
                <dir type="char">Ellen by the window . . .looking out. She stands motionless.
                    Paralysed by misery she witnesses the daily scene of wretchedness.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="140">
                <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
                <loc>Street in front of Hutter's's house</loc>
                <dir type="char">Ascending. In the distance, a strange procession is wandering
                    across the street. One coffin after another carried by survivors. Past Hutter's
                    house, towards the procession, a man is dragging himself along, tired to death.
                    She supports himself by a stick. He catches sight of the distant procession and
                    lifts up his hands to heaven in misery. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="141">
                <dir type="char">with window -frame Ellen</dir>
                <!-- need to fix this. Something is missing -->
                <loc>Ellen's room.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Ellen, on the point of fainting, turns away from the window She
                    cannot bear the sight of this wretchedness any longer. She sinks into a chair,
                    resting her head in her hands. </dir>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">The book, open. She has been reading it for days </dir>
                <cam>Close up: A page of the book:</cam>
                <p> ONLY IF A CHASTE WOMAN CAN FEARLESSLY MAKE HIM MISS THE FIRST CROWING OF THE
                    COCK WILL HE DISINTEGRATE IN THE LIGHT OF DAWN</p>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen lifts up her head, staring into space like a visionary. She
                    knows. She shuts her eyes.</dir>
                <cam>Fade out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="142">
                <cam>3 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
                <loc>In front of Harding's mansion..</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <loc>The porch.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Harding - haggard - a broken man, comes out. He closes the door and
                    supports himself against the door-post. His hand reaches up, paints a black
                    cross on the door . . .and falls down. His hollow eyes refrain from looking at
                    his work . . . again . . . they cannot bear to see the symbol. He moves forward
                    with a glazed look in his eyes. </dir>
                <cam>Fade-out. </cam>
                <cost>Harding: black cape, dark trousers</cost>
            </scene>
            <scene num="143">
                <cam dis="7">7 meters</cam>
                <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
                <loc>In front of deserted house Street</loc>
                <dir type="char"> A group of emaciated men with a fanatical look about them are
                    standing around. An unkept-looking woman is haranguing them. They are raising
                    their fists.</dir>
                <title> He has been seen! He ran out of the house! He strangled the
                    attendant!</title>
            </scene>
            <scene num="144">
                <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
                <loc>Well in the market-place</loc>
                <dir type="char">Two ancient women are sitting by the well. Death has no terrors for
                    them. Since every new day is a present to them. </dir>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">The are whispering to each other; their heads are trembling.</dir>
                <title> In the deserted house. . . that's where it is hiding. He strangled him. The
                    vampire. </title>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Further back agitated people are running across the square,
                    shouting excitedly to one another. The two woman turn around gesturing ˚ercely.
                    The clench their bony fists threateningly. Harding can be seen behind the well.
                    He has heard everything. </dir>
                <cam>Close up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">He utters a bitter and mocking laugh.</dir>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Harding walks on.</dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="144" sub="a">
                <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
                <cam>Street shot from above: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Crossing. Crowd gathering from all sides, then moving in one
                    direction.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">A street-corner with a man who points at something above. People
                    rush up to him; they all turn to face the same way, look up, make threatening
                    gestures Somebody throws stones. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="145">
                <loc>Gable of a house</loc>
                <dir type="char">A figure is crouching on a roof-top</dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="146">
                <!-- (?)  what does this mean      -->
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">It is Knock. He is looking down with a sneer on his face and pokes
                    out his tongue A stone whizzes part him. He suddenly gets up and clambers
                    off.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="147">
                <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
                <loc>Ellen's bedroom</loc>
                <dir type="char">Ellen in an old armchair, busy embroidering a cushion in the
                    cross-stitch manner of the 1840s An inscription reading: I LOVE YOU She puts
                    down her work, resting her head. Tired, she falls to day-dreaming. Then she
                    lights a lamp. </dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen takes up her work again, determined to finish it.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="148">
                <time>Evening</time>
                <cam dis="4">4 meters</cam>
                <loc>Back of deserted house.</loc>
                <dir type="stg">The street is empty.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Knock jumps down a wall and runs off. In the distance some men
                    appear, chasing him. They catch sight of him and rush af ter him.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="149">
                <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
                <loc>Meadows outside the town</loc>
                <cam>Shot against a wide expanse of sky.</cam>
                <dir type="char">In the distance running figures, no more then silhouettes (Turn
                    slowly) Knock in front. His pursuers following a long way behind.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="150">
                <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
                <loc>Fields. Evening mists. Cornfields waving in the wind.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Suddenly, right in front between the ears of corn head. Dishevelled
                    hair. Then a bony back The heads turn around slowly. It is Knock.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="151">
                <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
                <loc>A lane between fields.</loc>
                <time>The landscape has grown dim in the evening light. </time>
                <!-- not sure how to split the time line up-->
                <dir type="char">The men chasing Knock are approaching. They stop. They seem to have
                    lost the tr ail. Suddenly, one of them sees something. He opens his eyes wide,
                    shouting: there!!! They all look one way. They dash off in that direction.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="152">
                <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
                <loc>Cornfield,</loc>
                <cam>Long-shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">In the distance one can still the back and dis- hevelled head. Is
                    it Knock? He seems not to hear or see his pursuers. The men are coming near,
                    rushing towards him across the field. They lift their sticks and fists.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
                <loc>A scare-crow. A black coat is dangling on a stick. Bits of straw and tattered
                    rags.</loc>
                <dir type="char">The men fall on it in the disappointment. Suddenly they stop.
                    There! What can that be !!!</dir>
                <cam>Long-shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">A hundred feet away a head has appeared. Then the f igure of a man.
                    It is moving away quickly. The chase starts up again.</dir>
                <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="153">
                <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
                <title> Night</title>
                <loc>Deserted house.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Medium Nosferatu at the window.</dir>
                <cam>close-up:</cam>
                <cam>Dissolve</cam>
            </scene>
            <scene num="154">
                <cam dis="8" sync="2">8 meters 2x</cam>
                <loc>Ellen's bedroom</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen wakes up. She sits up in bed, listening as if she had heard
                    somebody calling her. She gets up, walking as if pulled by invisible
                    threads.</dir>
                <cam>Long shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">She goes over to the window. In the fore- ground Hutter asleep in
                    an armchair, look- ing worn out.</dir>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen is clinging to the window. She sees. </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="155">
                <cam dis="3"> 3 meters</cam>
                <loc>Deserted house.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Nosferatu at the window. He raises his arms slowly.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="156">
                <loc>Ellen's room</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen is about to collapse by the window. Shaking with fear she
                    struggles violently with herself. The last battle. Twice her hands comes up to
                    open the window and drops down again weakly; then, with sudden determination,
                    she pulls herself up dead straight and deliberately throws the window wide open.
                </dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="157">
                <cam dis="4">4 meters</cam>
                <loc>Deserted house.</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up: Window</cam>
                <!-- kind of jumped between including the details of the shot in the cam element or loc element -->
                <dir type="char">Nosferatu moves away from the window, turns around and
                    disappears.</dir>
            </scene>

            <scene num="158">
                <cam dis="4">4 meters</cam>
                <loc>Ellen's room.</loc>
                <cam>Close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen trembling with fear and apprehension</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="159">
                <loc>Deserted house</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
                <loc>Locked-up gates</loc>
                <dir type="stg">Suddenly the gates swing open:</dir>
                <dir type="char">Nosferatu appears </dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="160">
                <cam dis="12" sync="2">12 meters 2x</cam>
                <loc>Ellen's room.</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen is covering her face with her hands, seized with mortal fear. </dir>
                <cam>Long shot; window moves out of picture</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen at window. She wants to call for help. She staggers forward.
                    She stops in front of Hutter. One last moment of indecision. Then she wakes him
                    up. Hutter jumps to his feet. He catches the trembling figure in his arms. and
                    carries her over to the sofa. She begs him, hands raised as if in prayer:</dir>
                <time> Bulwer . . . Fetch Bulwer!</time>
                <dir type="char">She entreats him to go. Hutter takes her hands, she quickly kisses
                    his head, Then he rushes out.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="161">
                <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
                <loc>In front of Hutter's House. A path bordered by flowers. </loc>
                <dir type="char">Hutter rushes out.</dir>
                <cost>Trousers, pleated shirt, collar without tie. No hat no waist coat.</cost>
            </scene>
            <scene num="162">
                <cam dis="5">5 meters</cam>
                <loc>Ellen's room</loc>
                <cam>Long shot.</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen is still looking in the direction she saw Hutter leave, then
                    she gets up and walks toward the window.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="163">
                <loc>Deserted house.</loc>
                <cam>Long Shot:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Nosferatu is walking forward and moves out of the picture.</dir>
                <dir type="stg">The house looks more deserted than ever!</dir>
                <loc>In front of Hutter's house</loc>
                <dir type="stg">Nobody is about.</dir>
                <dir type="char">Nosferatu is approaching. He comes to a halt. (He is preparing to
                    jump, looks up) He enters the house.</dir>
                <loc>Ellen's room</loc>
                <dir type="char">Ellen turns around suddenly. She is shaking with fear, anticipating
                    the horror about to happen. And it is coming - - slowly, tensed like a predatory
                    animal. She recoils, moves backwards step by step, and step by step it follows
                    her Heart! - Hand</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="166">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <loc>Bulwer's laboratory</loc>
                <loc>(Living room)</loc>
                <loc>In addition to the already familiar fish tanks there is a large telescope by a
                    window. A profusion of antiquated scientific gadgets, globes etc. A lamp is
                    burning.</loc>
                <!-- need to figure out how to break this up -->
                <dir type="char">Bulwer asleep in dressing-gown and night-cap in the armchair. Cages
                    with birds and all kinds of animals. Hutter rushes in. He wakes Bulwer, begs him
                    to come with him. Bulwer starts to get dressed.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="167">
                <loc>A municipal building on the period (town hall)</loc>
                <dir type="char">A large crowd is gathering in front of the town hall. Knock has
                    been captured. More people keep pouring in from all sides.</dir>
                <annot>Omitted</annot>
                <!-- verify if this is actually an annotation -->
            </scene>
            <scene num="168">
                <cam dis="5">5 meters</cam>
                <loc>An office room inside the town hall</loc>
                <dir type="char">Sievers rushes in excitedly from the adjoining room accompanied by
                    a man who has brought him the news. From the other side Knock is being brought
                    in. The lunatic is trembling with fear. exit</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="169">
                <cam dis="4">4 meters</cam>
                <loc>Ellen's room</loc>
                <time>Night.</time>
                <dir type="char">Ellen in bed, the strangler is at her throat, his fingers clawing
                    her arms. Her eyes, widened in mortal fear, have a glazed look. Then she seems
                    to have heard something.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="170">
                <dir type="stg">A cock jumps on to a still-life farm implements. He flaps his wings,
                    puffs up his throat and her- alds the morning.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="171">
                <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
                <loc>Siever's lunatic's cell</loc>
                <dir type="char">Knock Inside the town hall Knock at the window, held by two men.
                    Trying to ward them off, he shouts anxiously:</dir>
                <title> The master . . . the master . . .!</title>
            </scene>
            <scene num="172">
                <loc>Ellen's room.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Nosferatu raises his head. He looks drunk with pleasure. Ellen eyes
                    are full of terrible fear. She must not allow Nosferatu just to go. She pulls
                    her arms around him: he cannot resist and bends his head over her again.</dir>
                <annot>Omitted</annot>
            </scene>
            <scene num="173">
                <cam>3 meters</cam>
                <loc>The sun is rising over the small town.</loc>
            </scene>
            <scene num="174">
                <loc>Ellen's room</loc>
                <dir type="char">Ellen's last moment of apprehension.
                    <!-- Not sure if this is a title or dir. Need to check video --></dir>
                <loc>There, isn't that a flicker of sunlight on the wall over her bed?</loc>
                <dir type="char">Here eyes light up hopefully and remain fixed on this first sign of
                    the new day. She stretches out her hand for it. And look: it is moving
                    downwards.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="175">
                <cam dis="5">5 meters</cam>
                <loc>Street with front gardens</loc>
                <loc>The long shadows of sunrise.</loc>
                <loc>Nobody is about</loc>
                <dir type="char"> Then shoulders of Hutter and Bulwer appear. They are hurrying on
                    and turning into a side street.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="176">
                <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
                <loc>Ellen's room</loc>
                <loc>The bed is bathed in sunlight.</loc>
                <dir type="char">Ellen's eyes are full of anticipation</dir>
                <dir type="char">. Has she sacrificed herself in vain? Suddenly the horrible figure
                    jerks himself up. He looks about in amazement. He clutches his heart. The
                    bestial tenseness of his bearing relaxes. For a moment he stands, legs apart, as
                    if trying to regain his balance. He clutches his heart again and falls on his
                    knees, his face turned to the sun, distorted by pain.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="177">
                <annot>Siever's lunatic cell <cam dis="5">Knock 5 meters</cam></annot>
                <loc>Town hall</loc>
                <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char">Knock, in a <cost>straitjacket</cost>, alone in the sunlight which
                    is falling through a barred window. He is mumbling disconnected words:</dir>
                <title> The master . . .the master . . . is dead.</title>
                <dir type="char">His head sinks on to his chest.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="178">
                <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
                <loc>Ellen's room</loc>
                <dir type="char">Nosferatu on his knees, supporting himself with one hand on the
                    ground. He raises the other in the direction of the sun to shield himself from
                    the light that brings him death. But he cannot hold out against the sun. His
                    fingers, his hand, his arm are dissolving in the light. The sun seems about to
                    strike his heart. Now his body is dis- integrating in the light. Ellen throws up
                    her hands triumphantly calling:</dir>
                <title> Hutter!</title>
            </scene>
            <scene num="179">
                <cam>4 meters</cam>
                <loc>In front of Hutter's House</loc>
                <cam>Shot looking out from the doorway into the distance.</cam>
                <dir type="char">Bulwer and Hutter are running, not just walking into the
                    house.</dir>
            </scene>
            <scene num="180">
                <cam>8 meters</cam>
                <dir type="char">Ellen in bed.</dir>
                <dir type="char"> In anticipation, her hand reaches out for Hutter. Hutter comes
                    rushing in, falls on his knees by the bed. He t akes hold of her hand.</dir>
                <cam>Close-up:</cam>
                <dir type="char"> Her hand grasps his, the it lets go weakly and drops away. Ellen's
                    head falls over - - - - Bulwer is standing at the window, hands behind his back
                    looking out.</dir>
            </scene>
            <title>THE END</title>
        </act>
    </script>
</root>
