<?xml-model href="../nosferatu_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
   <script>
      <head><title>...</title>.... <note>....</note>
      </head>
      <act num="1">
         <scene num="48">
            <cam dis="4"> 4 meters</cam>
            <loc>Dining hall</loc>
            <cam>View from door deep into the dining hall</cam>
            <dir type="char">By the fireplace Count Orlok, no, not Orlock but a gigantic vampire, a
               motionless, sombre watcher in the night. <cost>Medium close-up</cost> He looks at
               Hutter with a fixed glaze. </dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="49">
            <cam dis="6"> 6 meters</cam>
            <loc>The small room.</loc>
            <cam>Shot of door:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter. He supports himself against the doorpost. A ter- rible
               realization has dawned on him. Shut the door, shut it quickly! There is no bolt. No
               lock. He looks around, puts the heavy oak-chair against the door. Is it possible to
               escape?</dir>
            <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
            <loc>Window.</loc>
            <dir type="char">Hutter rushes up and flings it open.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="50">
            <cam dis="3"> 3 meters</cam>
            <loc> Tegeler Forest</loc>
            <loc>Night. Undergrowth.</loc>
            <dir type="stg">A pack of wolves, raising their heads howling.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="51">
            <cam dis="8"> 8 meters</cam>
            <loc>The small room</loc>
            <cam>Long shot:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter falls on his knees by the side of the bid. Hutter clutching the
               bedclothes, he stares at the door behind which the horror is waiting. What is this? </dir>
            <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
            <dir type="stg">Moved by an invisible hand the door opens to half its width in one
               single jerk. </dir>
            <cam>Long shot:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter. Terrified, he covers his eyes with his arms, pulls at the
               bedclothes and shields his eyes. He mustn't see it. He mustn't look!</dir>
            <cam>Fade out.</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="52">
            <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>  <title>The same night</title>
            <loc>Ellen's bedroom at the Hardings</loc>
            <dir type="char">She wakes up suddenly. She has been dreaming. As if she had seen a
               vision ... She has a premonition of danger ... Now she gets up. Moves over to the
               window and steps out on to the balcony. </dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="53">
            <cam dis="6
   ">6 meters</cam>
            <loc>Harding's study Night.</loc>
            <dir type="char">Harding is sitting at his desk. He hears a noise Rushes out.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="54">
            <loc>Ellen's bedroom</loc>
            <cam>Medium close-up of door</cam>
            <dir type="char">Ellen is perching on the edge of the balcony. Harding leading to the
               balcony rushes into the room. Discovers that the bed is empty. He shouts: Ellen!
            </dir>  <title> Ellen!</title>
            <dir type="char">He catches sight of the sleepwalker at the moment when, woken up by his
               shouts, she loses her balance and falls over. He runs up to her and gathers her in
               his arms. He carries her over to the bed. A servant, alerted by the noise appears in
               the door. A doctor! shouts Harding. The ser- vant disappears.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="55">
            <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
            <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
            <loc>The small castle room</loc>
            <cam>Long Shot</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter in bed, tense and doubled up. Slowly, Nosferatu creeps up on
               him. Irresistible, he bends over the terrified and help- less man and buries his
               fangs in his throat.</dir>
            <cam>Fade-out. </cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="56">
            <cam dis="7">7 meters</cam>
            <cam>Fade in.</cam>
            <loc>Ellen's bedroom</loc>
            <cam>Long shot:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Ellen shouts:</dir>  <title> Hutter!!!</title>
            <cam>Long shot</cam>: <loc> Ellen in bed</loc><dir type="char"> ...in delirium. Anny is
               kneeling by her side. A doctor. Professor Sievers, is taking her pulse.</dir> Harding <!-- I assume this is a character in which case im not quite sure what to wrap it in.  -->
            <dir type="char">Ellen trembles like a wounded bird. She doubles up throws herself about
               and retreats into a corner of the bed.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="57">
            <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
            <loc>The small castle room Night</loc>
            <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">NOSTERATU turns his head. He is listening intently as if he could feel
               - hear the terrified shouting in the distance.</dir>
            <cam>Long shot</cam>
            <dir type="char">NOSTERATU moves away from Hutter's bed. He dissolves into the air!
               leaves the room</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="58">
            <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
            <loc>Ellen's bedroom</loc>
            <dir type="char"> Ellen is calming down slowly. Her terror turns into apathy. Breathing
               weakly. </dir>
            <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
            <dir type="char">She settles back listlessly into her pillows. Sievers can tell the
               improvement from the pulse-rate and says to Harding:</dir>  <title> Normal
               congestion of the blood. . . caused by an awkward position during sleep...</title>
            <dir type="char">He has assumed an academic air. His beard trembles in his eagerness. </dir>
            <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="59">
            <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
            <loc>Poczamok</loc>
            <dir type="stg"> Behind a pointed gable of the castle the sun is rising slowly.</dir>
            <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="60">
            <cam dis="7">7 meters</cam>
            <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
            <loc>The small castle room</loc>
            <dir type="stg">The light of dawn is falling through the window as though a sky-light
               and moving along the wall until it reaches Hutter's face, looking half-faint -ing,
               half asleep. Suddenly he wakes up </dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="60"> continued <!-- The script has "continued after the scene number 60 so im not entirely sure what we should do about it besides just changing the schema for this one little thing -->
            <dir type="char">He starts up and clutches his throat. He jumps out of bed, clenching
               his fists, runs over. To the door. Carefully ...he looks out</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="61">
            <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
            <loc>Dining hall Daytime.</loc>
            <dir type="char"> The room is empty ...Hutter, pale and hollow-eyed, staggers in. He
               looks around ...nothing. Shaking his head, fists clenched with wild determination, he
               drags himself forward. </dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="62">
            <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
            <loc>Portrait gallery with flight of stairs</loc>
            <dir type="char">Hutter is dragging himself along with difficulty. He goes down a few
               stairs. At the end of the corridor he finds a door. He opens it.</dir></scene>
            <scene sub="62a."> <loc>A curving
               gallery exterior</loc> <dir type="char">Hutter opens one door after the other</dir>
                </scene>
         <scene num="63">
            <cam dis="15">15 meters</cam>
            <loc>A vault Empty and dark.</loc>
            <dir type="char"> In the center of the darkness a black coffin. Hutter has pushed the
               door open and enters. He starts back. He stares without understanding. Fear grips
               him. But he must make certain. Trembling heavily, he lifts up the coffin lid. He
               recoils in horror. Dropping the lid, he retreats into the darkest corner. For inside
               the coffin he has seen, black and long, the lifeless body of NOSFERATU.
               Horror-stricken, Hutter almost collapses. Then he rushes out. </dir>
            <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="64">
            <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
            <loc> Poczamok Vratna Pass Tatra</loc>
            <cam>Fade in.</cam>
            <dir type="stg">Sunset. Between a line of bizarre tree-trunks evening approaches like a
               ghost...</dir>
            <!--Labled this as a direction but I think it could also be a sort of location?-->
         </scene>
         <scene num="65">
            <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
            <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
            <loc>A niche inside the castle The small castle room.</loc> <dir type="char">Hutter is
               crouched on the floor. His body is twisted with fear. His hair is standing on end
               ...his eyes are staring. Sud- denly, he starts up and listens. Can he hear a noise in
               this desolate place? Could it mean his salvation? With difficulty he drags his
               weakened body over to the window.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="66">
            <cam>Window frame for out-door shot</cam>
            <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
            <loc> Poczamok The walls of the castle</loc>
            <dir type="char">seen from outside Hutter stares from a window. He refuses to believe
               what he sees. </dir>
            <cam>The crossbar of a window</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="67">
            <cam dis="6"> [
               <!-- "[12] meters 6 meters" is kinda confusing at the moment so I only used the 6 meters. Will change at later date  -->
               12] meters 6 meters</cam><loc> Poczamok</loc>
            <dir type="char">One can see a low-wheeled cart with the two fantastic horses harnessed
               to it. And now: is it a shadow? A ghost. Nos- feratu. He is moving to and fro, to and
               fro. From the cart to the castle. And back again. Carrying boxes. Black coffin like
               boxes. From the back door of the castle to the carriage He piles them up. Box on box.
               Into a gigantic pyramid. All this happens at an uncanny speed. </dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="68">
            <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
            <loc>Poczamok</loc>
            <dir type="char">Part of the castle wall Hutter, staring at the phantom with glazed
               eyes.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="69">
            <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
            <loc>Poczamok Castle yard</loc>
            <dir type="stg">The carriage is now loaded. Suddenly the phan- tom jumps on to the
               topmost box and dis- appears inside it. Instantly the horses dash off with the cart
               at lightning speed. The big gate closes behind them with a bang.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="70">
            <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
            <dir type="char">The small castle room Hutter jumps back from the window. </dir> 
               <title>Ellen!</title>
            <dir type="char">NOSFERATU is on his way. Ellen is in danger. He has to hurry. Save
               Ellen. Ellen! Ellen!. Suddenly, he starts tearing down the wall-hangings and tearing
               up the bedclothes . He tears them making long pieces and knotting them into a rope. </dir>
            <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="71">
            <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
            <loc>Poczamok The abyss</loc>
            <dir type="char">Hutter dangling from a window in the castle walls on a rope. But the
               rope is too short. Beneath him, the abyss still opens up. And yet he risks the drop -
               dead or alive.</dir>
            <cam>Medium close-up.</cam>
            <dir type="char"> So he hurls himself down. Hutter is lying at the bottom of the abyss,
               between trees and boulders. Tossing and turning in fever and pain. So he tries to
               lift himself up. But pain seizes him again. Then he faints.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="72">
            <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
            <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
            <loc>By the river Pruth Waag</loc>
            <!-- Is "Waag" the title? On the pdf this word is located on the far left of the page and its bolded although unlike the other titles it doesnt specifically say "title" -->
            <dir type="stg"> The river flows majestically through the immense plain. The scenery is
               bathed in sunshine. All is peaceful. Then a large raf t appear s around a bend in the
               river and gloats slowly into view. Boatmen with long poles are pushing it with
               considerable effort. At the stern a high pile of boxes. Black, coffin like boxes.
               Stacked into a pyramid. An uncanny sight. Indefatigably, the boatmen go on punting
               The raf t is coming closer and closer - like doom.</dir>
            <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
         </scene>

         <title>End of Act I</title>
      </act>

      <act num="3">
         <title>Act III </title>
         <scene num="73">
            <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>  <title>A Budapest hospital</title>
            <loc>Hospital Ward</loc>
            <dir type="char"> A long line of white beds. In the foreground, Hutter. In bandages ...
               his eyes closed. The doctor comes to him now. He examines him. Questions the nurse
               She tells him about the case:</dir>  <title>He was brought in yesterday by
               Huzules who said he had fallen down a mountain. He is still feverish ...</title>
            <dir type="char">As the doctor continues his examination Hutter wakes up, opens his
               eyes. There is fear in his feverish look still. The nurse hurries up to him to hold
               him. Yet he crawls away to the end of the bed. Spreads out his hands to defend
               himself. Suddenly his eyes go dead. He collapses. His lips are murmuring something
               ... The doctor bends over to hear what he is saying. Hutter muttering to
               himself</dir>
            <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Doctor and nurse look at each other without understanding.</dir>
            <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="74">
            <cam dis="18">18 meters</cam>
            <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
            <loc>The port of Varna</loc>
            <dir type="stg">At the quayside, ready for loading, and next to other cargo the pile of
               black coffins. Custom officials are examining the lettering and papers. They are
               approaching the boxes. The man searches among the papers and hands over the freight
               letters to his boss. </dir>
            <cam>Close-up:</cam> Freight letter <!-- Do I label this as a direction or note? -->
            <dir type="stg">Mixed cargo, from Varna to Whitby
               <!-- had this as a note element before I tried to make the xml work 100% with the schema -->
               Content: garden soil for experimental pur poses. </dir>
            <cam>Normal shot:</cam>
            <dir type="char">The inspector smiles incredulously. He orders a search!! Barefooted
               dock-workers drag up one of the apparently very heavy boxes, heaving and swearing.
               The inspector gives an order. They open the lid with difficulty. There is earth
               inside! The inspector gives another order: turn it out! The workers obey. Sand is
               falling out nothing but earth . Satisfied, the inspector turns to another pile of
               cargo. Yet in the earth . . .something moves violently ...something is alive ...jumps
               out...horrible animals ...rats! One of the dock workers, who bends over to scoop the
               scatters earth back hits out violently. Did not one of the animals...reeling from the
               blow ... bite his foot? </dir>
            <cam>Long shot:</cam>
            <dir type="stg">The big hand pulley [steam crane] hauls up one of the boxes and drops it
               into the belly of the sailing-boat that is anchored at the quay. At the ship's stern
               one can discern a name, underneath the baroque figure head; DEMETER</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="75">
            <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>  <title> Professor Bulwer, a Paracelsian, explains
               the nature of carnivorous plants to his students</title>
            <loc>The institute</loc>
            <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Professor Bulwer, surrounded by a few students, quiet and simple
               people. They are listening to his lecture. Now he points emphatically to a plant with
               a very strange shape. </dir>
            <cam>Close-up</cam>: <dir type="stg"> A flower. Its petals reaching out like tentacles.
               Motionless. Now. And insect. Hovering, attracted by the scent . . . settles on the
               colorful calyx. There in a flash the tentacles have gripped it. The insect is caught.
               Its struggling is in vain. With irresistible force the flower has drawn it into the
               recesses of the calyx . . . </dir>
            <cam>Medium- close-up:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Bulwer pointing at the flower. Slowly his lips are moving:</dir> 
               <title> The patient who came in yesterday has had an attack. </title>
         </scene>
         <scene num="77">
            <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>
            <dir type="char">Lunatic's cell Sievers and the attendant stop short at the door way.
               Straining their eyes to see into the semi- darkness. There, in the corner. Something
               moves slowly. It is a man. Now his face is in the light. Like a panther preparing to
               leap, his ferocity re- strained, he raises himself up slowly. His crazed burning eyes
               staring at Sievers. And now we re- cognize him at last . . . it is Knock!!! Suddenly,
               in one leap, he is at the window. Sievers is startled, says something to the
               attendant. Who prepares the straitjacket be brought along. Yet the expected attack
               does not come. Knock remains at the window, arms jerking, he begins . . . to catch
               flies which he puts into his mouth. Horrible food. The madman's face twists into a
               grin that resembles distant lightning. His swollen lips are murmuring
               something:</dir>  <title>Blood is life! Blood is life!!!</title>
            <dir type="char"> Suddenly, the madman starts up and throws himself with all his might
               on the unsuspecting Sievers. Who can barely ward him off. But the attendant comes to
               his help quickly and throws the straightjacket over the raging man's head. </dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="78">
            <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
            <loc>The Institute:</loc>
            <dir type="char">Bulwer, in a quiet, scholarly manner with his students. He points to an
               aquarium.</dir>
            <cam>Close-up:</cam>
            <dir type="stg">On a piece of rock in the water hangs a small polyp. Now it stretches
               out its tentacles, grabs a small fish and pulls it up to its mouth. It is almost
               transparent, colorless and of a jelly-like consistency. </dir>  <title>And this
               one . . .a polyp with tentacles . . . transparent . . . almost incorporeal . . .
               almost a phantom . . . </title>
         </scene>
         <scene num="79">
            <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
            <loc>Lunatic's cell.</loc>
            <cam>Close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">On the floor, in his straitjacket, whining pitifully, mad Knock. His
               face. Turning his sad eyes upwards. He notices something there. His lips form a
               word:</dir>  <title> Spiders . . . !</title>
            <cam>Close-up:</cam>
            <dir type="stg">A spider-web with a live spider which clutches, vampire-like an insect
               and is sucking its blood.</dir>
            <cam>Normal:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Knock in exultation. Sievers stands motionless . . . does not
               understand. Brusquely, he gives an order and leaves. </dir>
            <cam>Fade-out.</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="80">
            <cam dis="4">4 meters</cam>
            <cam>Fade in. </cam>
            <loc>The graveyard of Whitby</loc>
            <dir type="stg">View from the pier-head towards the shore. In the fore- ground the
               surging sea. Further back, where the shore rises steeply, the graveyard of
               Whitby.</dir>
            <cam>Closer:</cam>
            <dir type="stg"> The graveyard. Afternoon light. In front of the graveyard a long row of
               benches. People are strolling up and down looking out on to the sea . . . sitting on
               the benches and enjoying the view.</dir>
            <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
            <dir type="char">A bench, somewhat apart from the others. Ellen is sitting there.
               Dreamily, her eyes searching a distant country beyond the sea. She seems to be in an
               anxious day- dream about her distant lover. Now she shuts her eyes, because tears are
               welling up.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="81">
            <cam dis="4">4 meters</cam>
            <title> Croquet?</title>
            <loc>In Harding's Park</loc>
            <dir type="char">Harding, youthful and athletic, is batting. The shuttlecock flies high
               up into the air. Anny, in a light dress, shouts with joy . . . catches it . . .
               throws it back. The shuttlecock flies backwards and forwards. It is a picture of
               health and light.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="82">
            <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam> A<loc>t the park gates.</loc>
            <dir type="char">The postman, a small old man, rummages in his leather bag and produces
               a letter which he hands with an air of importance to Harding's servant who is as old
               and wizened as he. Before he leaves, the post- man points to the stamp which seems to
               be of special value, lifting up his eyebrows: This letter has travelled ar . . . it
               comes from a very remote country. The two old men bend over the rare letter. Then the
               old servant takes it in.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="83">
            <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
            <loc>In the park</loc>
            <dir type="char">As the servant approaches. Harding and Anny stop playing. Anny takes
               the letter, reads the address and runs to her brother. It is for Ellen, she says,
               point- ing into the distance. Shall we take it to her straight away. Harding agrees,
               they hand their rackets over to the ser- and walk off.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="84">
            <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
            <loc>At the graveyard</loc>
            <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Ellen is still sitting there, looking over the vast waters, lost in her
               sad longing thoughts.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="85">
            <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
            <loc> Heligoland The sea</loc>
            <dir type="stg">Distant view over the sea. A sand bank skirted by rocks, jutting out
               into the surf waters.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="86">
            <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>
            <loc>At the graveyard.</loc>
            <dir type="char">Harding and Anny are approaching. They are joining the lonely Ellen.
               shak- ing hands and trying to cheer her up. Guess what we have brought you! They show
               her the letter. Ellen trembles. She takes the letter quickly and tries to open it! I
               cannot do it. Gladly and quickly, Anny takes over. You'll see, he is safe and sound
               and sends you good news. She starts to read it gives a joyful laugh, she was right.
               All is well. The worries were unfounded Happily she gives Ellen the letter. But
               barely has she read the letter when Ellen's face assumes an expression of hurt
               certainty. Does she derive evil premonitions from these lines? </dir>
            <cam>Close up:</cam>
            <dir type="stg"> letter.</dir>
            <!-- This section is from a note although the note element doesnt work. Will discuss with group next meeting -->
            <dir type="stg"> the mosquitoes are a real pest. I have been stung on the neck by two at
               once, very close together, one on each side . . .</dir>
            <cam>Normal:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Ellen's face is distorted as if she were suffering physical pain.
               Harding and Anny are perplexed. </dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="87">  <title>GALAZ</title>
            <loc>The port of Galaz at night.</loc>
            <dir type="stg"> The 'Demeter' is anchored off the jetty. Nobody is about on the quay. A
               stormy night, strange uncertain light. Sud- denly - a gentle movement from the ship
               down the gangway to the shore . . . rats . . .</dir>
            <cam>Fade-out: </cam>
            <dir type="stg">The coffins are reloaded</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="88">
            <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
            <loc>The hospital at Budapest</loc>
            <dir type="char">Hutter, dressed, stands in front of his bed. He looks pale and weak
               still, yet full of resolution. The nurse notices his unsteady stance. She fusses
               around him. You ought to stay a few more days! Have some more rest! But he wards her
               off. His gestures are restless and fluttering, a strange force has taken possession
               of him.</dir>  <title> I have to get home by the shortest possible way!
               !</title>
            <dir type="char"> So he says goodbye, disregarding the nurse's advice, thanks her for
               her care and goes out quickly. </dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="89">  <title>Constantinople</title>
            <loc>The port. Night.</loc>
            <dir type="stg">Wild dogs are barking from the debris in the street up to the distant
               firmament, writhing in the mud like snakes.</dir>
            <cam>Focus on quay:</cam>
            <dir type="stg">The "Demeter" at anchor. What's scuttling over there? . . . A shadow
               from the ship to the land . . . rats. . . one. . . four. . . ten . . . and endless
               stream . . .the carry terror with them.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="90">
            <cam dis="8">8 meters </cam>
            <loc> Polnischer Kamm Non-stop rain Entry to the Vratna Gorge</loc>  <title> In
               the Hungarian plain.</title>
            <dir type="stg">Coach station in the Pusta The mail coach is arriving at top speed. The
               coachman whips his exhausted horses into a last effort. The coach has barely stopped
               when Hutter jumps off. He calls for more speed. Now fresh horses are being brought
               along. Hutter joins the grooms and tells them to hurry on! To hurry on! The tired
               horses have been taken out of harness and are being led to the stable. Bring fresh
               horses! Hutter gives a helping hand. Now the straps are done up. The coachman blows
               his horn. Some late-comers appear. They get into the coach. Hutter is the last. And
               the heavy coach rumbles off, the horses gallop- ing, sparks flying from the hooves,
               dust rising, into the pathless country.</dir>
            <cam>Fade- out. </cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter leads a limping horse through </dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="91">
            <cam>Fade-in:</cam>
            <loc>The port of Constantiople </loc>
            <cam>Long shot.</cam>
            <dir type="stg"> In a fresh breeze, the "Demeter" emerges from the confusion of
               mast-heads and gains the open sea.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="92">
            <cam dis="15">15 meters</cam>
            <loc>Lunatic's cell </loc>
            <dir type="char">In a stupor, Knock is perching on his bunk. The attendant holding a
               broom, is about to leave the cell. At this moment Knock lifts his eyes. With a look
               of artful cunning and with rigid concentration he follows the attendant's movements.
               Now, he seems to have discovered an opportunity; softly, he sneaks up on the
               unsuspecting man and takes away the newspaper that sticks out of his pocket. The
               attendant does not notice and shuts the door behind him. The moment Knock is alone he
               unfolds the paper trembling with expectancy and starts read- ing. searching for
               something with wide-open eyes. Now he has found what he was looking for. He is
               riveted to this passage. </dir>
            <cam>Close-up:</cam>
            <title>The Newspaper</title>
            <!-- I changed this from note to title mainly because the note element does not work. I could change the schema myself but I'd rather do that as a group -->
            <dir type="stg"> PLAGUE
               <!-- Also not sure if the title of the newspaper should be labled as a title? I assume not but might as well ask the question -->
               In Transyvania and in the Black Sear ports of Varna and Galaz a plague epidemic has
               started. Young women in particular fall victim to it in large numbers. All the
               victims show the same peculiar wound marks on the neck whose origin is still an
               enigma to the Doctors The Dardenelles have been closed to all ships sus- pected of
               carrying the epidemic. It is out of the question that the epidemic will reach Western
               Europe.</dir>
            <cam>Medium close-up: </cam>
            <dir type="char">Knock's mocking, triumphant face assumes an expression of demonic
               grandeur. He straightens himself up, lifts up his head, raises his arms as if
               greeting the evil. </dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="93">
            <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
            <loc>North Sea</loc>  <title>Open Sea</title>
            <dir type="stg"> The Mediterranean. In the distance the "Demeter" sailing through the
               waters gleaming in the even- ing light. </dir>
            <cam>Dissolve. Medium close-up</cam>
            <loc> The ship's deck</loc>
            <dir type="char"> The ship's mate is running up the companion-way in great agitation and
               crosses the deck on his way to the captain's cabin. </dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="94">
            <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
            <dir type="stg">In the captain's cabin The captain of the 'Demeter' bent over maps,
               making en- tries in the log-book. The mater enters and reports excitedly: </dir>
             <title> Below deck a sailor has fallen ill. He is talking in a fever.</title>
            <dir type="char"> The captan looks up, shocked. He leaves his work and fol- low the
               mate.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="95">
            <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>
            <loc>Below deck.</loc>
            <dir type="stg"> In the background the ship's hold. Among other cargo in the deep
               darkness the coffins. To be seen through an open door. In the foreground the crew's
               cabin with hammocks In one of them the delirious sailor. </dir>
            <cam>Medium Close-up: </cam>
            <dir type="char">Captain and mate go up to the patient who stares at them as if they
               were ghosts. He seems to listen intently. Every noise makes him start. Shot of hold
               Brooding, intense darkness. The lid of one of the coffins seems to open a little. </dir>
            <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
            <dir type="char"> The captain, more angry than concerned, advises the patient in his
               uncouth sailor's way to have a strong drink. Promptly the mate produces his bottle
               and give it to the patient. The smell seems to wake him up from his lethargy and he
               takes a long sip. The captain tells him to have a good rest and goes out again with
               the mate. The sailor alone. His eyes wandering . . . Suddenly, they remain fixed, as
               if spellbound, on the door leading to the hold. In horror he sits up and remains in a
               crouching position as if turned to stone. Pan to the door lead- ing into the hold.
               There, horrible and awe-inspiring, stands NOSFERATU And . . . he . . .
               approaches.</dir>
            <cam>Fade out</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="96">
            <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
            <loc>Hornunger Moor Lünebur ger Heide</loc>
            <dir type="stg">Wild and desolate scenery In the distance a galloping horseman on the
               plain. He comes closer and closer . . . moving at tremendous speed. It is Hutter. </dir>
            <cam>Dissolve</cam>
            <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter, standing near his horse and examining its injured hoof. With a
               desper ate gesture, he lets go of it. Yet he has made his decision. He must go on. He
               takes the horse by the reins and walks on, dragging the limping animal after him.
            </dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="97">
            <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>  <title>The gulf of Biscay</title>
            <loc>On deck, the 'Demeter' Evening.</loc>
            <dir type="char">In the last light of the sun captain and mate are about to push the
               shrouded corpse of the last sailor over the railing. They have covered their mouths
               and noses with cloths for protection.</dir>
            <cam>Shot of ship's side </cam>
            <dir type="char">The corpse is slid down into the water by ropes. On deck. For a moment
               the two last survivors pause in quiet contem- plation of the horror of death.
               Suddenly, the mate's body stiffens, he has made a resolution. For a short moment, he
               shuts his eyes and tries to master the horror that is rising up inside him. Then he
               pulls himself together, tears the cloth off his face, takes up an axe and,
               brandishing it in the air,</dir>
            <cam> calls out:</cam>
            <!-- I assume this is describing a camera shot? -->  <title> I'm going down!!! If
               I haven't come back in ten minutes . . .</title>
            <dir type="char"> With the courage of a desperate man he hurries over to the
               companion-way. </dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="98">
            <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>
            <loc>Below deck. </loc>
            <dir type="char">There are the black boxes. They are the man's target. He lifts his axe
               at the first one and shatters its lid. There it is: He is tempted to retreat. Rats!
               All round his ankles he feels the crawling of horrible creatures. Yet he pulls
               himself together for a second time. Another box, smashed by a second blow. And the
               same thing happens again: rats! only rats! He is wading through wriggling bodies
               which surround him from all sides. Yet he withstands the horror. There, a third box. </dir>
            <cam>Close-up:</cam>
            <dir type="char">The mate. In despair, foaming at the lips, he prepares for the third
               blow.</dir>
            <cam>Long shot:</cam>
            <dir type="char"> The axe falls from his hand. His hair is standing on end. Quick as
               lightning NOSFERATU rears up from the box. Now the mate is finally overcome by horror
               . . . Covering his eyes with his hands he runs upstairs, crazy with fear. Slowly and
               steadily, NOSFERATU is approaching. </dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="99">
            <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam>
            <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
            <loc>On deck </loc>
            <dir type="char">The captain is guarding the helm. Then from the hatch, the mate emerges
               . . . his hair has turned grey . . . his face looks crazed . . . he is foaming at the
               mouth . . trying to escape. . . he sways . . .turns deliriously in a circle . .
               .loses his sense of direction. . .does not see the railing. . . and overshoots it.
               Falling head first. The captain watches in horror. Now he is lef t all alone. But his
               face remains determined. He picks up a rope and ties himself to the helm, not to be
               tempted to leave. Thus he awaits the horror. . . </dir>
            <cam>Fade out. </cam>
         </scene>
         <title>End of Act I</title>
      </act>
      <act num="5">
         <title>ACT IV </title>
         <scene num="100">
            <cam dis="5">5 meters </cam>
            <loc> Heligoland</loc>
            <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
            <loc>A cliff by the coast Night</loc><dir type="stg">, roaring surf. The storm is
               howling. A gigantic wave moves up, breaks the water splashes high up.</dir>
            <dir type="stg">Moving coach</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="101">
            <cam dis="5">5 meters</cam>
            <cam>Anny's room. Night.</cam>
            <dir type="char">Anny is asleep. The storm is pushing against the windows, opening them.
               The curtain is billowing and fluttering in the wind. Anny wakes up. Confused,
               Terrified, she jumps up. She tries to shut the win- dow, yet cannot bring herself to
               do it. The storm is pushing her back . . . she recoils. She runs out of the
               room.</dir>
            <!--   Im seperating these directions due to the large gap in text-->
            <dir type="char">Waves Ellen Anny wakes up Carriage Ellen walking forward Waves Carriage
               Hutter Anny wakes up Waves Ellen Anny Boat</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="102">
            <cam dis="3">3 meters</cam>
            <loc>Ellen's room at the Hardings </loc>
            <dir type="stg">The storm is sweeping through the open window. The bed is empty . . .
               Anny enters. She knows at once what has happened, - rushes out.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="103">
            <cam dis="4">4 meters</cam>
            <loc>Roof of Harding's mansion</loc>
            <dir type="char"> Ellen, her clothes fluttering in the wind, her hair like a flag, is
               sleeping in the storm. She stretches out her arms defensively. A white figure
               against the black night sky. </dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="104"> XXXXXXXXXX <!-- I feel as if we talked about this but at the moment I cant recall on the solution we came up with for this so im leaving it blank until further notice -->
            <dir type="char">(placement text) </dir>
            <!-- this is simply a placement text and will be removed once I figure out what to do for this -->
         </scene>
         <scene num="105">
            <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
            <loc> Contre jour North Sea</loc>
            <dir type="stg"> High Sea. The storm is raging, enormous tidal waves . . . In the
               distance a sailing ship, the 'Demeter' at full sail, racing to its perdition.
               Trick</dir> <gapMk>(Scenes 106 and 107 are missing)</gapMk>
            <!--Again, im leaving this blank until we discuss it later-->
         </scene>
         <scene num="108">
            <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
            <loc>View across the town at night</loc>
            <dir type="stg"> The storm is tossing the trees. Sailing boat moving towards it
               objective .</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="109"> is missing <!--Same for this one-->
            <dir type="stg">(placement text)</dir>
            <!-- Another temporary text -->
         </scene>
         <scene num="110">
            <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>
            <loc> Wismar Sea</loc>
            <dir type="stg"> The storm rages violently. The sand bank threatens 'Demeter', the fatal
               ship, has closer, still moving at full speed. </dir>
            <cam>View from the sea towards the harbor.</cam>
            <dir type="char"> Sailing ships are coming in at full sail. Contre jour (wismar). Trick
               Ellen runs out from room Broken axle Ellen runs through garden Ship moves towards
               objective Knock 1 Ship coming into the harbor Hutter running street. Knock Ship in
               harbour. Nosferatu appears Hutter running through street Nosferatu through gate with
               coffin Door Hutter Knock escape Nosferatu square or street Room]</dir>
         </scene>
      </act>
   </script>
</root>
