<?xml-model href="../nosferatu_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
   <script>
      <head>
         <title>N O S F E R A T U</title> by Henrik Galeen <note> (F.W. Murnau's hand annotations
            and scenes additions and location markers are in Bold Print) </note>
      </head>
      <act num="1">
         <title>ACT 1</title>
         <scene><annot>8 meters location shot: Wismar</annot>
            <cam>Fade in.</cam>
            <loc>Townscape</loc>
            <cam>View over the roof's of a small old-fashioned town built in the style of the 1840s.
               The sun shines peacefully on pointed gables and leafy squares.</cam>
            <cam>Fade out</cam>
            <cam>Two shot, one from the church tower onto the town the other from the harbour over
               towards the town. 1st: view of Lübeck. Dissolve to harbour of Wismar</cam></scene>


         <scene num="23">
            <cam dis="4" sync="2">4 meters 2x</cam>
            <cam>Fade-in</cam>
            <loc>Outside a window</loc>
            <dir type="stg">There are flowers in green window-boxes. On the window sill a kitten is
               playing in the morning sun. With graceful movements she tries to catch a ball that
               dangles from a thread. Now the ball is being pulled in through the window. The cat
               jumps in af ter it.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="34">
            <loc>Ellen's sitting room</loc>
            <cam dis="7" sync="2">7 meters 2x</cam>
            <loc>Small neat kitchen</loc>
            <dir type="char">The morning sun casts the shadow of a window frame onto the floor.
               Ellen, by the window, is pulling the thread with the ball, the cat follows it with a
               leap. Then she puts the little animal on her arm. Playing with it she sits down on
               the window sill bathed in sunshine and looks out dreamily. She squats on the floor
               opposite the animal and plays with it. Her dressing gown moves in the breeze, her big
               child-like eyes a laughing.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="34" sub="a">
            <cam dis="20">20 meters</cam> <cost>Hutter white jabot blue waist coat.</cost> <loc>A small sitting
               room (attic)</loc>
            <dir type="char">Poor-looking and tidy. A bed, a chair in the period style. Hutter is
               standing in front of the mirror. He is about to put his jack- et on. He pauses to
               listen, takes a look through the side window. Smiling happily he finishes dressing
               and goes out.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="4" sub="a">
            <loc>A small flower garden</loc>
            <cam>Shot from above.</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter appears, gardening knife in hand, looks up front of Hutter's
               house beaming with joy. He finds a clump of carn- ations, cuts the flowers with a
               quick gesture and makes a bouquet.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="5">
            <loc>The small kitchen</loc>
            <dir type="char">Ellen, still playing with the kitten, hears Hutter coming and jumps
               up.</dir>
            <cam>Shot of cooker</cam>
            <dir type="char">Ellen comes over and begins to busy herself with the sauce pans, with a
               childlike earnestness towards her house-wifely duties.</dir>
            <cam>Shot of door:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter is standing in the doorway and laughs and laughs. Hiding the
               bouquet behind his back, he laughs and laughs</dir>
            <cam>Shot of cooker</cam>
            <dir type="char">Ellen turns around, catches sight of her husband and seems a little
               ashamed that she hasn't yet made breakfast. Now Hutter moves closer to her, looks
               into the sauce pan holds it upside down indicating that it is empty, and looks at her
               reproachfully.</dir>  <title>Ellen!</title>
            <dir type="char">She is sulking now and trying to placate him. But he pulls out his
               watch; it is late already; he has to go. He kisses her good-bye, but she calls him
               back again to confess that she hasn't got any money left to do the shopping. He pulls
               out his purse with a sad look and holds it up: there is nothing in it! They both
               sigh. He leaves with a heavy heart. The moment she is alone she takes a small basket
               of potatoes, which is all she can find, the last resort of the poor house-wife, and
               starts peeling them. A potato drops on the floor, the kitten comes up and plays with
               it.</dir>
            <cam>Fade-out</cam>
            <dir type="char">They are rushing towards each other, Ellen throws herself into Hutter's
               arms</dir>
            <cam>Long Shot</cam>
            <dir type="char">He produces the bouquet, hands it to her beaming all over his face. She
               is touched then, saddening, she takes the glowers looking at the stems and stroking
               them. His voice asks for the reasons of her behavior she says:</dir>  <title>Why
               have you killed them ... the beautiful flowers?</title>
            <dir type="char">Hutter is taken aback for a moment. He apologizes and kisses her. Then
               she forgives him, they stand in an embrace.</dir>
            <cam sync="2">Fade-out 2x</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="5" sub="a">
            <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
            <loc>Lauenburg</loc>
            <cam>Fade in</cam>
            <loc>Street with front gardens</loc>  <title>Professor Bulwer</title>
            <dir type="char">Professor Bulwer is walking vigorously, yet slowly along the road,
               enjoying the morning and the sunshine. His stick strikes the ground energetically.
               Suddenly he stops and turns around. Who is following him in such haste? Isn't it
               Hutter? He grasps the passing man by his sleeve; he holds on to it. Hutter greets
               him, looking pleased. Bulwer laughs and looking deep into his eyes says:</dir> 
               <title>Why so hasty , my young friend? One reaches one's goal soon enough.</title>
            <dir type="char">Hutter, of course, doesn't understand him. He has to get to office
               quickly. He greets him again and again. Until he manages at last to break free with a
               laugh and rushes off. Bulwer stands there for a moment, then he resumes the regular
               rhythm of his walk.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="6">
            <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam> <title>Caption: Knock - a house agent</title> <cam>Fade-in</cam>
            <loc>Dusty cramped office</loc>
            <dir type="stg">Pale light is falling through tiny blind window-panes into the strange
               room which is eccentrically decorated with bits of old-fashioned furniture. KNOCK is
               standing at a high desk. People call him a house agent.</dir>
            <cam>Close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">Knock's spindly hunch-backed figure. Grey hair, weather- beaten face
               full of wrinkles. Around his mouth throbs the ugly tic of the epileptic. In his eyes
               burns a sombre fire. He is reading a letter.</dir>
            <cam>Close-up The letter. On a sheet of paper decorated on the margin with grotesque
               vignettes a medley of intricate and quite ill- egible signs.</cam>
            <cam>Med. Close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">Knock seems to be able to make sense of the strange letter, for his
               ugly mouth sets into an understanding smile. Then he turns and opens the door.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="7">
            <cam dis="5">5 meters</cam>
            <loc>Small room ad- joining the office</loc>
            <dir type="char">Very narrow and dark, totally without sun. Hutter, buried in files.
               Knock looks through the door and calls him in.</dir>
            <annot>Another clerk is present</annot>
         </scene>
         <scene num="8">
            <cam dis="30">30 meters</cam>
            <loc>The dusty and cramped office</loc>
            <dir type="char">Knock and Hutter enter. Knock points to the letter with mysterious
               gestures and tells Hutter: </dir>  <title>Count Orlock - His grace - From
               Transylvania wants to buy a beautiful house in our little Town</title>
            <cam>Close-up Knock's demonic face with wide open eyes</cam>  <title>You could make
               a nice bit of money . . . It will take some effort, however . . . a few drops of
               sweat and blood. . . Perhaps a little blood .</title>
            <cam>Closeup</cam>
            <dir type="char">In Hutter's face expressions of mounting joy and strange apprehension
               are fighting each other. Yet joy wins in the end.</dir>
            <cam>Long shot</cam>
            <dir type="char">Knock digs up and old atlas from the depths of the cabinet and opens
               it. His finger runs over a page.</dir>
            <cam>Closeup The route from England to Transyvania on the map.</cam>
            <cam>Long shot</cam>
            <dir type="char">Transylvania? asks Hutter, his eyes suddenly shin- ing at the thought
               of a journey. Yet Knock has turned back to the letter, now reading the last
               page.</dir>
            <cam>Closeup The back page of the letter, covered with the same illegible
               squiggles.</cam>
            <cam>Long shot</cam>
            <dir type="char">Knock seems to be able to make sense of this page too. He turns back to
               Hutter who is al- ready day-dreaming about his journey.</dir>  <title>He wants a
               handsome deserted house.</title>
            <cam>Long shot</cam>
            <dir type="char">For a moment Knock is lost in thought, then he has an idea. He limps
               over to the window.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="9">
            <cam dis="4">4 meters Window frame, take in Knock</cam>
            <loc>Section of window View down the street The deserted house. A dilapidated facade.
               Black and hollow windows. Not a sign of life. Shadows on it.</loc>
            <time>Daytime - Sun</time>
         </scene>
         <scene num="10">
            <cam dis="15">15 meters</cam>
            <loc>The dusty and cramped office</loc>
            <dir type="char">Knock walks back from the window and says to Hutter:</dir> 
               <title>That house...just opposite yours. Offer him that!</title>
            <dir type="char">Hutter seems to be a little taken aback, but he rallies around quickly.
               Knock urges him to set out on the journey at once, hands him some money and doc-
               uments and pushes him to the door.</dir>
            <cam>Fade-out</cam>
            <cam dis="18" sync="2">18 meters 2x As in scene 8</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="11"><loc>Room in Hutter's House</loc>
            <dir type="char">Ellen is sitting by the window. Now she can see him coming. She waves
               to him. Her face lights up with joy. She hurries over to the door. Presently Hutter
               enters. Moved and happy, he puts his arms around her and tells her his great
               news:</dir>  <title>I shall go on a journey far far away to the country of
               mountains where there are bandits and ghosts still.</title>
            <dir type="char"> Ellen is startled. A shadow passes over her forehead. She wants to
               hold him back. But he is not listening. He has got to pack; already he is leaving
               her.</dir>
            <cam>Fade-out</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="12">
            <cam dis="15">15 meters</cam><cost>Frau Schroeder without shawl saddlebags</cost><loc>The attic
               room</loc>
            <cam>Fade-in</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter is packing his little travelling bag. Ellen appears in the door
               behind him. Sud- denly she starts to beg him tearfully, en- treating: Do not go! I am
               worried about you! But he rejects her remonstrations. Now he has finished packing. He
               gets up. Ellen realizing that he has made up his mind steps back, resigning herself.
               But there is fear in her eyes. Seeing her like this he hes- itates for a moment. But
               then he embraces her again with determination, takes up his bag and leaves the room
               with her.</dir>
            <cam>Fade out</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="13">
            <cam>15 meters</cam>
            <loc>(Lord)Harding's park</loc>
            <dir type="char">Hutter, all ready for the journey, takes his leave from Harding and his
               sister Anny. Ellen, weeping is supported by Anny.</dir>
            <cam>Close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">The two men. Hutter, taking both of Harding's hands and looking deep
               into his eyes:</dir>  <title>I entrust Ellen to your care.</title> <dir type="char">Harding
            promises his friend to look after Ellen, she can live here, she will never be alone.</dir>
               <cam>Long shot of all characters</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter gives his hand to Anny and then to Ellen One last farewell kiss.
               At this moment her grief is over. As if she had a premonition she says:</dir> 
               <title>Farewell! There is no escape left.</title>
            <dir type="char"> At first they are all startled by these words. Then Hutter breaks
               away. Another farewell, another wave of the hand and Hutter vanishes into the park.
               Ellen is staring vacantly into the distance.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="14">
            <loc>Square with fountain</loc>
            <dir type="char">A number of healthy-looking people are walking about in the sunshine.
               Tied to the fountain a lonely sattled horse. Hutter appears, mounts the horse gives
               one last backward look and gallops off.</dir>
            <cam>Fade out</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="15">
            <cam dis="9">9 meters Schlesische Hutte</cam>  <title>The Carpathian Mountains Wild
               and rocky mountains. Contre jour</title>
            <cam>Fade-out</cam>
            <time>Evening</time>
         </scene>
         <scene num="16">
            <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
            <cam>Long shot</cam>
            <loc>Outside the Carpathian inn.</loc>
            <dir type="stg">The big mail coach drawn by four horses drives up and comes to a
               halt.</dir>
            <cam>Shot of door of inn</cam>
            <dir type="char">The inn-keeper, a small old Jew, comes out and sees the coach.</dir>
            <cam>Shot of coach:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter jumps out first. He looks around.</dir>
            <cam>Long shot:</cam>
            <dir type="stg">The house. One part of brick-walled living area, the other coach house
               and open stables Shot of coach In the meantime the other passengers have got out.
               Long-haired, black Huzules. All identically dressed and of identical appearance like
               ghosts. they go into the house. The inn-keeper has gone up to Hutter and greets him
               with an inviting gesture.</dir>
            <cam>Shot of coach</cam>
            <dir type="stg">The horses are now unharnessed, the coach is being pushed into the coach
               house. Night is falling.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="17">
            <cam dis="8">8 meters</cam> <dir type="char">servant: Frau Kurz</dir> <loc>Inside the Inn.</loc>
            <dir type="char">A large smoky room with an enormous tiled stove. A central hanging lamp
               throws out dazzling light At tables in the background the passengers. Hutter who came
               in last, is standing in the foreground, he looks around and sits down right in front.
               At once the old servant approaches with a glass and puts it down in front of him. He
               overcomes a strange anxiety that was brought on by the evening mood in a strange
               country and puts on a sudden show of liveliness. He knocks on the table and
               says:</dir>  <title>Quickly, my meal - I must be off to Count Orlock's
               castle.</title>
            <dir type="char">The servant recoils in horror. The strangely identical looking
               passengers, sitting in the background rise up abruptly to stare at him.</dir>
            <cam>Shot of bar</cam>
            <dir type="char">The old hunch-backed Jew pricks up his ears.</dir>
            <cam>Long shot</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter looks around in embarrassment, then takes up his glass
               resolutely and downs it in one gulp.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="18">
            <cam dis="4">4 meters</cam> <loc>Walddorfsenke</loc> <loc>A grassy slope behind the inn</loc>
            <dir type="stg">The ground falls away towards the back. Night mists are creeping up from
               the valley. The horses are put out here to graze. Suddenly, they raise their heads,
               as if frightened and, scattering, gallop away.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="19">
            <loc>Inside the inn</loc>
            <cam>Shot of window:</cam>
            <dir type="char">The passengers, seen from behind are standing by the win- dow, looking
               out apprehensively. The old servant has not go the courage to go up to where they
               stand and makes the sign of the cross. Hutter stands alone, looking around. He is
               perplexed and wants to ask what is happening. The old servant comes up to him and
               whispers into his ear.</dir>  <title>You mustn't go there now there are wolves
               about Spend the night here.</title>
            <dir type="char">Hutter understands and decides to stay.</dir>
            <cam>Fade-out19a</cam>
            <dir type="stg">Horses, panicking</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="20">
            <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam>
            <loc>A room at the inn.</loc>
            <dir type="char">A tiny white-washed room with sharp angles: a flickering light from the
               old servant's candle. Now Hutter enters. She puts the candle down, goes out without a
               word. Her eyes expressing concern for him. Hutter alone. He goes over to the window,
               throws it open and looks into the starless night.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="21">
            <annot>(missing from script)</annot>
         </scene>
         <scene num="22">
            <cam dis="5">5 meters</cam>
            <loc>Inside the inn</loc>
            <dir type="char">The pale passengers, now without Hutter in the enormous room, look
               frightened. They, too, are listening to the hor- rible howling. They look at each
               other and are crossing themselves in terror!</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="23">
            <cam dis="20">20 meters</cam>
            <loc>The tiny white-washed room</loc>
            <dir type="char">In the light of the candle Hutter, shivering, closes the win- dow. He
               is no longer sleepy. He walks up and down the room restlessly, stopping in front of a
               little bookcase.</dir>
            <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">Looking for something to distract him Hutter pulls out a book at
               random.</dir>
            <cam>Long shot</cam>
            <dir type="char">He moves back to the candle, sits down on his bed and opens the book.
               He gets interested in it.</dir>
            <cam>Close up The book's title page: VAMPIRE</cam>
            <dir type="stg">The page os being turned over.</dir> <title>THE NOSFERATU From the bloody sins
            of mankind a creature will be born which will seek revenge for the sin committed by the
            parents and visited on their children and children's children. Whosoever lusts after
            blood without reason in under his spell, the spell of the vampire NOSFERATU.</title> <cam>Shot
               of bed Close-up </cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter, shaking his head, continues reading Book:...grown up on his
               native soil - from which alone he draws his power.</dir>
            <dir type="char">Hutter shuts the book, having lost interest. It seems confused to him.
               He yawns and puts out the candle.</dir>
            <cam>Fade-out</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="24">
            <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam>
            <cam>Fade-in</cam>
            <loc>Small white room at the inn</loc>
            <dir type="char">Morning sun is flooding in from the window. Hutter wakes up. Yawning
               like someone who has slept deeply but not well. He sits up rubbing his eyes. They
               fall on the book on the bedside table. He reads the title</dir>
            <cam>Close-up VAMPIRE</cam>
            <cam>Normal shot:</cam>
            <dir type="char">spits on the floor in contempt of the confused rubbish and throws the
               book playfully into a corner. Then he pauses to listen, goes over to the window to
               open it. He takes a deep breath of the morning air.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="25">
            <cam dis="6">6 meters</cam> <loc>Walddorf</loc> <dir type="stg">The grassy slope in the morning
               light. Coachmen and grooms are rounding up the horses with long whips and lots of
               shout- ing.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="26">
            <cam dis="5">5 meters</cam>
            <loc>The small room</loc>
            <dir type="char">Hutter steps back from the window. His eyes are laughing, as he turns
               round. He stretches himself happily; then he takes off his shirt, goes over to the
               washstand, pours water over his body. He has a proper wash.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="27"> <loc>Dolny Kubin</loc> <loc>In the yard</loc>
            <dir type="char">The old servant, mother to all animals, throws corn to her chickens.
               There are sparrows, too. Everything is bathed in sunlight.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="28">
            <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam>
            <loc>Outside the Inn</loc>
            <dir type="stg">The bustle of departure. The horses are in harness. The passengers have
               got into the coach. Now, in the morning light, one can see their differences. They
               are much less uni- form than they had seemed the previous nightfall. They are
               chattering noisily to the people who are staying be- hind and with the peasants and
               nosy children who are gathered around the coach.</dir>
            <cam>Close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">The coachman is about to climb onto his seat, but the small Jewish
               inn-keeper holds him back: one passenger is missing. They look up to the windows;
               angry about the delay the coachman cracks his whip a few times.</dir>
            <cam>Shot of inn:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter appears in an upstairs window, still only half dressed; he gives
               a wave: I am coming. And disappears again.</dir>
            <cam>Shot of door</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter comes rushing out with his travelling bag.</dir>
            <cam>Shot of coach</cam>
            <dir type="char">He climbs to his seat on the coach-box, the horses start moving.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="29">
            <loc>Outside the inn</loc>
            <dir type="char">The Huzules take off their hats. The children are waving. The old
               servant has joined them. God bless the travellers. May he guard them against evil
               spirits. They stretch out their hands as if warding them off.</dir>
            <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter breaks into loud laughter.</dir>
            <cam>Fade-out</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="30">
            <cam dis="12">12 meters</cam> <loc>Westerheim</loc> <loc>A Mountain range</loc>
            <cam>Long-range shot</cam>
            <dir type="stg">In the distance a steep path cutting through the wild scenery, on it the
               mail coach creeping slowly upwards.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="31">
            <cam dis="10">10 meters</cam> <loc>road to the Schlesische Hütte</loc> <loc>The mail coach</loc>
            <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
            <dir type="stg">The mail coach is moving into the setting sun</dir>
            <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">A coach window, and old woman. Hutter leans out, giving the coachman a
               push with an umbrella</dir>  <title>Drive on!</title>
            <time>The sun is setting</time>
            <dir type="char">Next to her another old woman, identical looking She is staring into
               the abyss. Now the first one turns to look in the same direction: two identical
               faces.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="32">
            <cam dis="4">4 meters View from Schlesische Hütte</cam>
            <loc>The rocky gorge</loc>
            <dir type="stg">Wisps of mist are rising and falling in the last rays of the setting
               sun. Patches of sun and shade</dir>
            <cam>Fade-out</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="33">
            <cam dis="10">10 meters Close to Arler Hütte</cam>  <title>At the crossroad</title>
            <dir type="char">A carved madonna casts a long shadow across the road. Behind it an old
               woman on her knees, deep in prayer. She lifts her head and looks down the road. The
               mail coach approaches, the horses are pulling with difficulty, breathing hard. She
               seems to ask herself: do they want to drive to the haunted castle? and gets into the
               middle of the road to warn them off. The mail coach stops. Hutter gets off the coach
               box. Now he stands at the crossroad. The passengers are anxious to move on gesturing
               violently to him not to take the left fork. But Hutter disregards their shouting He
               waves farewell with his hat and walks briskly off.</dir><dir type="char">Hutter
               walking past the carved madonna</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="34">
            <cam dis="8">8 meters Vratna Pass</cam>
            <loc>Distant mountains</loc>
            <dir type="stg">View through the cut made into the rock by the road into the far
               distance. In the background the fantastic castle of Count Orlok in the evening light.
               One can see a steep road leading straight up into the sky. Something comes racing
               down. A coach? A phantom? It moves with unearthly speed and disappears behind a
               ground swell.</dir>
            <loc>1) Castle Orlok</loc> <cam>dissolve</cam>
            <loc>2) Steep road between boulders</loc>
         </scene>
         <scene num="35">
            <cam dis="4">4 meters Near Schlesische Hütte</cam>
            <loc>At the crossroad</loc>
            <cam>Angle as in Scene 33</cam>
            <dir type="char">Mortally fightened, the coachman beats the horses. The old woman has
               disappeared as if swallowed up by the ground. Astonished, Hutter follows the
               vanishing coach with his eyes. He is all alone now, standing like this for a while.
               Then he pulls himself together and walks resoltuely along the road on the left.</dir>
            <cam>Fade-out</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="36">
            <cam>Vratna Pass</cam>
            <cam>Fade-in</cam>
            <loc>Carpathian virgin forest.</loc>
            <dir type="char">The trees are castling long shadows on the forest path. Hutter appears.
               He halts: what's that? Some- thing comes racing up, turns around as if moved by a
               hidden force and moving jerkily. Stops dead. Hutter likewise. A black carriage. No
               wheels? Two black horses - griffins? Their legs are invisible, covered by a black
               funeral cloth. Their eyes like pointed stars. Puffs of steam from their open mouths,
               re- vealing white teeth. The coachman is wrapped up in black cloth. His face pale as
               death. His eyes are staring at Hutter. Raising his whip he makes an inviting, almost
               commanding gesture. He waits. Hutter cannot r ally enough strength to follow the
               invitation. Yet those eyes assert their power. Step by step, as if pulled by
               invisible threads, Hutter approaches the uncanny creature. He gets into the carriage.
               It reverses quick as lightning, dashes off a disappears.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="37">
            <cam dis="5">5 meters At the Vratna Pass, behind Tyer Hora</cam>
            <loc>A fairy-tale forest</loc>
            <dir type="char">Empty. By the roadside a wise, man-sized raven. Its shoulders hunched
               up. It turns its head listening. Then takes two hops forward and looks down the road.
               Who's coming? The familiar vehicle sweeps up and past. A young man, holding on
               desperately, sits inside, looking terrified. The raven follow him with mocking eyes
               behind glasses.</dir>
            <dir type="stg">Coach drives at top speed through a white forest</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="38">
            <cam dis="5">5 meters Long shot of a snake- like bend.</cam>
            <dir type="stg">Valley. Deserted lane. Only a lonely twisted will-tree with a straggly
               top can be seen. Again the carriage races past. Like an ancient man who has been
               disturbed in his rest the tree looks after the vehicle with blank eyes. Isn't there a
               grin on its mouth? Drives over stone bridge across deep gorge</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="39">
            <cam dis="15">15 meters Poczamok</cam>
            <loc>Count Orlock's castle</loc>
            <dir type="stg"> The arch of a gate in the shade. The silhouette of the carriage drives
               underneath it at a sharp angle and disappears in the moonlit spacious castle
               yard.</dir>
            <cam>Shot of castle yard</cam>
            <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">The porch. The carriage stops in front of it. Al -most in a faint,
               Hutter slides down. As if in a whirlpool, the carriage circles round him and
               disappears. Hutter turns around and follows it with his eyes. He stands in front of
               the closed gate, holding his bag.</dir><dir type="char">Then, very very slowly
               the two wings of the gate open up. Somewhere far back in the dark corridor a man can
               be seen standing motionless. He is holding a candle which lights up his chalk-white
               face. He is waiting. Who is that? Hutter bounds up the two steps and stands in the
               doorway. He would still like to go back. Yet it is too late now. Hesitantly he walks
               towards the stranger. Behind him the gate closes</dir>
         </scene>
         <title>End of Act 1</title>
      </act>
      <act num="2">
         <title>Act II </title>
         <scene num="40">
            <loc>Hall.</loc>
            <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">In the center Orlok, the candle in his hand. The walls of the hall are
               plunged in darkness from which Hutter's back emerges. He faces the mot- ionless
               figure. It is pale, ghostly creature with hollow eyes and thin mouth the lord of the
               cas- tle himself?</dir>
            <cam>Close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">The face twists into a polite grimace. Sharp r atlike teach appear over
               the lower lip.</dir>
            <cam>Medium Close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">They are now face to face. It must be the count for this is no
               servant's gesture with which he now takes hold of his visitor's bag.</dir> 
               <title>The servants are asleep It is almost after midnight.</title>
            <dir type="char">Hutter's clenched fingers let go. Bag in hand, Orlok turns around. He
               holds up the candle and walks ahead. Hutter follows.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="41">
            <loc>Gallery of ancestor's portraits</loc>
            <cam>Medium Close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">One of the castle owner's ancestors , frontal view. For centuries he
               has been asleep like this with his eyes closed. Now something approaches. His eyes
               begin to move. Two figures are passing: Orlok and his visitor.</dir>
            <cam>Long shot panorama</cam>
            <dir type="char">He follows them with his eyes. They walk close to the wall where
               portrait follows portrait.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="42">
            <cam dis="25">25 meters</cam>
            <loc>Dining room.</loc>
            <dir type="char">Gigantic dimensions. In the center a massive Renaissance table.
               Somewhere in the distance a fire place. Flanked by two armoured figures. Black and
               motionless. In older times this must have been used by knights for their drinking
               bouts. Are these their armour? Is that long line that runs across the wall a crack in
               the old structure? Or a lance left hanging there? Suddenly, Hutter notices that the
               count is waiting. Quickly he hands him the plans of the deserted house and Knock's
               letters. With a smile Orlok takes them and begs him to take a seat. The meal is
               waiting. Hutter sits down. Orlok lifts up the papers and studies them.</dir>
            <cam>Close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">Orlok reading. The back page of the letter shows a con- fusion of
               numbers, legible and illegible letters. The holy number seven is repeated several
               times. In between, cab- balistic signs. The spindly fingers holding the letter cover
               up the rest like claws.</dir>
            <cam>Close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter is spell bound, his eyes wide-open</dir>
            <cam>Closeup</cam>
            <dir type="char">Over the top margin of the letter Orlok's eyes appear. He is looking
               over to Hutter like a snake about to hypnotize it's victim.</dir>
            <cam>Close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter eating. He puts a morsel into his mouth. He lifts up his eyes.
               His look turns into a stare. He is unable to swallow</dir>
            <cam>Long shot</cam>
            <dir type="stg">The hall with the halo of light in the center; the figures are looming
               above the table.</dir>
            <cam>Close-up</cam>
            <dir type="stg">An antique clock with a pendulum. A hammer strikes the hour. The big
               hand points to 12 o'clock.</dir>
            <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter staring into space as if transfixed. After the twelfth stroke he
               drops his knife and fork. The knife grazes his hand, it is bleeding.</dir>
            <cam>Medium Close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">Quick as lightning the count rushes up to him offering his help. He
               prevents Hutter from wiping off the blood. The knife might have been poisoned The
               sticky blood should be removed from the cut. His lips are sucking at the hand
               hastily. Frightened, Hutter pulls away his hand from his grip. He moves backwards
               towards the fireplace.</dir>
            <cam>Medium Close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">By the fireplace. The Count is polite; he has lost his ghostlike
               appearance. He is asking for something in a friendly, almost sad manner.</dir> 
               <title>Shall we stay up together for a little while? It's a long time to go till
               sunrise . . . And during the day I am always out and about.</title>
            <dir type="char">The Count sits down. And Hutter cannot resist his chivalrous manner. He
               sinks back into the massive chair.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="43">
            <cam dis="18">18 meters</cam>
            <cam>Fade-in</cam>
            <loc>The same hall</loc>
            <dir type="char">Hutter wakes up in the large armchair near the fireplace. He can hardly
               remember the events of the night. The armchair opposite seems to be empty. But there
               is light on it. Hutter's gaze wanders across the hall over to the window.</dir>
            <cam>Shot of window It is very high and divided up into small panes. Morning light is
               streaming in.</cam>
            <cam>Shot as before</cam>
            <dir type="char">An old-fashioned window. An ancient hall, very dusty. Nothing strange
               about it. Hutter yawns. His eyes fall on the cut in his hand and he remembers a few
               more things. What has he got on his neck? He touches his throat. Must have been
               mosquitoes. A mirror! His bag is nearby on the floor. He takes out his mirror and
               looks at his neck.</dir>
            <cam>Close-up The mirror shows two red spots on his neck, very close together.</cam>
            <cam>Normal close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">Why should he worry about a few little spots? he thinks and puts the
               mirror away. He yawns once more. But suddenly he stops. What's this? He looks at the
               table, astonished.</dir>
            <cam>Close up: A still-life of food: fruit, a joint, all kinds of gastronomic
               delicacies.</cam>
            <cam>Normal:</cam>
            <dir type="char">He is overjoyed. He rushes over to the table and begins to eat as if he
               were starved.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="44">
            <cam dis="22">22 meters Poczamok</cam>
            <loc>The dilapidated terrace</loc>
            <dir type="char">Still eating, Hutter steps out into the sunlight. He looks around,
               seeming relaxed. He holds a sheet of paper and a pencil in his hands. Then he casts
               about for a suit- able place and, leaning against the stone wall He begins to write a
               letter.</dir>
            <cam>Close-up:</cam> <title>The beginning of the letter: My dearest, my only one. . .</title>
               <cam>Normal:</cam>
            <dir type="char"> Hutter stands upright, looking at the clouds. Why does that stupid
               mosquito buzzing around his nose stop him from concentrating? He catches it quickly.
               And now he knows how to continue. He puts pencil to paper again.</dir>
            <cam>Close-up:</cam> <title>Part of the letter:...the mosquitoes are a real pest. I have been
            stung at the next by two at once, very close to- gether, one on each side...</title> <cam>Long
               shot:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter keeps writing</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="45">
            <cam dis="14">14 meters Poczamok</cam>
            <loc>Forest near the castle</loc>
            <dir type="char">A man on horseback is approaching. He stops occasionally and peers over
               to the castle as if he were scared of it.</dir>
            <cam>Outside the porch:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter stands there, waving with the letter. The rider comes up
               cautiously and takes the letter without dismounting The he dashes off at a gallop
               showing signs of great fear.</dir>
         </scene>
         <scene num="46">
            <cam dis="15">15 meters</cam>
            <cam>Fade-in.</cam>
            <loc>Dining room</loc>
            <dir type="char">Orlok is sitting by the fireplace bent over some plans. Hutter is
               standing behind him. Orlok shows more interest in the young man than in the papers
               lying in front of him. Looking over his shoulder he asks for some more information.
               Hutter rummages among the papers in his bag. A little picture falls on the table. He
               wants to hide it quickly, yet Orlok was quicker. He has picked it up and is looking
               at it.</dir>
            <cam>Close up A miniature portrait of Ellen.</cam>
            <cam>Medium close-up</cam>
            <dir type="char">Orlock asks about the person in the picture. And Hutter is forced to
               answer him.</dir>
            <cam>Close up:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Orlok's eyes open wide. His lips look even thinner than before.
               Contemplating the picture he whispers:</dir>  <title>What a beautiful throat
               your wife has...</title>
            <cam>Medium close-up:</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter is breathing hard. The fear which grips him in the count's
               presence is replaced by a sudden fear for his wife. He forgets himself and reaches for the miniature. 
               For the first time he touches Orlok's body. The count jumps
               up. He raises himself to his full height with triumphant determination and a glazed
               look in his eyes, and says, anticipating the horrors to come with pleasure.</dir>
             <title>I shall buy the house... The handsome deserted house opposite
               yours.</title>
            <dir type="char">Quickly, he takes up the contract and signs it. He hands it back to
               Hutter. Hutter bows uneasily and retires. Orlok watches him go, a satanic look has
               come into his eyes. His hands have turned into claws. Hutter takes his bag with
               him</dir>
            <cam>Fade- out:</cam>
         </scene>
         <scene num="47">
            <cam dis="15">15 meters</cam>
            <cam>Fade-in: Candle is burning</cam>
            <loc>A small room in castle</loc>
            <dir type="char">Hutter is standing in the middle of the room, quite dazed. He shakes
               off his misgivings. He decides to leave tomorrow. He kisses the picture and starts
               to undress, when to his amazement he discovers a book in his pocket. The old book
               from the inn. Did the inn-keepers wife put it there? Mechanically, he opens it.</dir>
            <cam>Close-up: The book</cam> <title>Chapter II Night is the vampire's element. He can see in
            the dark which is a wonderful ability to have in this world half of which is night. We
            humans, however, are helpless and blind at night</title> <cam>Normal</cam>
            <dir type="char">Hutter shuts the book. A horrible thought has occurred to him. He is
               feverish. Is it this book, these ancient walls which make him believe in the
               existence of ghosts? Did not the count seem to have vampire-like claws and rat's
               teeth. He jumps up, first running, the sneaking to the door.</dir>
         </scene>
      </act>
   </script>
</root>
